<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>INFRAPATELLAR BURSITIS</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Alchemy in motion</source>
  <url>https://www.alchemyinmotion.com.au/case-studies/sports-musculoskeletal-case-studies/infrapatellar-bursitis-case-study/</url>
  <parent_folder>Knee</parent_folder>
  <section>
    INFRAPATELLAR BURSITIS CASE STUDY
    <paragraph>This case study explores an interesting presentation we had through the clinic recently.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    How they presented / Mechanism of Injury:
    <list>
      <item>Patient present with inflammation below the knee cap.</item>
      <item>Patient reported day prior to swelling, they increased repetitive lunging and kneeling intermittently for approx. 3hrs. Interestingly patient had no pain.</item>
      <item>He reported he had noticed the knee swell up over the hours post kneeling/lunging but was not in pain.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Self management between time of injury &amp; presenting:
    <list>
      <item>He had iced his knee but the swelling had not gone down.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Assessment:
    <list>
      <item>Squat: pain free to 90 degrees</item>
      <item>Single leg stand: pain free 30sec</item>
      <item>Single leg Squat: pain free</item>
      <item>Lunge: NAD</item>
      <item>Jump x10: NAD</item>
      <item>Hop x10: NAD</item>
      <item>Knee Active range of motion: Flexion 95 degrees nil pain but swelling limits AROM. Ext NAD</item>
      <item>Patella glides stiff but pain free even with compression.</item>
      <item>Palpation: Nil Tenderness patella tendon or quads tendon.</item>
      <item>Ligament + meniscus tests: negative</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph/>
    <image src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="/>
    <image src="https://www.alchemyinmotion.com.au/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Infrapatellar-Bursitis-Case-Study-1024x770.png"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Impression / Diagnosis:
    <list>
      <item>Infrapatellar bursitis</item>
      <item>To confirm the diagnosis, we sent the patient for an ultrasound which he had the following day.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Treatment:
    <list>
      <item>Soft tissue massage on quadriceps and hip flexors allowed the patient to regain an additional 10 degrees of knee flexion taking him to 105 degrees.</item>
      <item>We also released his glutes as he had reduced hip external rotation on his affected side – this allowed him to regain full passive range of motion in his hip</item>
      <item>Fitted patient with tubigrip (compression sock) to help reduce swelling</item>
      <item>Education re: benefits of trialling 3-5 days of oral anti-inflammatories to see if swelling subsided.</item>
      <item>Educated patient on importance of avoiding kneeling, lunging, deep squatting and prolonged sitting in short term until swelling subsided.</item>
      <item>We then referred patient back to the GP to have the bursa drained two weeks later as the swelling was not reducing with conservative management.Patient had bursa drained and also had a cortisone injection into bursa at the same time.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Home Exercise Programme:
    <list>
      <item>Gradual increase in quads strength and Single leg control over approx. 6weeks. Including:SquatsSeated knee extensionSingle Leg balanceSide planksSingle leg bridgesDeadlifts</item>
      <item>Squats</item>
      <item>Seated knee extension</item>
      <item>Single Leg balance</item>
      <item>Side planks</item>
      <item>Single leg bridges</item>
      <item>Deadlifts</item>
      <item>We then progressed to:Bulgarian split squatsArabesquesLunges</item>
      <item>Bulgarian split squats</item>
      <item>Arabesques</item>
      <item>Lunges</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Squats</item>
      <item>Seated knee extension</item>
      <item>Single Leg balance</item>
      <item>Side planks</item>
      <item>Single leg bridges</item>
      <item>Deadlifts</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Bulgarian split squats</item>
      <item>Arabesques</item>
      <item>Lunges</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome:
    <paragraph>Over the following two weeks post injection the bursa slowly reduced in size and the patient regained full range of motion. With gradual re-introduction to exercise, the patient is now back to normal activities with no restrictions.</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
