<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Knee Pain</title>
  <source>PT Case Study extracted from Capital Area Physical Therapy &amp; Wellness</source>
  <url>https://capitalareapt.com/case-study-physical-therapy-knee-pain/</url>
  <parent_folder>Knee</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Capital Area PT Case Study: Knee Pain
    <paragraph>In this case study you will see how physical therapy can resolve knee pain that didn’t really have much to do with the knee at all!</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    History
    <paragraph>A 36 year old man presented to PT with complaints of inner knee pain which began suddenly after lifting a large box. Since onset of his pain, he had not been able to run or exercise at his local high intensity training gym and experienced pain with stairs, walking, and rolling in bed. He reported occasional “giving out” of his knee. X-ray of the knee was negative.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Evaluation
    <paragraph>At the patient’s first visit, a variety of objective measurements were taken to assess his baseline function and assist the therapist in building an individualized plan of care. Some of these measurements included:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>He was asked to demonstrate some of the exercises he does at the gym, such as planks, squats, and lunges.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Limitations such as gluteal strength,core activation, and foot muscle engagement and motor control were apparent in isolation and during complex movement patterns.Squat formwas impaired with excessive forward trunk lean, toeing out, and knees caving in. He displayed significant limitations of ankle dorsiflexion range of motion and his hamstrings and hip flexors were very tight. His psoas muscle, a hip flexor, displayed excessive tone and limited active gluteal engagement and hip extension.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Treatment
    <paragraph>The last sessions integrated running form, agility work, jumping, and safe return to full gym classes with reduced risk of injury. The patient endedtherapy with no pain in his kneeat rest or with activity, improved motor control during exercise, and independence with a home exercise program he could integrate into his gym warm up. He plans to continue his stretching program to see long term flexibility changes.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Consideration
    <paragraph>Not many “basic knee exercises” were used for this patient. He described very rapid (within only 1-2 sessions) improvement in knee pain with stretches implemented at his hips and ankles and motor re-education at his core and glutes. *Just because that is the area of pain, doesn’t mean that is the problem area. If other areas don’t do their job correctly, then something must take up the slack. In this case, the knee was crying out for help because of dysfunction at the joints above and below!</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For more information on this case study, physical therapy for management ofknee or hip pain, or to make an appointment for an evaluation or treatment, contact us at one of ourtwo physical therapy clinicsin Malta and Queensbury NY.</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
