<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Knee Case Study Week 3 Subjective</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Knee_Case_Study_Week_3_Subjective</url>
  <parent_folder>Knee</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Referral
    <paragraph>14 year old boy called James has bilateral knee pain right worse than left worsening over the last 12 months</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Subjective:</section>
  <section>
    History of Presenting Condition
    <paragraph>12 month history of bilateral knee pain. James initially started to notice pain in his right knee after doing sport, he would find that it ached quite a lot, but the next morning it would be pain free again. Approximately 3 months after he started to notice that both knees would be hurting after he had played a football game or done a physical education session at school.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>His mother took him to the doctors 6 months ago and was diagnoses with normal ‘growing pains’ and was advised that this would pass. His knee pain has now become so painful that he really struggles to do any form of physical activity, therefore his mother took him back to the doctor who has now referred him to Physiotherapy.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Presenting Condition</section>
  <section>
    Past Medical History
    <paragraph>Nil no childhood illnesses, has grown from 4 foot 10” to 5 foot 8” in the last 12 months</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Drug History
    <paragraph>Paracetamol PRN</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Social History
    <paragraph>At school, enjoys PE and maths, plays for a local football academy and the local football team. He trains Tuesday and Thursday evenings with the academy and a Wednesday evening with the school team. His school games are on a Monday evening and academy games are on a Saturday and his local team have games on a Sunday. He plays in goal and has no substitute. He is hoping to become a professional football player.</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
