<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Total Knee Replacement</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Witty, Pask &amp; Buckingham</source>
  <url>https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/case-studies/total-knee-replacement-due-to-osteoarthritis/</url>
  <parent_folder>Knee</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Total Knee Replacement
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/knee_osteoarthritis1.jpg"/>
    <paragraph>History</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A 54-year-old recently retired firefighter attended for treatment, assessment and advice regarding his long-standing knee pain.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>In the past, he had undergone multipleknee jointinjections and arthroscopic (Keyhole) surgery to repair tornmenisci(cartilage) in both knees.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>He had seen many physiotherapists over the years and essentially felt that until recently he was managing his symptoms independently. He has no other medical issues other than mild hypertension and he runs a Karate club, training up to 4 times per week.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Over the preceding year, his functional ability had declined to have an impact on his daily life and sport. He wanted to enjoy his recent retirement with his wife and grandchildren.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>His most recent visit to an Orthopaedic surgeon had concluded that he was finally ‘old enough’ to undergo aTotal Knee Replacement.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ref.1 describes research that shows that a TKR ‘resulted in greater pain relief and functional improvement after 12 months than did nonsurgical treatment alone.’</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ref 2 NHS guidelines on the 108,713 knee replacements in the UK in 2016 state that you will be offered a knee replacement if:</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>You have severe pain, swelling and stiffness in your knee joint and your mobility is reduced</item>
      <item>Your knee pain is so severe that it interferes with your quality of life and sleep</item>
      <item>Everyday tasks, such as shopping or getting out of the bath, are difficult or impossible</item>
      <item>You’re feeling depressed because of the pain and lack of mobility</item>
      <item>You can’t work or have a normal social life</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>SUBJECTIVE for our patient</paragraph>
    <paragraph>OBJECTIVE for our patient</paragraph>
    <paragraph>IMPRESSION</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Moderate to severeOsteoarthritisin the left knee with likely underlying meniscal damage/degenerative change.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For more specifics regarding an arthritic joint – see Pasky’s“wear and tear” case study.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>TREATMENT</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Pre-habilitationx 3 sessions over a period of 6 weeks</paragraph>
    <paragraph>* Nb. All within the patient’s pain tolerance levels</paragraph>
    <paragraph>We also discussed what was likely to happen when in hospital, checked he was ok with his basic quads exercises as the hospital physio would be around quite soon after surgery to start mobilisation! We practised the use of elbow crutches both on the flat and also up and down stairs.</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/Picture1-306x236.jpg"/>
    <paragraph>Postoperative– 2 weeks after surgery. Weekly appts for the first 3 weeks</paragraph>
    <paragraph>By 2 months post-op, he was swimming regularly and needed no further physiotherapy input.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>By 3 months post-op, he was walking up to 3 miles</paragraph>
    <paragraph>By 6 months post-op, he was cycling past 6 miles</paragraph>
    <paragraph>By 12 months post-op, he had forgotten about his ‘new’ knee !!</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Thoughts</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The prospect of a Total Knee Replacement surgery is scary but talking it through with and having treatment from your physiotherapist can allay fears, provide clever hints and tips and even make you stronger to maximize and improve the speed of your recovery. The results are excellent in most cases. – See ref 3.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Keith Allen Shirtcliffe</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ref 1Total knee replacement outcomes</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ref 2NHS guidelines on total knee replacement</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ref 3Total knee replacement is highly effective for pain and function</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/themes/wpb2017/images/footer-logos.jpg"/>
  </section>

</document>
