<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Amputation secondary to Diabetes Mellitus</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Amputation_secondary_to_Diabetes_Mellitus:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Amputation secondary to Diabetes Mellitus: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Amputation Secondary to Diabetes Mellitus</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Amputation is the surgical removal of a limb due to complications associated with disease or trauma. There are two main categories in which amputees are grouped: Traumatic and non-traumatic. Diabetes Mellitus (DM) is one of many causes of non-traumatic amputation. Engstrom and Van de Ven (1999)[1]defines DM as a systemic disorder in which blood glucose may be intermittently raised above the normal range. In the United States (US) studies have shown that DM is the leading cause of non-traumatic Lower Extremity Amputation (LEA). Hence, treating these patients requires knowledge of the condition</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>Transtibial, Non-traumatic, Lower Extremity Amputation, Diabetes Mellitus, Secondary, Rehabilitation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>55 years old Male, recently hospitalized for elective surgery where he underwent a transtibial amputation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Past Medical History</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Vascular investigations:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medication:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Present Medical History:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Social History:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>ICF Table</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Pathology: Transtibial Amputaion</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Body structure and function:1. Integumentary system- Poor skin condition and surgical wound2. Somatosensory system- Impaired sensation and pain3. Cardiopulmonary system- Decrease endurance4. Musculoskeletal system- Decrease Range of motion and strength, Dependent ambulation5. Neuromuscular system- Impaired balance6. Psychological Issues- Depress</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Activity Limitation:1. Unable to ADLs such as cooking, washing, going to the shop and showering2. Unable to ambulate independently3. Unable to have sex</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Participation Restriction:1. Unable to work as construction worker2. Unable to take care of his common law wife and children along with grandchildren</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Contextual Factors:Personal: Positive- 1. Good family and friends supportNegative- 1. Poor financial status2. Unemployed3. Patient has several co-morbidities such as DM and HTN4. Patient is depressed and has history of smoking and drinkingEnvironmental:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Positive-</paragraph>
    <paragraph>1. Access to free health care2. Nil steps at home and flat terrain</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Negative-</paragraph>
    <paragraph>1. Lives in 2-bedroom board house with no modern conveniences</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Based on the clinical examination done the clients main problems are as follows:1. Pain2. Decrease Range of motion and muscle strength for bilateral lower extremity3. Poor balance- short sitting dynamic, standing static and dynamic4. Decrease endurance5. Impaired sensation6. Depressed</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>There were four main goals that were establish in order to guide the treatment sessions:1. Prevent complications2. Manage the wound and stump3. Restore mobility and independence4. Manage pain and to begin to think about discharge</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The treatment modalities (Interventions) used were:1. Education and teaching of both patient and family about the following- DM, Skin care and sensory deficits</paragraph>
    <paragraph>2. Pain Management with the use of TENS and Ice</paragraph>
    <paragraph>3. Stump Management- a.Teaching of Desensitizing techniques which included end weight bearing and the use of different materials such as cotton b.Scar Mx patient taught massage c.Shaping of stump using elastic bandage d. Wounding healing was addresses with UV to increase healing process</paragraph>
    <paragraph>4. Patient Positioning- Proper sleeping and sitting positions were explained to patient such as not to cross legs when sitting or put pillow under knee</paragraph>
    <paragraph>5. Exercise therapy- a.strength training, ROM exercises, functional activity training and general conditioning b.Transfers, balance training- sit to stand exercises, sitting on therapeutic ball with nil assist and standing in parallel bars with hands then to no handsc.Throwing and cathching exercises in sitting and standing d. Ambulation with assistive device such as walker and then progressed to crutches</paragraph>
    <paragraph>6. Pre-gait training- a.Orientation to the center of gravity and base of support b.single leg standing c. Stepping over and around obstacles</paragraph>
    <paragraph>7. Patient referred to a Councillor</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Intervention 1: (Patient education)- Patient demonstrated that he could manage his sensory deficit along with skin care management effectively</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Intervention 2: Patient reported having decreased pain throughout treatment sessions and rated pain as 0/10 NRS</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Intervention 3: (Stump Management)- Patient demonstrated he was able to manage his stump appropriately and had decreased sensitivity, oedema and the scar tissue was mobile and wound healed</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Intervention 4: (Patient Positioning)- Due to the fact that patient was taught proper positioning, common problems such as muscle tightness and contractors did not develop</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Intervention 5: (Exercise Therapy)- It was observed over the weeks of treatment, that the patient regain normal range of motion. He had increase in muscle strength for bilateral lower extremity, trunk and maintain normal upper extremity strength</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Patient's balance and coordination also improved, that is sitting and standing static and dynamic balance improved. Patient also showed improvements in endurance and ADL's such as carrying objects while walking and picking up objects from the floor</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Finally, patient's physiological status improved, he was now hopeful and looking towards the future.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Diabetes based on studies done, have shown to make up 60% of all non-traumatic LEA. Hence, majority of the patients a Physiotherapist will see for amputee rehab have diabetes. It is therefore important for the physiotherapist working with such patients to have a good understanding of the condition in order to rehabilitate these patience successfully. Additionally, the rehabilitation process should not only focus on the amputated limb, however the rehab should also focus on the sound limb. In the article entitled risk of re-amputation in diabetic patients, stratified by limb and level of amputation: 10 year observation. It was found that the risk of amputation is greater in diabetics with the rate of major amputation of the contralateral limb is 11.6% at 1 year and 53.3% at 5 years. In the case presented the patient had a number of issues, all of which were addressed through strategies for range of motion, strength, balance, coordination, agility and endurance. Safety should also be a number 1 priority for the physiotherapist, as their healing rates are slower than non-diabetics which puts then at risk of significant post-operative complications. Safety goals should take 2 main forms; A- prevent injuries due to falls and B- prevent damaged to the sound limb by reducing abnormal stresses. Ir should be noted that use of crutches for a diabetic amputee may place them at increased risk of fall and injury of their intact limb. It is recommended that a walker be used instead.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[2][3]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Engstrom B, Ven CVd. Therapy for Amputees. 3rd Edition. Churchill Livingstone. London. 1999</item>
      <item>↑Izumi Y, Satterfield K, Lee S. Harkless L. Risk of Reamputation in Diabetic Patients Stratified by Limb and Level of Amputation: 10-year obeservation. 2006; 29 (3):566-570</item>
      <item>↑CDC reports finds large decline in lower-limb amputations among US adults with diagnosed diabetes 2012</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
</document>
