<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Amputee Case Presentation - The Diabetic Amputee</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Amputee_Case_Presentation_-_The_Diabetic_Amputee:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Amputee Case Presentation - The Diabetic Amputee: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Amputee Case Presentation- The Diabetic Amputee</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Mr. S is a 62 year-old male 2 weeks post Left BKA who was discharged home from hospital with Rehab in the Home (RITH). RITH is an early supported discharge program, and he was referred for physiotherapy, occupational therapy and social work. He usually lives alone, but his brother is staying temporarily on discharge to assist. I am seeing him at home for physiotherapy in his pre-prosthetic stage of rehabilitation. The goals were to maximize independence and safety within the home environment prior to being seen in the outpatient amputee clinic in 3 weeks time.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>transtibial, early supported discharge,diabetes, physiotherapy</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Client Characteristics</section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Subjective- Main complaints are reduced independence (I) with ADLs, transfers and mobility. C/o pain and increased sensitivity at end of stump. Patient goals- To be as independent as possible at home with minimal assistance required from family and support services, including (I) with transfers and ambulation with ECs. OCM: TUG- 27 seconds with ECs, Lawton's ADL - 16/30</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Objective:  Bed Mobility: Independent Sit-Stand: Independent Standing Balance: Able to stand with supervision for 10 seconds Transfers: with stand-by assist x 1, Floor: 1 x modA Ambulation: (I) with ZF. SBA x 1 with Elbow Crutches Wheelchair: (I) on flat surfaces. s/v over ramp. Power- LL- (L) Gr 3+/5 Left Knee F/E, Hip F/E and Add/Abd (R) Gr 4+/5 Globally LL, UL- (L) + (R) UL Globally 5/5. Good hand dexterity Sensation- Intact, some increased sensitivity at end of stump</paragraph>
    <paragraph>ICF: Body Functions and Structures: (L) BKA- transtibial Impairments: Reduced standing balance, reduced LL and core strength, reduced endurance, reduced mobility, and increased pain. Activity Limitations: Independent with w/chair on flat surfaces but requiring supervision over threshold, Requiring 1 x A to transfer, 1 x A to ambulate with Elbow Crutches, Assistance required for domestic tasks and community transport. Participation Restrictions: Reduced work capacity and unable to drive Environmental Factors: Temporary support from brother staying. Stress present as partner unable to assist currently as waiting for visa</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>My clinical evaluation of Mr. S's main problem is reduced independence due to reduced mobility post amputation. He has reduced strength, balance and endurance, and pain from the stump. He is also at increased risk of falls, which increases risk of damage to his stump. His is very motivated to improve, but also likely to engage in risk taking decisions, and unlikely to cease smoking, which could adversely affect his rehabilitation.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>2 wks of RITH at home including:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>After 2 weeks of RITH intervention at home, Mr. S improved significantly with his transfers and mobility.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Mr. S improved significantly in the 2 weeks post discharge from hospital with rehabilitation in the home. We were able to assist with the transition home, and maximize independence in the home environment, enabling an effective early supported discharge. Mr. S's mood improved significantly on discharge home, as he was able to leave hospital but continue his rehabilitation in the home environment.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Whilst there is much evidence to support early supported discharge programs in mild-moderate stroke population[3], there is definitely a role in the amputee population to assist with this transition home, where these services are available. The challenges with Mr. S where that whilst he was very motivated to be as independent as possible, he initially was reluctant to take on education to reduce risk of falls and wait for supervision to ambulate when not yet independent. A fall on day 3-post discharge from hospital increased his receptiveness to falls prevention education.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Falls prevention is important in the amputee population to reduce incidence of future falls, to ensure reduced risk of injury and to maintain quality of life. Quality of life has been shown to be reduced with increased number of falls with amputees in the community[4]. The benefits of staying on a frame were discussed, but Mr. S was insistent on continuing to ambulate with elbow crutches. Mr. S was very keen for a prosthesis, which will be reviewed in the amputee outpatient clinic</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <paragraph/>
    <list>
      <item>↑Gaily RS, Clark CR.Physical therapy management of adult lower-limb amputees. In: Michael, JW editor. Atlas of Limb Prosthetics: Surgical, Prosthetic, and Rehabilitation Principles. Rosemont, IL, American Academy of Orthopedic Surgeons,1992.</item>
      <item>↑Lusardi MM, Postoperative and preprosthetic care. In Lusardi, MM, Jorge, M and Nielsen, CC editors. Orthotics and Prosthetics in Rehabilitation, Third Edition. Missouri: Elsevier, 2013.p. 532-59</item>
      <item>↑Hofsted H, Naess H, Moe-Nilssen R and Skouen J. Early supported discharge after stroke in Bergen (ESD Stroke Bergen): a randomized controlled trial comparing rehabilitation in a day unit or in the patients' homes with conventional treatment. International Journal of Stroke (2013) 8: 582-587</item>
      <item>↑Hordacre B, Barr C, Crotty M. Community activity and participation are reduced in transtibial amputee fallers: a wearable technology study . BMJ Innov 2015;1:10-16</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
