<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Case study of Rehabilitation of High Above knee Amputation in young adolescent patient</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Case_study_of_Rehabilitation_of_High_Above_knee_Amputation_in_young_adolescent_patient:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Case study of Rehabilitation of High Above knee Amputation in young adolescent patient: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Case study of Rehabilitation of High Above knee Amputation in young adolescent patient</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Case study of the rehabilitation of (Rt) high above knee amputation of a young adolescent patient following road traffic accident, because of short stump a double socket with TES belt is prescribed to increase the leverage and reduce the energy expenditure during ambulation along with multi axial knee joint with dynamic foot prosthesis is prescribed.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>High above knee, short stump, double socket, total contact, moderate pain in the stump.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Young Saudi male high school student of 18 years of age referred to our Physical medicine and rehabilitation center for prosthetic rehabilitation from the central hospital of our region with a diagnosis of right above knee amputation. High above knee amputation was done a month ago following a road traffic cacident, which lead to crushing injury to right lower limb.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>There is no relevant past medical history, apparently young, healthy man on bilateral axillary crutches with present complains of moderate pain in the stump. During his hospital stay inpatient physiotherapy were given to him, which include stump positioning, education on stump care and ROM exercises and strengthening exercises were taught.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Objective Assessment:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>This amputee has short stump along with the physical problem includes overacting of hip flexors and abductors and weak Adductors. The environmental problem includes being a right-sided amputee limits his ability to drive the car and goes to school. Emotional problem, he is too shy to go to school using axillary crutches.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Interdisciplinary meeting was held where the patient too was present and the findings were discussed and decided to give above knee prosthesis With the specification of Ischial weight bearing total contact double socket for energy conservation, multi axial knee joint and dynamic foot is prescribed as the patient being a young adolescent with good musculature around stump, the cast was taken on the same day.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Weekly 5 days patient attended physiotherapy department for 3 weeks the physiotherapy treatment includes:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Outcome</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Instead of conventional total contact socket, a total contact double socket were used for the prosthesis, as conventional total contact prosthesis has few disadvantages which includes:</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>difficulty in wearing the socket in a sitting position</item>
      <item>difficulty in obtaining a favourable disposition of the stump soft tissues in the socket</item>
      <item>difficulty in avoiding stump perspiration problems</item>
      <item>difficulty in modifying the socket shape according to the changes of the stump circumference</item>
      <item>difficulty in obtaining a comfortable fit</item>
      <item>weight</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>To over come this problem double socket using laminated polypropylene sheet were used for this prosthesis. Because of the reduced weight and ease in handling the internal socket, donning is easy in a standing or sitting position. The wearer can easily insert his stump into the internal socket and then into the external socket in one pushing motion.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>http://www.healthcare.uiowa.edu/igec/falls-prevention-toolkit/01- practice-fall-gait-assessment/assets/ABC-Scale.pdf</item>
      <item>http://www.physio-pedia.com/images/f/fa/AmpNoPro.pdf</item>
      <item>https://members.physio-pedia.com/open-ebooks/gailey-amputee-balance/</item>
      <item>http://www.oandplibrary.org/alp/chap27-01.asp</item>
      <item>http://www.oandplibrary.org/poi/pdf/1981_03_129.pdf</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
</document>
