<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Case presentation on a Left BKA</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Case_presentation_on_a_Left_BKA:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Case presentation on a Left BKA</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>A high level rehabilitation BKA who has been fitted and now wearing patellar tendon bearing socket prosthesis. Patient is independent in all activities of daily living has been receiving post prosthetic physiotherapy intervention. Thus far patient has been compliant with management and demonstrates a high level of competence.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>below knee amputation, phantom pain,, weakness,  prosthesis, high level rehabilitation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Patient X is a 26-year-old female who is a business student who was diagnosed with osteosarcoma of the left ankle and bilateral breast cancer. Patient has no known chronic illnesses had several chemo, surgical and physiotherapy management.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>The patient's main problems are phantom pain, difficulty walking for greater than five minutes and weakness in the left lower limb. The Phantom pain could be from the trauma that the patient received prior to amputation and excessive loading that is applied during walking and weakness and difficulty walking is due to decrease muscle strength in the left hip and knee muscles and endurance.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Patient to be seen 2 times per week.</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Education on residual limb care</item>
      <item>Stretching of bilateral knee flexors for 20 min with hot pack in place</item>
      <item>Bridging 3x10 reps with 5 seconds hold</item>
      <item>Bilateral SLR 3x10 reps</item>
      <item>Stationary bike cycling with resistance within patients tolerance for 15 min</item>
      <item>Hip flexion, extension, abduction, adduction exercises with thera-band using the Oxford regime</item>
      <item>Gait training in parallel bars with therapist giving approximation at the left hip to encourage weight acceptance and decrease hip hike.</item>
      <item>Stretching of knee flexors for 30 seconds 4x 10 reps</item>
      <item>Dynamic balance training</item>
      <item>Quads setting</item>
      <item>Mirror box therapy x 30 min</item>
      <item>TENS to the 2 electrodes placed below the left knee for 45 minutes -4Hz , 200ms</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>HEP: to be done 3 days per week</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Dance work out</item>
      <item>Bird-dog exercises 1x10 reps with 5seconds hold</item>
      <item>Massage to the residual limb</item>
      <item>Mirror therapy</item>
      <item>Pool activities- flutter kicks, pulsed hip adduction, abduction while reclining on a noodle.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Reaction to treatment tolerated well. Nil adverse effects, Patient demonstrates competence with her management.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>This patient can be considered a high-level rehabilitated left below knee amputee secondary to her been independent in activity of daily is motivated, cooperative and was very active prior to amputation and wants to get back to the level where she can participate in a one or two kilometers walk run competition. It is said that over time with prolong physiotherapy and home exercise programs as prescribed the patients energy expenditure should decrease and the level of participation increase[2].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>However, because this patient is experiencing phantom pain on long standing or walking for prolong periods. According, to Grumiller et al,[3]if there is increasing load this might intensifies the pain in the amputated limb this might impact on the patient's overall goal. Therefore, a training program should be specifically designed to improve this patient hip strength and thus resulting in sufficient improvement in prosthetic walkers to afford running, Nolan 2012 and this must be maintained to prevent regression and will then impact solely on how progression is done to achieve goals.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Collen FM Wade DT et al. The Rivermead Mobility Index: a further development of the Rivermead Motor Assessment. Int Disabil Studies. 1991; 13: 50-54.</item>
      <item>↑Takaaki, C et al. (2002). Physical fitness of lower limb amputees. Am J Med Rehabilitation. 81:321-325 Nolan L. (2009) Lower-limb strength in sports-active transtibial amputees. Prosthet Orthot Int. Sep; 33(3):230-41.</item>
      <item>↑Grummillier C, Martinet N, Paysant J, Andre JM and Beyaert C. (2008) Compensatory mechanism involving the hip joint of the intact limb during gait in unilateral trans-tibial. J Biomech. Oct; 41(14):2926-31.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
