<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>HIP TO BE COOL</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/HIP_TO_BE_COOL:_My_first_experience_with_a_hip_disarticulation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>HIP TO BE COOL: My first experience with a hip disarticulation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This case presentation is my first experience with a client with a hip dis-articulation. I have included her course of treatment from her surgery to walking out the door on her new prosthesis. A total of 5 months in the making. It was a long and difficult journey and she struggled with pain, immobility, and grief for the loss of her limb, but in the end she is now walking and much happier.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>hip dis-articulation, phantom pain, osteosarcoma, grief</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Jane Doe is a 61-year-old female who was diagnosed with osteosarcoma in her right leg in October of 2014. As a result, she underwent a hip dis-articulation Jan 23/2015.   Jane is otherwise very healthy with no other co-morbidities. She is a retired janitor. She is married and has 2 adult children. She is extremely active and her passion is running. Jane typically ran 10 km 3x/week.  The loss of her limb was VERY traumatic for her and she was devastated by this gross change in her mobility.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>After her amputation she was transferred to a rehab center in a hospital 160 km away from her home community. She did her pre-prosthetic training there and was discharged home to wait for her wound to heal Feb 24/15.  Jane returned to the amputee clinic to check the healing of her wound and assess her readiness for prosthetic training and she was casted for her limb March 19/15 She had her first fitting April 14/15 and her second fitting was April 23/15 She started prosthetic training May 25/15 as an inpatient at the same hospital rehab unit that did her pre-prosthetic training.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>She successfully walked out of the rehab unit July 3/15 with her new prothesis.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Jane's main problems on her pre-prosthetic admission were pain, weakness, poor mobility and balance, decreased function/ADL's and grief for her lost limb. On her second admission for prosthetic training her main problems were mild weakness, decreased mobility, no previous knowledge or understanding of how to use a prosthesis, and a sense of being a burden to her family/ how would she put meaning back into her life?</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>Outcome</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>In relation to my typical caseload Jane would be considered "high level rehabilitation". Simply because most of my clients are older and have many co-morbidities that limit their prosthetic outcomes. Jane luckily is only 61 and had no other illnesses. I was able to attain grade 5 for manual muscle testing on the left leg. She was also able to do advanced core stability training, which helped her better control the hip and knee joint on her prosthesis. For myself this was the first time I had the opportunity to work with a client that had a hip dis-articulation. The socket is actually a "bucket" that completely encases the pelvis. Very different from TF amputees. The limb has a Otto Bock components HIP: 7E7/ KNEE: 3R60 EBS and FOOT: Triton LP 1C63. Jane is also looking into switching to the C leg, which is a computerized knee down the road. The training we did for this prosthesis was fascinating. There is a great deal of pelvic tilt needed for getting the hip to release after midstance. Also loading of the toe leaver is critical to gain enough knee flexion to swing through well without vaulting. Luckily Jane has good kinesthetic sense and picked up on the necessary pelvic and trunk movements to control the hip and knee quite easily. Keeping up with her and managing to challenge her was fun. A fantastic learning experience for me.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.11.21.3The Academy TODAY 2009; Vol. 5, No. 1: pages 1-14,Stevens P et al, Clinically relevant outcome measures in orthotics and prosthetics.</item>
      <item>↑Adapted from The Lancet 2011;377:1693-702, Langhome P. et al, The international classification of function, disability and health framework for the effect of stroke on an individual.</item>
      <item>↑Veneri, D. and Lucarvic, J. (2012) Rehabilitation Manual for persons with above knee amputations. pages 40-60.</item>
      <item>↑Brooks, D et al (2001). The 2-minute walk test as a measure of functional improvement in persons with lower limb amputation. Archives of Physical Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation, 82, 1478-1483.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
