<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Hotel Worker, Lady Q Undergoes Transtibial Amputation but 'Gears up' for Prothesis and Rehabilitation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Hotel_Worker,_Lady_Q_Undergoes_Transtibial_Amputation_but_%27Gears_up%27_for_Prothesis_and_Rehabilitation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Hotel Worker, Lady Q Undergoes Transtibial Amputation but 'Gears up' for Prothesis and Rehabilitation: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Hotel Worker, Lady Q Undergoes Transtibial Amputation but 'Gears up' for Prothesis and Rehabilitation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>53 year old diabetic, Lady Q, a post-transtibial amputee, was gainfully employed in a hotel prior to amputation and is keen on returning to work. Post-op: she joined a smoking cessation, and an amputation support group, is compliant with medication, seeing a dietitian. She wishes to obtain prosthesis and is willing to work hard during post-amputation rehabilitation to ensure recovery.Considerations of Lady Q's health issues, psychological status and family/social support will help guide the process of pre- and post- prosthetics rehabilitation and reintegration into work and social environs.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>diabetic, transtibial, phantom limb pain, contacrture, endurance, rehabilitation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Lady Q, known Type 2 diabetic with a long history of smoking. Diagnosis of peripheral artery disease (PAD) several months ago lead to arteriosclerosis obliterans in the dorsalis pedis artery of her right leg. She was subsequently hospitalized with a chronic Fontaine’s stage IV foot ulcer and critical limb ischemia. After a revascularization attempt via percutaneous transluminal angioplasty (PTA), circulation was only marginally improved and she underwent transtibial amputation.Post-amputation she presents with: pain; phantom limb sensation; decreased strength, range of motion and balance; decreased skin integrity; decreased endurance and ability to walk and work and psychological issues.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination FIndings
    <paragraph>Subjective findings are any information reported by Lady Q, such as phantom limb pain, feelings in regard to her current condition, matters pertaining to her health status, home and social life. Inclusive of her goals of getting fitted with a prosthesis, being able to walk,to return to work and active social life.Objective findings are based on observation and measurements made by examiner/(PT).</paragraph>
    <paragraph>ICF Model:Body function/ structure</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Personal factors</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Environmental factors</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Client's main problems:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Multidisciplinary approach - Physicians, PT, Prosthetist, Dietitian, psychologist, OT, social worker.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lady Q and family were provided with pamphlets, website info for support services; advice given on continued care; how to and when to get in touch with PT and/or other members of the multidisciplinary team in preparation for discharge</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Lady Q was determined to maximize rehab potential, she routinely did her stretching exs, prone lying daily and use of extension board (initially)to prevent knee flexion contracture.She became competent in performing most daily operations like don/ doff prosthesis, sitt to st and vise versa, car and walking up and down stairs, walking &gt;50m with load.She is managing most ADLs, able to prepare meals and manages bathing and toileting independently</paragraph>
    <paragraph>She regained self confidence - now volunteers / advocates at amputee support group, goes to church and exercises at park with family. Work/Studying/ job change - telephone operator / receptionist at hotel.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lady Q is now compliant with medication management and diet, no worsening of vascular complications on contralateral limb developed. She has adapted to her condition, is cooperative and determined in advance gait training, cognizant of rehab goals and knowledgeable of her roles and responsibility on discharge.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Lady Q was progressed safely and successfully through the nine phases of the rehabilitation process for amputees[4][5]. It was a challenging yet diligent rehabilitation journey from her acute post-surgical treatment in hospital to pre-prosthetic rehabilitation phase, prosthetic prescription, prosthetic training, community integration, vocational rehabilitation, discharge and arrangements for follow-up.In particular, vigilance to prevent falls, skin care, promote wound healing, ensure comfortably fitted prosthesis to minimize pressure on sensitive areas and prevention of blisters/ breakdown of residual limb.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lady Q is happily reintegrated into work and social environment and is studying to enhance her skills at her new vocation.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Galley RS, Galley AM. Stretching and strengthening for lower extremity amputees. Miami, FL. Advanced Rehabilitation Therapy Inc. 1994</item>
      <item>↑International Committee of the Red Cross. Exercises for Lower-limb amputees. Geneva, Switzerland. 2008</item>
      <item>↑International Committee of the Red Cross. Exercises for Lower-limb amputees. Geneva, Switzerland. 2008</item>
      <item>↑Engstrom B, Van de Ven C. Therapy for Amputees. Churchill Livingstone, London. 1999</item>
      <item>↑Esquenazi A.Rehabilitation in Limb Deficiency. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1996; 77(3): S18-28.</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
</document>
