<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Individuals With Amputation In Low Resource Setting</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Individuals_With_Amputation_In_Low_Resource_Setting:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Individuals With Amputation In Low Resource Setting</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Lower limb amputation is one of the oldest known surgically performed procedures[1]. Many previous studies from Nigeria have recognised trauma and complications of management of musculoskeletal conditions by traditional bone setters as the leading cause of amputation in Nigeria. An example of which is my case presentation of a 44 year old farmer who had a motorcycle accident on his way to the farm and because of the lack of health facility in the primary health center he was taken to, he decided to visit a traditional bone setters resulting in a more serious complications</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>Trauma, below knee amputation, phantom limb pain, fracture, low resourced setting, fracture</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>My client is a 44-year-old male farmer who lives and farm in a rural area of North Central part of Nigeria. He was involved in a motorcycle accident on his way to the farm and had a comminuted tibia fracture of the right leg. He was taken to a primary health center within the village but due to lack of medical personnel and facility in the health center, he was referred to a tertiary facility about 20km to the village.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>My client felt the referred facility was too far for him and also did not have the financial resources to be managed in such facility. He thus reported to a traditional bone setter where he was managed for six weeks with no significant improvement before finally reporting to the tertiary health facility which is where I practice.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>He reported to the tertiary health facility with a leg ulcer and foul smelling discharge from the leg. Stiffness of the knee and ankle joint.  Absent of sensation to deep and light touch from the knee joint down to the foot</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>My client was referred to the physiotherapy unit of the health facility after surgery. The tertiary health facility where I practice is yet to incorporate interdisciplinary team approach into practice. Patient had a below knee amputation done. Patient chief complaint: Right phantom limb pain</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Patient history:patient had below knee amputation done secondary to trauma with history of trauma as documented in the abstract. He was met lying prone on bed with stump bandaging in place. Afebrile, acyanosed, conscious and alert and not in obvious respiratory distress. Segmental</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Examination:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Outlining client ICF findings:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Clinical Hypothesis</section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>After about 20 treatment sessions both in the ward and the department gym, client can now ambulate with a pair of axillary crutches, nil contracture and now has an increase performance and independence with functional mobility at an ambulatory level. Good gait pattern and good strength of his residual limb. Can now climb stairs with proper gait mechanism. Pain level reduced significantly to 0/10 on the VRS</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>After about 20 sessions of physiotherapy, patient now has good gait pattern with good strength of the residual limb.  Data from Nigeria on lower limb amputation is sparse but most studies reported a tune of about 80% from lower limb amputation with a high prevalence of male more than females[2].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Rehabilitation of amputees aims at restoring them to the best possible functional status. In the USA, immediate postoperative lower limb amputation prosthetic application was found to reduce average rehabilitation time from 128 to 31 days[3].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>In contrast, in West Africa, Nigeria amongst, many amputees never have prosthetic replacement they mobilize permanently on crutches[4], which is just in line with my client who could not afford the cost of fabricating a prosthesis and was referred to social workers. Social workers also have little to do to assist in this regard as they get little or no funds.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Murdoch G, Wilson A B eds Amputation: surgical practice and patient management. ST LOUIS MO: Butterworth- Heinmann medical 1996</item>
      <item>↑Onuba O, Udodok E, The scope of amputation in the developing countries. Postgraduate Doctor Africa; 2000; 11:118-121</item>
      <item>↑Unegbu M.I Dim E.M Safer Amputations. A review of 158 cases. Nigerian Journal of Surgical Sciences. 2007; 17:25-32</item>
      <item>↑Onuba O, Udodiok E, The scope of amputations in the developing countries. Postgraduate Doctor Africa; 2000;118-121</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
