<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Interdisciplinary care of a 84-year-old patient, following a trans-femoral amputation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Interdisciplinary_care_of_a_84-year-old_patient,_following_a_trans-femoral_amputation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Interdisciplinary care of an 84-year-old patient, following a trans-femoral amputation.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This clinical case concerns the rehabilitation of Mr. D, 84-year-old, hospitalized further to a trans-femoral amputation due to a sepsis on a prosthesis of knee. His wishes were to be able to re-walk with crutches inside his apartment, and be able to drive again. The objectives of rehabilitation were: the prosthesis, learning to walk, and the patient's independence. Phantom limb pain and fatigue somewhat disrupted the rehabilitation. However, after 16 weeks of rehabilitation, Mr. D returned home having achieved some of his objectives. The care started on September 29th, 2014.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>Trans femoral amputation; re-education; prosthesis; physiotherapy</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Mr. D is 84 years old. He is retired from the Air Force where he worked as a helicopter pilot. He is married, father of three children whom he sees regularly. He lives in an apartment on the first floor, with a lift. He has no particular hobby.  Mr. D was first operated on for a complete prosthesis of his right knee in 2001; after his prosthesis went loose he was operated on again twice, in 2003 and 2007. In the year 2014 his knee began to ache, Mr. D delayed before consulting his doctor.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>When he eventually visited his surgeon, Mr. D could hardly walk, the infection was already too large and amputation could not be avoided. It took place on September 16th, 2014.  Among Mr. D's risk factors it is necessary to note hyper blood pressure, overweight (BMI 26.9), a former smoking, sleep apnea and multiple operations including one for coronary artery disease. Mr. D's background is a coronary artery disease for which he was operated on in 2009, with 4 stents inserted; and surgery to remove several tumors (kidney in 1982, prostate and rectum in 2003 and 2010).</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Following various tests we chose with Mr. D. to work on his phantom limb pain in order to reduce it; we also decided his swelling needed to get reduced so as to stabilize the stump. Pre-prosthetic rehabilitation was also focused on the reduction of the right hip flexum, and work to strengthen the right leg. The muscles of the upper limbs, the left lower limb and trunk were all the same maintained for the walk with crutches. The work on transfer and balance made the patient more independent. We also reviewed the situation with Mr. D on therapeutic education and his actual skills. Once the patient was paired, we worked on walking, balance, support transfer.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>Outcome</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Mr. D's rehabilitation lasted 16 weeks. The first part of pre-fitting rehabilitation went well, and Mr. D qualified for all the requirements, including a joint mobility and adequate muscle strength, allowing the fitting of a prosthesis.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The second phase of his rehabilitation was more complicated. Indeed, the phantom limb pain never disappeared. The use of mirror therapy and TENS reduced it but it reappeared upon weight bearing and walking, which prevented Mr. D from walking on long distances. The "graded motor imagery"[2]might be able to be tested. This problem largely deteriorated his morale, and a psychologist reviewed the subject with him. Fatigue was also detrimental to the recovery of walking on long distances.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Indeed, a trans-femoral amputee spends much more energy than a normal person to walk (+ 68%)[3], and given Mr. D's age, this expenditure was difficult to manage. These two elements hampered the patient in achieving some of his objectives: he can move in his apartment with his crutches, but over short distances. Mr. D is still independent on his daily trips because he was given a wheelchair.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Thanks to the operation of the interdisciplinary team, the management of Mr. D's case was focused on the patient's interests and goals.[4]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <paragraph/>
    <list>
      <item>↑Bryant G. Stump Care. The American Journal of Nursing 2001; 101(2); 67-71</item>
      <item>↑Rothgangel,S, Braun,S, Beurskens,A, Seitz,R, Wade,D, The clinical aspects of mirror therapy in rehabilitation: a systematic review of the literature, Journal of Rehabilitation Research, 34:1-13,2011</item>
      <item>↑Waters RL, Perry J, Antonelli D, Hislop H. Energy cost of walking of amputees: the influence of level of amputation. J Bone Joint Surg 1976;58:42-6</item>
      <item>↑Körner, M. (2010) Interprofessional teamwork in medical rehabilition: a comparison of multidisciplinary and interdisciplinary team approach, Clinical Rehabilitation, 24 (8)745-755</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
