<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Lower Limb Amputation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Lower_Limb_Amputation:_Diabetic_Case_Presentation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Lower Limb Amputation: Diabetic Case Presentation: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Lower Limb Amputation: Diabetic Case Presentation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>A case presentation summarising the 21 day acute in-patient journey of a diabetic below knee amputee through to discharge to a community setting.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>Transtibial, diabetes, peripheral artery disease, phantom limb sensation, acute, in-patient</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>50 year old teaching assistantHistory of presenting condition:Peripheral artery disease leading to arteriosclerosis obliterans in the dorsalis pedis artery of the right legSubsequently hospitalised with an advanced diabetic foot ulcer and critical limb ischaemiaRevascularisation attempt via percutaneous transluminal angioplasty – an operation for enlarging a narrowed vascular lumen by inflating and withdrawing a balloon on the tip of an angiographic catheter through the stenotic region +/- positioning of an intravascular endoluminal stentMarginal improvement therefore transtibial amputation</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Past medical history:SmokingType 2 diabetesPeripheral artery disease: results in a restriction in the lumen of the arteries causing stenosis and restricted blood flow to an areaArteriosclerosis: generalised degeneration of the elastic tissue and muscles composing the arterial system causing them to become hard and tortuous</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Subjective assessment:Day 7 post right elective below knee amputation resulting from diabetic complicationsModerate post-amputation pain: reduced with analgesiaPhantom limb sensations (PLS): a normal experience for the majority of amputees. It is not a noxious sensation, but often described as a light tingling sensation and re-assurance is keyDepression: decreased mood and thoughts about not being able to walk and return to workObjective assessment:Decreased strength: full 5/5 on L. On R, 4/5 hip flexion and hip extension, 4+/5 hip abduction and hip adduction, and 4-/5 knee flexion and knee extensionDecreased range of movement: full range on L. on R, 90 degrees hip flexion, neutral hip extension, 20 degrees hip abduction, neutral hip adduction, 70 degrees knee flexion and -20 degrees from full knee extensionDecreased balanceDecreased enduranceDecreased skin integrity limiting opportunities to use PPAM aidIndependent wheelchair mobility and transfer to/from wheelchair with arm outDecreased ability to walk, secondary to 2 and 5, and therefore return to work (long term goal)</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Main problem = decreased range of movement at the hip and knee (neutral position of hip extension and -20° from achieving full knee extension)Decreased knee extension results in:Decreased ability for through range strengtheningReduced opportunity to use PPAM aid and ultimately a prosthesisDecrease hip extension results in:Decreased ability for through range strengtheningAltered gait pattern in stance phase on the rightUltimately, reduced potential success with future prosthetic function</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Decreased Rom:Reduced hip extension:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Reduced knee extension:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Decreased strength:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Decreased balance:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Progression:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Decreased endurance:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Decreased ability to walk:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Phantom limb sensation:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Minor global increase in strength and endurance of the amputated lower limb. Unable to determine significance of an improvement using the oxford grading scale due to changes being small and subjective nature of the grading system.Full range of extension at the knee and a 5-10° increase in hip extension on the right side. Would allow for greater functional application when appropriate to trial with a PPAM aid and eventually a prosthesis.Improved postural correction to aid with balance, and ability to stand safely and independently within parallel bars. Ability to stand unsupported with supervision for</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Unlikely to see a drastic increase in strength in such a short time frame as muscle strength takes 6-12 weeks to improve[1]. It may have been more beneficial to obtain an objective outcome measure, such as the number of repetitions of exercises +/- weights used.The loss of range at the knee post-amputation was an acute change, likely caused by swelling and pain from the trauma of amputation, therefore, soft tissue changes were easier to correct as swelling and pain were controlled.Balance is required to reduce the risk of falls and maximise safety. This is of particular importance in diabetic patients as they are more susceptible to injury and tissue failure.[2]Vascular transtibial amputees expend 40% more energy in gait and therefore require greater endurance to cope with these demands.PPAM aids may only be used from 5 days post-amputation following a satisfactory wound check. As the wound was not of satisfactory healing, this was avoided, in keeping with guidance[3]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Garber CE, Blissmer B, Deschenes MR, Franklin BA, Lamonte MJ, Lee I-M, Nieman DC, Swain DP. Quantity and Quality of Exercise for Developing and Maintaining Cardiorespiratory, Musculoskeletal, and Neuromotor Fitness in Apparently Healthy Adults: Guidance for Prescribing Exercise. Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise [online]. 2011; 43(7):1334-1359 [Accessed 17 July 2015].</item>
      <item>↑Lowe T, Khadir SA, Lowe R. The Diabetic Amputee. 2015 Accessed 17 July 2015.http://www.physio-pedia.com/The_Diabetic_Amputee[Accessed 17 July 2015].</item>
      <item>↑Bouch E, Burns K, Geer E, Fuller M, Rose A. Guidance for the Multi Disciplinary Team on the Management of Post-Operative Residuum Oedema in Lower Limb Amputees. 2015. Accessed 17 July 2015http://bacpar.csp.org.uk/publications/guidance-multi-disciplinary-team-management-post-operative-residuum-oedema-lowe</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>&lt;/div&gt;</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
