<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Mr. W. A Bilateral Below Knee Diabetic Amputee</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Mr._W._A_Bilateral_Below_Knee_Diabetic_Amputee:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Mr. W. A Bilateral Below Knee Diabetic Amputee</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Mr. W. is a bilateral below knee amputee who developed Type II diabetes after his most recent amputation. The following is a case study of his journey through an outpatient physiotherapy setting and his reintegration into society.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>below knee amputee, diabetes, cardiac complications, bilateral</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Demographics:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medical Diagnosis:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Co-morbidities:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Previous Care or Treatment:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Objective : Physical Examination Tests and Measures</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Functional Mobility:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>This gentleman is learning to adjust both psychologically and physically to the fact that he now is a bilateral below knee amputee. He functioned very well for 19 years being a single limb amputee. He presents with some adjustment issues psychologically, as the process of undergoing the second amputation has been more difficult than he expected, and what he has been able to do physically has been much harder. He also now has to deal with other issues related to the development of diabetes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Functionally the main goals are to reduce the contractures in the lower extremities, increase strength particularly in the gluteals bilaterally, improve his balance, improve confidence and ease of movement in bed mobility, become independent with ambulation with a single point cane for short to moderate distances, and with the rollator walker for longer distances, and to be able to be independent x 13 stairs with 1 railing and the single point cane. Because of the cardiac issues and deconditioning that he presents with, it is also a goal to improve his cardiac fitness and endurance.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Subjective:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Objective:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Mr. W's case is a somewhat unique one in the fact that he had both legs amputated and then found out that he was diagnosed with diabetes. However, given the fact that his right leg did develop a small sore on it that developed into osteomyelitis, it makes me wonder if he was an undiagnosed diabetic prior to the actual event that caused amputation of his remaining limb.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>As Pecoraro et al have found in most cases an episode involving minor trauma caused cutaneous injury, and preceded 69-80% of amputations in diabetics.[1]Mr. W. did have some adjustment issues initially as he struggled with the loss of his second leg, and the difficulties he experienced through this process.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Initially when I first started working with Mr. W. he was probably in the "depression" phase of grieving for his limb. However, the fact that he was very motivated, and had a strong work ethic allowed him to overcome this and move into the "acceptance and hope" stage as written in the article by Saul Morris.[2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mr. W. made significant improvements in all aspects of outcome measures both subjective and objective. Objectively, the fact that he improved from a score of 26/47 to 42/47 on the Amputee Mobility Predictor-bilateral (AMP-B) is quite significant. This outcome measure was selected given the fact that Mr. W is a bilateral amputee and there has been work to show that the AMP-B provides a more accurate assessment of the functional capabilities of Service Members with bilateral lower limb amputation.[3]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Pecoraro RE, Reiber GE, Burgess EM., 1990, Pathways to diabetic limb amputation. Basis for prevention., Diabetes Care. 1990 May;13(5):513-21.</item>
      <item>↑Morris, Saul, 2003 The psychological aspects of amputation. Taken fromhttp://www.amputee-coalition.org/first_step_2003/psychological-aspects-amputation.html July 12, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Raya MA, Gailey RS, Gaunaurd IA, Ganyard H, Knapp-Wood J, McDonough K, Palmisano T. 2013 Amputee Mobility Predictor-Bilateral: A performance-based measure of mobility for people with bilateral lower-limb loss., Journal of Rehabilitation Research and Development. 2013; 50 (7): 961-968.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
