<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Older Person Below Knee Amputation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Older_Person_Below_Knee_Amputation:Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Older Person Below Knee Amputation:Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Older Person Below Knee Amputation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Geriatric amputation has the possibility of devastating consequences at any age, let alone at the age of 73. Age and number of co-morbidities increase the 30 day mortality rate significantly.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The leading cause of Lower Extremity Amputation (LEA) in patients 65+ is severe peripheral artery disease (PAD) - with/without diabetes. Research estimates around 13% of geriatric patients will die within 30 days of LEA. (Physiopedia5) In comparison to clients who have one co-morbidity, some clients are 7 times more likely to die within a range of 30 days post amputation when having 4-5 co-morbidities.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>Diabetes, hypothyroidism, 73 year old female, gait training, transfer, gangrene.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>73 year old female, Ms. X, admitted to acute care hospital secondary to two fall incidents in one day while walking with four wheel walker at home on Jan. 11, 2014. Right below knee amputation secondary to gangrene of right foot and chronic peripheral vascular disease secondary to Diabetes on Jan.12, 2014. Code blue was called twice in acute care within the first week of amputation. When Ms X was medically stable, transferred to sub acute hospital on Apr. 25, 2014 for further rehabilitation with prosthesis.Patient has a prosthesis with a gel liner that has a pin locking systemRelevant associated medical diagnosis:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Subjective examination:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Clinical Hypothesis</section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Goal</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Outcome</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Although the patient has a long road to recovery, with consideration of her intact cognitive status, relatively safe home environment and supportive husband, Ms. X will have a better chance of a safe and successful recovery provided patient is compliant in taking her Synthyroid.However, Ms. X has eight comorbidities, there is up to 75% of dysvascular amputees have cardiac disease and is the leading cause of death post amputation.ICF encourages health care professionals to adopt a holistic approach through a biopsychosocial model that considers all aspects present in patient's life, which included health condition, environmental and personal factors.By considering the patients activity and participation that the health care team can help patient to resume her roles in her home setting environment with the help of home care team, day hospital program and regular follow up with the amputees clinic.Prior to discharge, occupational and physical therapists to conduct an interview with the patient and her husband pertaining to environmental factors and determine home modifications during home visitPersonal factors such as patient well being after discharge home, caregiver burn-out, information of respite care, when to contact medical team should be included in discharge planning.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[2][3][4]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Todd C, Skelton D. 20044http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0018/74700/E82552.pdf</item>
      <item>↑http://www.physio-pedia.com/Older_people_with_amputations</item>
      <item>↑http://www.physio-pedia.com/Older_people_with_amputations</item>
      <item>↑http://www.physio-pedia.com/Prosthetics</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
