<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Older person with amputation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Older_person_with_amputation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Older person with amputation: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Older person with amputation: Amputee Case Study</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>The impact of lower limb amputation on the geriatric patient can be complex. Taking into account all possible complications and post-operative goals is paramount for effective management of these patients. It is well documented that with age comes increased incidence of chronic disease. The numerous co-morbidities associated with chronic disease have several implications on the status of an elderly patient post amputation (Fried et al. 2004). This case study aims to discuss the examination and most appropriate rehabilitation process for an individual elderly patient with a lower limb amputation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>transtibial, elderly patient, PVD</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Client Characteristics</section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>SUBJECTIVE: Patient consented to physio. C/O of left lower limb stump pain when dependent - eases with lower limb elevation. Denies any dizziness. Patient reports to be managing pivot transfers with 1x assist currently. Wishes to be more independent with this to facilitate return home from rehab facility.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>OBJECTIVE</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Main problem: Inability to perform independent transfers to and from wheelchair due to general deconditioning and reduced strength.  Ability to return home is also limited by environmental factors including stairs at front entrance and lack of rails throughout bathroom/toilet.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Strength and ROM training  Plinth exercises including:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Transfers practice (and part-practice):</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Environment factors: Liaised with occupational therapist to arrange for home visit to take place. This allowed for necessary home modifications to occur including ramp access to home and installation of grab rails throughout the bathroom and toilet.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>With rehabilitation and multi-disciplinary input, the patient was able to achieve his goal of independent transfers to facilitate returning home with his wife. Increased community services and supports were also instituted to assist. Outcome measures for strength and ROM also demonstrated improvement.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Depending on the past medical and functional history of the geriatric amputee patient, our goals and expectations of rehabilitation can be variable. In this case assignment, I felt that achieving safe transfers to/from wheelchair was the main priority, rather than achieving successful prosthetic use.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Even though a prosthesis could in fact aid the ability of the patient to transfer more effectively, the presence of wound break down and reduced hip and knee extension ROM made the process and applicability of a prosthesis less suitable. The patient's pre-existing health concerns including congestive cardiac failure and his functional limitations prior to amputation meant the goals of rehabilitation were more focussed on wheelchair transfers rather than pursuing the direction of prosthetic fitting and rehabilitation. Other factors that contributed to this decision process included the patient's falls history and risk of skin tears.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Literature supports this idea also. A study by Fleury et al.[1]describes the low prosthetic success rate in geriatric amputee patients, with only 36% being successfully fitted with a prosthesis. The overall management of the elderly person with an amputation should be an individualised process. It should take into consideration the pre-existing health and functional status of the patient in order to allow for optimal outcomes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[2][3]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    <list>
      <item>↑Fleury A, Salih A, &amp; Peel N (2013), 'Rehabilitation of the older vascular amputee: A review of the literature', Geriatric and Gerontology International, vol.13, pp. 264-273.</item>
      <item>↑Fried L, Ferrucci L, Darer J, Williamson J, &amp; Anderson G (2004), 'Untangling the Concepts of Disability, Frailty, and Comorbidity: Implications for Improved Targeting and Care', Journal of Gerontology, Vol.59, No. 3, pp.255-263.</item>
      <item>↑Patrick L, Knoefel F, Gaskowski P, &amp; Rexroth D (2001), 'Medical comorbidity and rehabilitation efficiency in geriatric inpatients', J Am Geriatr Soc., vol.49(11), pp.1471-7.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
