<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Post-Operative Assesment and Mangement of a Transtibial Amputation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Post-Operative_Assesment_and_Mangement_of_a_Transtibial_Amputation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Post-Operative Assesment and Mangement of a Transtibial Amputation: Amputee Case Study</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>The assessment and treatment of a 77-year-old male with a recent transtibial amputation, who was already a left below knee prosthetic user. The reason for amputation was vascular compromise leading to a non-healing leg ulcer. The assessment was pre-prosthetic focusing on acute treatment and facilitation of discharge to the home environment from an inpatient setting.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>Transtibial, Independence, Outcomes measures, Physiotherapy, MDT, Transfers, Goal setting</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Demographics:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Present Condition: Non-elective admission for a Right transtibial amputation on 15/6/15 History</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Present Condition: Admitted with leg pain and non-healing right leg ulcer. Patient had the ulcer since an MRSA infection for a few months prior to amputation. Non-healing ulcer, due to history of peripheral vascular disease.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Past Medical history:  Peripheral vascular disease. Hypertension. TIA 2002- leading to carotid endarectomy. COPD, Previously laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Right hemi-arthroplasty Nov 2013 secondary hip fracture. History 2 x MI's more than 3 years ago. Left transtibial amputee 2000- prosthetic limb user.  Ex-smoker 2 years ago.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Subjective:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>History Patient lives with his wife in a one level access flat. Has a manual wheel chair for inside use and an electric wheelchair for outdoors- due to the flooring on the corridors outside the property making self propel difficult. Patient was a prosthetic user for a transtibial amputation on the left side. Patient was independently mobile over 50-100 yards and was able to manage stairs. Non driver. No specific hobbies highlighted except reading and watching TV. Patients perceived problem- pain-tender to touch over the underneath aspect of the stump NRS 8/10</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Patient's goals and expectations:</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>To be independent with transfers in and out of the wheelchair</item>
      <item>To be able to perform own activities of daily living including washing/dressing and making cups of tea.</item>
      <item>To be independent with toileting</item>
      <item>To receive a limb and return to pre-amputation level of mobility</item>
      <item>To return to his own living environment on discharge from hospital-did not want to go to in-patient rehab/intermediate care</item>
      <item>To be able to manage stairs.</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>Objective examination:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Body function and Structure Impairments</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Upper limb ROM--Full range of movement. No impairment right and left Muscle power -4+/5 globally in both uppers limbs</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Core Stability- Able to sit independently on the edge of the bed and reach outside base of support. Unable to bridge in lying due to prosthesis on left side.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lower limb-</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gait/metabolism expenditure- increased energy requirement sue to use of left below knee prosthesis. With further increased energy requirements due to right transtibial amputation resulting in from a vascular origin.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gait- unable to mobilises due to recent surgery and timescales of operation in relation to gait rehabilitation commencement. Transfers- Unable to transfer due to previous amputation on the left.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Activities:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Participation:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Patient is normally able to do his own shopping in town using public transport. No other recreational or leisure activities aware identified. Patient does attend the amputee support group on a monthly basis and transport, normally an ambulance or taxi is arranged for the patient through the charity supporting the class.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Environmental and Personal contextual factors:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The patient's home environment was largely set up for wheelchair use following his previous amputation. He uses an electric wheelchair to travel along the corridor, due to the carpets, which were wide enough for wheelchair use and the flat was situated on the ground floor. The flat was all on one level with no internal steps. There was enough room in the kitchen for wheelchair use and the patient had a perching stool already in place. The patents own environment is a facilitator for discharge as adaptations were already in situ form his previous operation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Previous personal experience of an amputation was a facilitator in this case as the patient was aware of what to expect and had an understanding of the how he would be limited in terms of activities and participation. However his previous amputation would also lead to difficulties, as higher energy expenditure would be required for tasks and the patient was more debilitated than previous.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The patient did have a Scandia toilet frame around his toilet, which meant he would need to be able to pivot transfer on and the toilet at home, or use alternative equipment. The patient was previously able to transfer though pivot on his unaffected leg. The frame was also identified as a tipping risk. This was a barrier to discharge.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Main problems</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Physiotherapy-</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Outcome</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>The patient on initial assessment the patient did have some areas of reduced ROM and muscle strength from a previous injury but also as a direct result from the operation and due to the natural ageing process of the musculoskeletal tissue. However early intervention and exercise were successful in improving this resulting in the approval for a prosthesis. According to the literature an interdisciplinary approach is most effective. In this case it was in supporting the amputee through to discharge by looking at the patient holistically and setting agreed goals, especially in relation to equipment for independence and the stump management to allow onward pre prosthetic rehabilitation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The MDT worked together with the patient and communicated regularly about the patient's goals in order to meet the amputee 10 day inpatient stay pathway and every one worked towards the same management plan. It has been said that amputees can grieve for the loss of their limb, through 5 stages. Initially the patient appeared display some elements of the bargaining phase during the initial post op days after the surgery as the patient stated various reasons/bargaining positions as to why he couldn't engage with physiotherapy straight away. However the patient progressed through these stages very quickly to acceptance over a course of 3 days. The use of outcome measure helps goal setting and monitors progression.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>During the in patient stay these, mainly focused on pain and ROM. There are little outcome measures that are suitable for the in-patient stay pre-prosthetically as the measure are mainly focused on prosthetic use. However planned outcome measures to be used for prosthetic rehabilitation are the Houghton score and the loco motor index</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>Barbara Engstrom, Catherine Van de Ven MCSP Therapy for Amputees, 3e Hardcover - 17 May 1999 •World Health Organisation (WHO). International classification of functioning disability and health (ICF). World Health Organisation 2001. Geneva.</item>
      <item>Lusardi MM, Postoperative and preprosthetic care. In Lusardi, MM, Jorge, M and Nielsen, CC editors. Orthotics and Prosthetics in Rehabilitation, Third Edition. Missouri: Elsevier, 2013.p. 532-594.</item>
      <item>Fletcher DD, Andrews KL, Butters MA, Jacobsen SJ, Rowland CM, Hallett JW Jr. Rehabilitation of the geriatric vascular amputee patient: a population-based study. Arch Phys Med Rehabil 2001;82:776-9.</item>
      <item>BACPAR toolbox of outcome measure. Version1 2012 BACPAR</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
</document>
