<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Post Prosthetic fitting rehabilitation of patient with trans tibial amputation, PVD and DM Type2</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Post_Prosthetic_fitting_rehabilitation_of_patient_with_trans_tibial_amputation,_PVD_and_DM_Type2:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Post Prosthetic fitting rehabilitation of patient with trans tibial amputation, PVD and DM Type2: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Post Prosthetic fitting rehabilitation of patient with trans tibial amputation, PVD and DM Type 2</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This case study follows the rehabilitation of a 62yr old male, transtibial amputee with PVD and Type 2 Diabetes. In Northern Ireland the number of adults diagnosed with diabetes has increased by 33% in 5 years. These issues are being addressed by a new strategy published by DHSSPS with an action and implementation plan from 2014. My aim was to evaluate the patient's assessment, treatment and outcome measurements with reference to the WHO ICF framework and current guidelines in the literature. This case supported current practice but also highlighted areas for improvement.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>Amputee, Diabetes, PVD, Northern Ireland, Recommendations, BACPAR</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>62-year-old man with a 8 week post-op following right transtibial amputation secondary to PVD and Type 2 Diabetes</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Past medical History:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>History of Present Condition:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Social History:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Movement</th>
        <th>R ROM</th>
        <th>R Muscle Power</th>
        <th>L ROM</th>
        <th>L Muscle Power</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Flex</td>
        <td>115</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Ext</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Abd</td>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>35</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Add</td>
        <td>15</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>20</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Int Rot</td>
        <td>20</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>25</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Ext Rot</td>
        <td>15</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>20</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee Flex</td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>120</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee Ext</td>
        <td>-10</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>full</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle D Flex</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle P Flex</td>
        <td>50</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>55</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Problem List:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Patient admitted for limb fitting rehab 8 weeks post-op.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Day 1- fitted with polyprop PTB socket with multiflex foot. Regular skin checks and contralateral foot checks day 1 to D/C and liaison with nursing staff on ward.  Fit with new juzo shrinker.  OT referral for W/C with stump board/ W/C skills.  Continue strength and stretch program for IRQ/hip/abdominals and core.  R/V previous goal setting.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Day 2-5 - posture/balance exs/proprioception exs/resisted exs in parallel bars Lat/AP/stride stance weight transferrance.  Gait re-ed in parallel bars.  Regular alignment checks and adjustments by prosthestist. Ongoing patient education re care of stump/oedema control/use of socks</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Day 6-10 - Increase advanced balance and resisted exs.  Progress to elbow crutches then sticks with assistance/supervision/independence . Gait analysis &amp; re-ed Outcomes measured . Practice - stairs/slope/outdoors/grass/rough ground/pavements/on-off floor/car transfers . OT- kitchen/bathroom activities/mirror therapy attempted/referral to community services for home assess.  Patient education-glycaemic control/care of contra lateral foot/smoking cessation/falls clinic. Introduce to peer support group/sports/hobbies/social integration. Final check/torque/cosmetic finish by prosthestist</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Day 11-15 Discharge and goals meeting.  OT-Shopping trip. Driving assessment . Temp D/C with prosthesis overnight.  Final outcomes measured Full D/C with info leaflet . R/V in 6 wks and 6 wk outcome measures</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Gait Analysis and Re-education:[1][2][3][4]</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Outcome Measures</th>
        <th>Day 7</th>
        <th>D/C</th>
        <th>6wk R/V</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>CIGAM</th>
        <td>Cb</td>
        <td>Db</td>
        <td>Db</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>LC15</th>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>35</td>
        <td>37</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>TUG</th>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>22</td>
        <td>17</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>2MWT</th>
        <td>56</td>
        <td>69</td>
        <td>79</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>ABC-UK</th>
        <td>55</td>
        <td>70</td>
        <td>73</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>SCS</th>
        <td>7</td>
        <td>7</td>
        <td>5</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Patient Goal</th>
        <th>Date Set</th>
        <th>Date Met</th>
        <th>Comments</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Reduce PLP</th>
        <td>22.04.15</td>
        <td>01.05.15</td>
        <td>Not improved with Mirror Therapy</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Walk with 2 E/C</th>
        <td>22.04.15</td>
        <td>01.05.15</td>
        <td>Now progressed to 2 sticks at D/C</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Go up 2 steps</th>
        <td>23.04.15</td>
        <td>03.05.15</td>
        <td>Safe and independent, OT to arrange hand rail</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Get into/out of car</th>
        <td>22.04.15</td>
        <td>01.05.15</td>
        <td>Independent</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Walk over grass</th>
        <td>24.04.15</td>
        <td>03.05.15</td>
        <td>Needs supervision for confidence</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Go shopping</th>
        <td>23.04.15</td>
        <td>06.05.15</td>
        <td>Supervision still required</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Climb stairs to bed</th>
        <td>22.04.15</td>
        <td>05.05.15</td>
        <td>Independent using 1 EC and 1 rail</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Evidence to support current practice and change of practice using ICF Framework.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>PATHOLOGY Pt has PVD, Diabetes, foot ulcers, poor glycaemic control and foot care. Diagnosed diabetes has risen in NI by 33% in 5 yrs. 1 in14 has had a foot ulcer. 1in10 foot ulcers result in 2 amputations/week here. Foot ulcers result from diabetic neuropathy and PVD.[4]After 1-5 years, 26-53% of dysvascular amputees in the UK require a 2nd amputation. BACPAR guidance recommends that prosthetic stability and gait should prevent abnormal loading of the contralateral limb.[5][6]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>BODY FUNCTION AND STRUCTURE : No referral made for W/C, stump board, community OT. No EWA used and minimal advice on ex. Pt did not wear juzo. This resulted in oedematous stump,FFD at knee,weak hip &amp; core muscles. Guidelines recommend use of a stump board, EWA and juzo shrinker.[7][8][9]Pt had fallen when transferring. BACPAR guidance recommends balance exs to reduce falls risk.[10]Rehab was based on BACPAR guidelines,Engstrom,the Prosthetic Gait Analysis for Physiotherapists &amp; Bob Gailey[1][2][3][4]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>ACTIVITIES:  Pt will always be W/C user and may become bilateral[5]. BACPAR guidance on the contralateral foot recommends education re risk factors and foot care.[5]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>PARTICIPATION : Diet,smoking,glycaemic control &amp; foot care- discussed[5]. 80% Type 2 diabetes cases could be prevented by diet and exercise. Diabetes and smoking increases heart disease &amp; stroke[6]. NICE recommend structured diabetes education[7].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.1Evidence Based Clinical Guidelines or the Physiotherapy Management of Adults with Lower Limb Prostheses. P Broomhead, K Clark, D Dawes, C Hale, A Lambert, D Quinlivan, T Randell, Ro Shepherd, J Withpetersen. BACPAR 2012</item>
      <item>↑2.02.1Therapy for Amputees Engstrom,B and Van de Ven C 19991</item>
      <item>↑3.03.13.2Prosthetic Gait Analysis for Physiotherapists. ICRC Physiotherapy reference Manual.Geneva, 2008</item>
      <item>↑4.04.14.2Prosthetic Gait Training for Lower Extremity Amputees. R Gailey, A Gailey. An Advanced Rehabilitation Therapy Incorporated Publication.19891</item>
      <item>↑5.05.15.25.3Risks to the Contralateral Foot of Unilateral Lower Limb Amputees: Guidance.F Brett, C Burton, M Brown, K Clarke, M Duguid, T Randell, D Thomas.BACPAR 2012</item>
      <item>↑6.06.1Fate of the contralateral limb after lower extremity amputation. Glaser JD1, Bensley RP, Hurks R, Dahlberg S, Hamdan AD, Wyers MC, Chaikof EL, Schermerhorn ML. Journal of Vasc Surg. 2013 Dec;58(6):1571-1577</item>
      <item>↑7.07.1White, E. (1992) Wheelchair stump boards and their use with lower limb amputees.British Journal of Occupational Therapy, 55(5),pp.174-178.</item>
      <item>↑Broomhead, P., Dawes, D., Hancock, A., Unia, P., Blundell, A. and Davies, V. (2006) Clinical guidelines for the pre and post operative physiotherapy management of adults with lower limb amputation. London: Chartered Society of Physiotherapy</item>
      <item>↑Oedema guidelines Guidance for the multi disciplinary team on the management of postoperative residuum oedema in lower limb amputees. E Bouch, K Burns, E Geer, M Fuller, A Rose. BACPAR 2012</item>
      <item>↑Guidance for falls prevention in Lower Limb Amputees. R Blundell, D Bow,J Donald, S Drury,L Hirst. BACPAR 2011</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
