<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Presentation on Geriatric Transtibial Amputee</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Amputee_Case_Study:_Presentation_on_Geriatric_Transtibial_Amputee</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Amputee Case Study: Presentation on Geriatric Transtibial Amputee
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Case presentation on geriatric transtibial amputee</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Mr. L is a 75-year-old transtibial amputee with multiple co-morbidities. This case presentation follows Mr. L through the pre-prosthetic fitting phase. Discussion is made on treatment for his impairments and considerations for the geriatric amputee.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>transtibial, geriatric, amputee, pre-prosthetic</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Mr. L is a 72-year-old gentleman who presented at our outpatient clinic with a right transtibial amputation. He had his amputation 3 months prior to appointment, and has only just referred to our clinic as his wound is now fully healed. The amputation was a result of gas gangrene of the right foot from a non- healing wound.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>His past medical history are as follows: Diabetes mellitus (DM), Hypertension, Ischaemic Heart disease (IHD) with recurrent congestive cardiac failure (CCF)- 2D echo results shows ejection fraction of 35%, peripheral vascular disease, previous first and second ray amputation of the right foot secondary to gangrene, cataracts in both eyes which are treated by surgery 2 years ago.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Premorbidly, he was ADL independent, community ambulation independent without aid. He was a retiree. He is currently staying with his family, and his main caregiver is his domestic helper. He is ambulant with wheelchair at home, and a motorized scooter outdoors. He reports to be ADL independent and independent in transfers.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Post amputation he was seen in an acute ward at the hospital and subsequently transferred to a step down rehabilitation ward. He was discharged from the rehabilitation ward after 3 weeks when he was able to transfer independently and caregiver was competent is assisting him at home for supervision of transfers and care of wound.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Subjective:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Objective:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Mr. L has a few problems that need to be addressed before he would be suitable for prosthetic fitting.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>The interventions are targeting the main problems.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Mr. L was able to increase his knee and hip range after stretching. He attained 0 degrees knee extension on bilateral knees but still had a 5 degree hip flexion contracture bilaterally. Hip abduction and extension strength increased to 4/5 bilaterally. After practice, he was able to complete full 30 minutes of seated cycling. He reported feeling less tired with transfers to toilet.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>After wearing the stump shrinker, his stump has reduced in size and was able to be successfully fitted with a prosthesis. However due to his recurrent CCF, his socket was fitted to allow accommodation of volume changes in stump. During normal days he would be wearing 2 prosthetic cotton socks. When he was having an episode of CCF, his stump would increase in size and the cotton socks would have to be taken out to accommodate the increased volume. He was taught to monitor for stump volume changes and change the number of socks accordingly.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Post fitting gait training commenced, starting from walking within the parallel bars. He also underwent balance training. However, due to the reduced hip range and reduced balance, it decided that he would be walking with a walking frame. Walking with a walking frame also reduces his energy expenditure during walking. Although he was able to complete 30 mins of cycling, he still felt tired after walking for about 20 metres. This is not a functional distance for outdoor walking, and thus would remain a K1 walker and continue to use motorized scooter outdoors.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Mr. L is a geriatric amputee who presents with the challenges of multiple co-morbidities. It is known that an older adult amputee has a reduced chance of prosthetic success, some reported as low as one third of geriatric amputee population.[1]Cardiac disease is quoted as one of the top reasons for prosthetic failure.[2]Mr. L has IHD, which affects his cardiovascular fitness. The increase in energy expenditure of prosthetic gait will increase the strain on the cardiovascular system. Thus, we decided to reduce the impact by the using of a walking frame, and alternative mobility for outdoors.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Geriatric amputees are at high risk of falls with risks factors such as neuromuscular weakness, medication side-effects, postural blood pressure changes, cognitive disorders, loss of vision, changes to sensation and proprioception as well as phantom sensations.[2]Mr. L presents with some of the above factors and thus at higher risk of falls. Care has to be taken with prosthetic mobility and transfers. It would be helpful to teach Mr. L fall recovery before discharge. It is well documented that improving joint mobility, muscle strength is important in the amputee.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Patients should have a personalized exercise program targeting the problem areas.[3]Mr. L had an exercise program drawn that that targeted his impairments. Mr. L also had practice with the PPAM, which helps to increase cardiovascular fitness, improve balance, reduce stump oedema and provides a psychological boost.[4]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <paragraph/>
    <list>
      <item>↑Fletcher, D., Andrews, K., Butters, M., Jacobsen, S., Rowland, C. and Hallett, J. (2001). Rehabilitation of the geriatric vascular amputee patient: A population-based study. Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, 82(6), pp.776-779.</item>
      <item>↑2.02.1Fleury, A., Salih, S. and Peel, N. (2012). Rehabilitation of the older vascular amputee: A review of the literature. Geriatrics &amp; Gerontology International, 13(2), pp.264-273.</item>
      <item>↑Broomhead P, Clark K, Dawes D, Hale C, Lambert A, Quinlivan D, Randell T, Shepherd R, Withpetersen J. (2012) Evidence Based Clinical Guidelines for the Managements of Adults with Lower Limb Prostheses, 2nd Edition. Chartered Society of Physiotherapy: London.</item>
      <item>↑Scottish Physiotherapy Amputee Research Group, National Centre for Training and Education in Prosthetics and Orthotics, PPAM Aid Clinical Guidelines for Physiotherapists</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
