<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Prosthetic Training for an Older Adult with a Transtibial Amputation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Prosthetic_Training_for_an_Older_Adult_with_a_Transtibial_Amputation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Prosthetic Training for an Older Adult with a Transtibial Amputation: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Prosthetic Training for an Older Adult with a Transtibial Amputation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This case touches on an elderly female with a transtibial amputation who had participated in a Home to Heal program and was returning to inpatient rehab for prosthetic training. This patient had limiting factors including delayed wound healing, arthritis, mild cognitive impairments, decreased family support for her rehab process and slight decrease in mood/motivation.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>transtibial, older adult, delayed wound healing, arthritis</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>She was born in Toronto, is in her late 80s, and has a historyof PVD, diabetes, hypertension and RA. Ischemia of the right leg led to a transtibial amputation. While waiting for her wound to heal, she returned home where she managed using a manual wheelchair for mobility and pivot transferring to other surfaces.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>ICF-Pathology</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Body Function and Structure (impairments)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Activities (limitations)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Participation (restrictions)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Environmental Factors</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>Personal Factors</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>The client's main issues include comorbidities which will affect prosthetic training, cognitive issues and lack of family involvement in her prosthetic rehab. Has delayed wound healing, which may lead to increased discharge with wearing prosthesis, unknown healing under scab. Oedema needs to be managed. Multidisciplinary team needs to be involved with wound assessment, treatment and monitoring.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>Outcome</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Overall, this case showed how delayed wound healing, cognitive issues, decreased family support and comorbidities such as arthritis can impact prosthetic training. The client ended up going home and not wearing the prosthesis for the first week since she was concerned about the delayed wound healing. It is important the client was able to return to her home after the amputation and experience functioning without a leg in her home environment. Sometimes I wonder if she began her prosthetic training too early. I also wonder if it would have been possible to arrange family involvement in a different way and sooner in her rehab stay.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑http://www.physio-pedia.com/Acute_post-surgical_management_of_the_amputee</item>
      <item>↑http://www.physio-pedia.com/Post-fitting_management_of_the_amputee</item>
      <item>↑http://www.physiopedia.com/images/3/3f/Preventing_and_Caring_for_the_Secondary_Conditions_of_Limb_Loss.pdf</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
