<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Rehabilitation of a young transtibial amputee</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Rehabilitation_of_a_young_transtibial_amputee:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>Rehabilitation of a young transtibial amputee: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Rehabilitation of a Young Transtibial Amputee</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This case presentation outlines the first seven weeks of rehab for a nineteen year old gentleman who suffered a traumatic right transtibial amputation. He is now ambulating independently with his prosthesis (no gait aids) in physio and looks forward to returning to university studies and a part-time cafe job.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>young, transtibial, traumatic</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>"Mr P" is a 19 year old man who suffered a traumatic right transtibial amputation after being hit by a train 7 weeks ago. He was taken by ambulance to the nearest trauma centre where his right lower leg was declared unsalvageable. It was amputated that evening. He also suffered multiple right rib fractures. He remained in the acute hospital for 7 days. His medical recovery was uncomplicated. He was seen by physiotherapists to monitor his breathing and teach transfers and crutch ambulation. He was then transferred to our inpatient rehabilitation centre. As he was mobile and from a safe home environment, he was discharged home Day 12 post amputation.Mr P had no significant medical past history. He is a ""social"" smoker and drinker, although admits to binge drinking when out with friends. Prior to the accident, he lived with his parents and younger siblings in a 2 storey house (access via 2 front steps, bedroom/bathroom upstairs but kitchen/living room downstairs). He had finished school the year previously and was in his first year of university, studying Arts. He had previously walked unaided, an unlimited distance and had no history of falls. He drives an automatic car and often catches public transport (trains, buses). He was not particularly sporty, reporting playing the odd game of golf or tennis with his mates. He did no formal exercise but enjoyed riding his bike and skateboarding. He worked part-time at a cafe and enjoyed socialising with friends and playing his guitar."</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>7 weeks post amputation:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Without prosthesis:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>With Prosthesis:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Main activity limitations:1. Limited walking distance2. Can't drive yet3. Can't skateboardMain participation restrictions:1. Not back at university2. Not back at part-time cafe work3. Not going out with friends (e.g. to pub)</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>At present, Mr P's main problems are:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>1. Able to wear prosthesis for only 40mins before needing to take it off to ""rest"" the residual limb (due to pressure discomfort)2. Gait endurance only 200m3. Discomfort in right single leg stance: holds for 2-3 sec only4. Is only using prosthesis in physiotherapy gym.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This problem list was developed by physio and patient together.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>As Inpatient and Pre-fitting:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Post-fitting:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Prosthetist:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>OT:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Psychologist:</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>The outcome of our intervention so far is that Mr P will most likely take his prosthesis home for the first time next week. He will start with a graduated wear programme of 40mins three times per day, progressing gradually up to 2 hours three times per day. At this point, he will go to 3 hours, twice per day and gradually build this up until he is wearing his prosthesis for most of the day. His mother is very supportive and has attended several physio sessions recently so she will assist Mr P with his graduated wear programme. He will continue attending physio for another week or so after he takes his prosthesis home but will then be given a six week therapy break to allow him to concentrate on returning to university, hobbies, etc. His OT is liaising regarding returning to driving and also a graduated return to work programme once he is tolerating longer wear times.After the six week break, Mr P will be invited to resume therapy to concentrate on any higher level activities he may wish to pursue, for example climbing ladders, running, golf, bike riding. He will also be guided to formulate an ongoing exercise plan for life-long health to counteract the negative effects of a sedentary lifestyle (weight gain can be particularly problematic for amputees).</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>In summary, Mr P's case demonstrates the speed at which a younger client can be progressed, as opposed to the older clients with multiple co-morbidities that make up the bulk of the current patient population in our rehab centre. It is unusual for us to have a client that does not require a wheelchair for non-prosthetic mobility. It is unusual for us to have a client that does not have some combination of cognitive difficulties, visual/hearing loss, peripheral neuropathy/circulation deficits or joint/cardiac/lung disease that limits mobility.However, psychologically Mr P has had greater adjustment issues than most of our clients. Often our clients have had pain and lack of limb function for so long that is almost a ""relief"" to have the amputation. Many describe looking forward to a new beginning whereas Mr P has to re-imagine his future.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>Morris, S. ""The Psychological aspects of Amputation"" Amputee Coalition of America (2008)</item>
      <item>International Classification of Functioning, Independence and Health. World Health Organization (2001) ISBN/WHO Reference number 92 4 154544 5</item>
      <item>Engstrom, B and Van de Ven, C ""Therapy for Amputees, 3rd Ed."" Elsevier (1999)</item>
      <item>Clinical Practice Guidelines for Rehabilitation of Lower Limb Amputation Dept. of Veteran's Affairs, Dept. of Defence (2007)</item>
      <item>Broomhead, P et al ""Clinical guidelines for the pre and post operative physiotherapy management of adults with lower limb amputation. Chartered Society of Physiotherapy, London (2006)</item>
      <item>Gailey, R.S. and A.M. ""Prosthetic Gait Training for Lower Extremity Amputees""</item>
      <item>Pescatello, L.S et al ""ACSM Guidelines for exercise testing and prescription"" American College of Sports Medicine (2014)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
