<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Support for an Amputee where the Multidisciplinary Approach has been Flouted</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Support_for_an_Amputee_where_the_Multidisciplinary_Approach_has_been_Flouted:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Support for an Amputee where the Multidisciplinary Approach has been Flouted: Amputee Case Study
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Support for an Amputee where the Multidisciplinary Approach has been Flouted</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>A young man of 33 years old, living 280 km from our centre (the equipment centre of Madagascar or CAM based in Antananarivo) arrives home with his brother. It was amputated left leg in 1/3 means-1/3 lower level following a fall bike. His reference wasn't official. It has been informally advise by the surgeon in his community to come in our centre. The MDT approach is dislocated from his start because there wasn't P&amp;O who has been consulted and given his opinion for the level of the amputation. In CAM, MDT (physician, P&amp;O and physio) is in front of the traumatized young hope still find walking</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>Mamy, Andrianaly, transtibial, traumatic, madà, Physiopedia</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Client Characteristics</section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>In 24 April 2014-SUBJECTIVE:Patient history:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Chief complaints:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Self report out come measures:</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>-OBJECTIVE:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Physical examination tests and measure:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>-</paragraph>
    <paragraph>ICF Findings</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Our clinical evaluation of the patient'main problem in the pre-fitting phase leads to the need of reducing the flexion of the left knee by a second surgery. If the young man isn't agree, his gait will be bad. If he's agree, he must follow physiotherapy exercises to have good stump and knee joint correct for fitting. Assessment may be set and the amputee's psychology prepared.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Surgery on the left knee in October 2014 followed by a functional support for stump management and maintenance of joints (left knee and hip particularly)</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>There was obtained a relative mobility of the left knee: maximum of extension but reduced bending at -40°</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>The case I've choose concerns a a young man 33 young old who lost his left leg in a motorcycle accident in December 1st 2013 at a place situated 280 km from our centre in the north-east of the capital of Madagascar where there isn't no fitting service, so no P&amp;O. There hasn't been a multidisciplinary team that could make a pre-assessment amputation. There was just the surgeon with his team block which should intervene urgently to avoid vital risk for bleeding. This has put us in difficulty to fit the amputee with a short stump and a knee joint locked in flexion. The amputee comes to see us 4 months later with all these complications and the CAM's team should strive to convince him for a 2nd surgery of the knee flexion contracture reduction. The young man was agree and the second surgery was been done on October 2014 with the outcomes followed: a complete extension but a limitation of flexion. We feel that physio-exercises twice per week are necessary to prepare the stump and the knee mobilisation before the fitting. It's one difficult case the CAM's team has to manage because it was so complex for the building of the prosthesis and in front of the social situation of this young man who must stop his activity. The fact that we cannot follow all the steps of assessment in the lower limb amputation put us in difficulties to fit this young man and stop a long time his social integration. Mobilisation of a lot of responsibles is necessary in our country.[3]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[4]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Disability in Africa,http://www.ascleiden.nl/content/webdossiers/disability-africa</item>
      <item>↑Jerome Peter fredericks, 2012, Thesis, Description and Evaluation of the Rehabilitation programme for persons with lower limb amputations at Elangeni, paarl, South Africa</item>
      <item>↑Fedération Africaine des Techniciens Orthoprothesistes, www.fatoafrique.org</item>
      <item>↑Organisation Africaine pour le developpement des centres pour les Personnes Handicapées, www.oadcph.org</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
