<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>The Diabetic trans-femoral amputee</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/The_Diabetic_trans-femoral_amputee:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>The Diabetic trans-femoral amputee: Amputee Case Study</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This case study describes learning that I gained through reflection on a client I had treated previously. This case study is an example of mistakes that can be made and a description of the valuable lessons learned regarding the management of the diabetic trans-femoral amputee.  Key learnings: to be realistic with mobility expectations in this type of patient, regarding cardiovascular disadvantage and high energy requirements; to thoroughly investigate and manage pain if it is a barrier to rehabilitation; to ensure good patient education in order to prevent regression in functional abilities.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>transfemoral, diabetes, pain management, learning, ambulation, amputation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Mr. P is a 69 year old male who is a director of a Plastic Injection Molding Company. He is responsible for managing and supervising the employees. He is married and lives with his wife in a single story house. He was not very active (in terms of sport and recreation) pre-morbidly and is an ex-smoker. He was driving independently pre-morbidly. Mr. P had an above knee amputation in July 2014 following progressive complications after a below knee amputation the month before. The amputation was preceded by multiple vascular procedures to both his limbs. He has extensive peripheral vascular disease, which lead to the initial amputation. He also several co-morbidities namely: Type 2 Diabetes, cardiomyopathy and cardiac failure. Mr. P was admitted to a rehabilitation facility following his amputation in the beginning of August 2014. He received extensive in-patient rehabilitation while waiting for his wound to heal. During his rehabilitation he had difficulty with hypotension as well as severe phantom limb pain, which settled prior to his discharge. He was discharged after 8 weeks, at which stage his wound had healed and he had started coning the stump. He had also had his first prosthetic fitting with a test socket prior to discharge. He commenced therapy as an out-patient 3 weeks following his discharge.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Initial examination was conducted on 27 October 2014 (3 months after amputation and 3 weeks after being discharged from in-patient rehabilitation) See medical history under "Patient Characteristics" above. Mr. P's goals and expectations were:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Examination within ICF framework:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Initially I had considered Mr. P's goal of being able to walk independently, achievable. I launched in to a high level exercise program. It soon became apparent that he was severely limited by pain, poor endurance and his co-morbid conditions. After a discussion with Mr. P we agreed that trying to achieve walking without crutches (or even with crutches) was unrealistic. He had already fallen twice at home and we were not willing to risk further falls. The risk of walking without an assistive device out-weighed the importance of fall prevention and preservation of his remaining limb. Considering this, Mr. P's main problem is poor mobility with a walker, and the inability to drive. The decision was made that the priority of treatment was to optimise gait with a walking frame, improve endurance, manage pain and facilitate return to driving.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Due to the gap in therapy, Mr. P's outcomes worsened when he was re-assessed 3 months after his neuroma surgery.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>My expectations initially were that we would be able to achieve independent walking without crutches. There were many obstacles during his post-prosthetic rehab that prevented us from achieving this goal. Firstly, his pain was not appropriately addressed. The causes of pain are complex and should have been investigated more thoroughly[1]. It was often overlooked and became a big barrier to progress.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mr. P had a number of co-morbid conditions. In hindsight I can now see that he battled with the exercises prescribed because of his poor endurance. The energy expenditure for a trans-femoral amputee is 150-170% more than normal[2], and his cardiovascular system was already compromised. My sessions should have been broken up with more rest periods and lower level exercises, which may have made him more compliant with a home program. I feel I had pushed him to ambulate too soon, placing his contralateral limb under undue risk.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>I have now learned that it is exceptionally important to protect the contralateral limb in diabetic amputees.[3]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The time that Mr. P spent at home without any exercise caused him to regress. This may have been due to a number of reasons, but the lesson learned here is the importance of discharge management even if it is for temporary discharge. I should have ensured he understood the importance of his home exercise program and stretching of his hip flexors. Good patient education may have made a difference to his outcomes when he returned after 3 months.[4]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Maurice D. Schnell, M.D. Wilton H. Bunch, M.D., Ph.D. Management of Pain in the Amputee, Digital Resource Foundation for the Orthotics and Prosthetics Community,</item>
      <item>↑ICRC Reference Manual - Prosthetic Gait Analysis for PhysiotherapistsfckLR</item>
      <item>↑Izumi, Y., Satterfield, K., Lee, S. and Harkless, L., 2006, Risk of Reamputation in Diabetic Patients Stratified by Limb and Level of Amputation: 10-year observation,http://care.diabetesjournals.org/content/29/3/566.long, Diabetes Care, March vol. 29 no. 3 566-570fckLR</item>
      <item>↑Pantera, E., Pourtier-Piotte, C., Bensoussan, L., Coudeyre, E. (2014). Patient education after amputation: Systematic review and experts' opinions. Annals of physical and rehabilitation medicine, 57(3), 143-158</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
