<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>The Diabetic BK Amputee</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/The_Diabetic_BK_Amputee:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>The Diabetic BK Amputee</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This case presentation outlines the care, protocols, and special considerations used with a below-knee amputee in clinical practice. The clinical setting is Regent Park Community Health Centre. This is a multidisciplinary primary practice and health promotion facility in downtown Toronto. Residents of Regent Park include low-income populations, immigrants and refugees, non-status individuals, and the homeless. As such, clients of the health centre face significant health inequities and barriers to health access.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>below knee, diabetic, Canada, bulbous, diabetes, peripheral vascular disease</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <list>
      <item>Demographic information: retired male, age 64 years, resent non-status immigrant</item>
      <item>Medical diagnosis: diabetes mellitus (poorly controlled), diabetic gangrene</item>
      <item>Co-morbidities: anaemia, decreased hearing , cigarette smoker, daily alcohol drinker</item>
      <item>Previous care or treatment: left 4th toe amputation 2014, ongoing wound care, single point cane</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>64-year-old male 10 days post left short below knee amputation for diabetic gangrene demonstrates decreased muscle strength throughout residual limb, sound limb, and bilateral upper extremities, and decreased independent mobility. Poor management of residual limb has resulted in bulbous shape. Client would benefit from ongoing PT intervention to address strength, mobility, and phantom sensation; to provide education to client and family; and to manage residual limb in preparation for prosthesis. This PT will refer client to specialty amputee service for prosthetic rehabilitation when health insurance has been secured.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>The client progressed well regarding lower extremity strength, and mobility. With treatment, the shape and stability of his residual limb also improved. By the time he was discharged to a rehab service, the limb was suitable for introduction of a prosthetic limb. Activity tolerance and standing balance also progressed well.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>In hindsight, upper extremity strengthening exercises would have been a valuable addition to this client's treatment program[1]. Specific upper extremity strengthening could have increased his ease of transfers and ambulation; improved his gait pattern with the two wheeled walker; improved safety by reducing risk of falls; and contributed to overall positive outcomes. However, in general the treatment provided prepared this client well for prosthetic use.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This patient is at increased risk of amputation of his remaining sound limb over the next 5-10 years[2][3]. Special care will need to be taken to protest and observe the right leg and foot to prevent any small wounds that could lead to gangrenous infection and eventually to an amputation[4]. Aggressive treatment must be put in place immediately if any wounds occur in the remaining limb[5]. Safety must be paramount in the ongoing care of this client as a fall could be devastating to his health status[1]. Steps should also be taken towards smoking cessation as this puts the client at increased risk of complications[2].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.1The Diabetic Amputee -http://www.physio-pedia.com/The_Diabetic_Amputee</item>
      <item>↑2.02.1Diabetic Amputation Rates in Canada: Not Good News,http://www.themayerinstitute.ca/diabetic-amputation-rates-in-canada-not-good-news/ 5. Izumi, Y., Satterfield, K., Lee, S. and Harkless, L., 2006, Risk of Reamputation in Diabetic Patients Stratified by Limb and Level of Amputation: 10-year observation,http://care.diabetesjournals.org/content/29/3/566.long</item>
      <item>↑Diabetes Care, March vol. 29 no. 3 566-570 6. Pecoraro RE, Reiber GE, Burgess EM., 1990, Pathways to diabetic limb amputation. Basis for prevention., Diabetes Care. 1990 May;13:513-21. - See more at:http://www.physio-pedia.com/The_Diabetic_Amputee#sthash.NfsKSqmB.dpuf</item>
      <item>↑Reducing the Risk of Complications - Diabetes,http://www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/cd-mc/diabetes-diabete/complications-eng.php</item>
      <item>↑Diabetes Mellitus - Ontario Wound Care,http://www.ontariowoundcare.com/diabetes.htm</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
