<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Trans-metatarsal amputation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Trans-metatarsal_amputation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>Trans-metatarsal amputation: Amputee Case Study</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This case presentation demonstrates the difficulties associated with achieving a satisfactory functional outcome with a trans-metatarsal amputation. These procedures are associated with a high rate of revision and failure. A coordinated approach from planning surgical procedure through post operative care and rehabilitation is required. Though a number of types of orthotic and prosthetic options are available, there is little evidence supporting one over the other, making achieving desired outcomes challenging.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>partial foot amputation, trans-metatarsal amputation, insensate, equino-varus</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>The patient is a 66-year-old female who acts as a carer for her intellectually disabled adult son, and provides part time care for a grandchild. She has Type II diabetes for 6 years with retinopathy and peripheral neuropathy. Patient has a proximal trans-metatarsal amputation of the right foot secondary to osteomyelitis. 2 revisions and 1 skin graft required to reach definitive length. Non-healing ulcer of the plantar disto-lateral aspect of the stump persisted for 15 months after final procedure. Despite the presence of peripheral neuropathy, there was significant pain associated with the ulcer. Ambulation was limited by both pain, and the need to offload the wound site to facilitate healing.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Patient's diabetes was controlled, vascular supply intact. Both lower limbs were insensate to mid-tibia. Wound exhibited classic characteristics of plantar neuropathic ulcer - localized, 'punched-out' appearance with development of callous at peri-wound margins, requiring regular debridement.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Physical examination notes generalized limited range of motion (ROM) with equinus deformity of the ankle, at 15 degrees plantarflexion. There was a marked equino-varus deformity of the stump. It was noted by both the patient and the treating team that this position had become more exaggerated since the amputation was performed. The tibialis anterior tendon had become increasingly tight and prominent in the absence of resistance from extensor and lateral muscle groups resected at the time of the procedure. No tendon transfer or lengthening procedures were done at the time. The resulting position of the foot focused pressure onto the wound site.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gait was apropulsive, with shortened stride length and a pronounced limp (secondary to both pain and increased functional length on the affected side due to equinus). A zimmer frame was used for ambulation. Balance was poor, as was patient confidence. Pain was also a significant limiting factor. The goals for both the patient and the healthcare team were long term wound healing and restoring mobility.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>Patient's longstanding ulceration and physical limitations are secondary to diabetes, peripheral neuropathy and altered mechanics. Improvement of residual limb mechanics by the use of appropriate physical therapy and orthosis/prosthesis should improve mobility and facilitate wound healing.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>Outcome</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Partial foot amputation (PFA) affects about 2 per 1000 people in industrialised countries, but is associated with a high failure rate and many complications[1].  In PFA the patient is left with a smaller weight-bearing surface subject to greater mechanical stress. Ulceration easily occurs in the insensate foot.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Retaining a balanced metatarsal parabola and avoiding uneven bone spurs is critical in avoiding failure[2]. Muscle imbalance occurs with most PFA. Resection of muscle/tendon results in functional instability. Equino-varus deformity often results from unopposed action of gastrocnemius, tibialis anterior, and tibialis posterior, coupled with loss of extensor tendons[3]. Ankle equinus results if Achilles tenotomy or transfer is not performed[2].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Initially flexible and reducible instability will eventually become fixed, and distal stump breakdown is inevitable. There is evidence that once the metatarsal heads have been amputated, power generation across the ankle is negligible, and the assumption that PFA is less energy expensive than trans-tibial amputation is incorrect[3]. Despite a range of below and above ankle prosthetic interventions available, there is little evidence to support the effectiveness of any combination of devices, thus informed decisions about treatment options is difficult. The fact remains, that orthotic/prosthetic management is paramount in the insensate foot after amputation</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Dillon MP 2010 'Partial Foot Amputation: Aetiology, Incidence, Complications, Prosthetic Intervention and a Characterisation of Gait' In: JH Stone, M Blouin, editors. International Encyclopaedia of Rehabilitationhttp://cirrie.buffalo.edu/encyclopaedia/en/article/154/</item>
      <item>↑2.02.1Sullivan JP 2005 'Complications of Pedal Amputations' Clinics in Podiatric Medicine and Surgery Vol 22, pp 469-484 doi:10.1016/j.cpm.2005.03.004</item>
      <item>↑3.03.1Nather A &amp; Wong KL 2013 'Distal amputations for the diabetic foot' Diabetic Foot &amp; Ankle Vol 4: 21288http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/dfa.v4i0.21288</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
