<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>War Vetern Case Presentation</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/War_Vetern_Case_Presentation:_Amputee_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Amputee Case Study</parent_folder>
  <section>War Vetern Case Presentation: Amputee Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>War Vetern Case Presentation: Amputee Case Study</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>The pt, KP is s/p L trans-radial BEA and R trans-femoral AKA, injuries sustained from Improvised Explosive Device (IED) while deployed in Iraq with secondary dx of possible TBI from explosion. Pt was recommended to out-patient therapy to increase independence with ADL, IADL, mobility, regulate emotions, reduce pain/edema, sensitivity in residual limbs and improve overall cognitive ability. Pt has potential to improve with skilled healthcare services.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Key Words
    <paragraph>veteran, amputee, trans-radial, trans-femoral, ADL, phantom limb pain</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>KP is a 45 y/o women war veteran. KP lives with her husband, Sam, in a two-story house with no elevator. They have no children or pets. They live 3 hours from their closest family members. KP has a close group of friends that she goes out for lunch with and long walks frequently. Though, she fears that, with her amputation and mental health issues her friends are beginning to avoid her more. They have a cleaning woman that cleans the entire house and does the laundry once a week. Frustrated with current ADL performance, anxious for LE prosthesis and not sleeping well. Emotional and unsure of future career status.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Subjective: Patient complains of phantom limb pain and weakness. The patient hopes to successfully use a prosthetic limb to ambulate at a high fitness level and reduce or eliminate the phantom limb pain. Patient is currently working with PT, doctors, OT, Prosthesist, social worker and nursing staff. Frustrated with current ADL performance, anxious for LE prosthesis and not sleeping well. Emotional and unsure of future career status.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Self Report Outcome Measures</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Physical Performance Measures</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Objective:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Physical Examination Tests and Measures</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Hypothesis
    <paragraph>s/p L trans-radial BEA and R trans-femoral AKA, injuries sustained from Improvised Explosive Device (IED) while deployed in Iraq. Possible TBI from explosion. Possible PTSD. Restore self-care skills, establish transfer skills, and regain social cognition skills. Also, restore strength, sensitivity, reduce edema, reduce pain and establish relaxation techniques. Cognitive compensatory strategies include: AE training, Prosthetic training and ADL and mobility retraining. Long term increase ADL, IADL and mobility, regulate emotions and improve overall cognitive ability.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Goal Method</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Goal Outcome</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>KP had a R trans-radial BEA and L trans-femoral AKA with a secondary dx possible mild acquired brain injury (TBI) and/or PTSD, complicating KP's ability to retain new information. KP's case reinforces previous evidence that endorses the use of retrograde massage, positioning in wheelchair, bed for edema treatment. KP's case reinforces previous evidence that endorses desensitization, tapping, mirror therapy to decrease pain[2].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>"Although all 27 (100%) of the amputees were able to maintain satisfactory family functioning, only 13 (48.1%) of the study participants were able to remain productively employed after undergoing amputation, and 20 (74%) reported long-term psychological problems in addition to their physical pain"[3].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>More research is needed on compensation strategies and coping mechanisms specifically for war veterans with amputations due to the psychological impacts of war. KP was referred to VA, veteran support group, OT for a driving evaluation and strength coach[4].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.001.011.021.031.041.051.061.071.081.091.10Radomski M.V. &amp; Latham C.A.T. (2008). Occupational therapy for physical dysfunction (6th ed.). Philadelphia: Wolters Kluwer Lippincott  &amp; Williams; Wilkins</item>
      <item>↑2.02.1Timms, J., &amp; Carus, C. (2015). Mirror therapy for the alleviation of phantom limb pain following amputation: A literature review. International Journal of Therapy &amp; Rehabilitation, 22(3), 135-145.</item>
      <item>↑Ebrahimzadeh, M. H., &amp; Rajabi, M. T. (2007). Long-term outcomes of patients undergoing war-related amputations of the foot and ankle. The Journal of foot and ankle surgery, 46(6), 429-433.</item>
      <item>↑Khadir, S.A. (2015). High-level rehabilitation of amputees. Retrieved fromhttp://www.physiopedia.com/High_level_rehabilitation_of_amputees</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
