<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Case Study McArdle Disease</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Case_Study_McArdle_Disease</url>
  <parent_folder>McArdle Disease</parent_folder>
  <section>Case Study McArdle Disease</section>
  <section>
    Title
    <paragraph>McArdle disease: a case report and review</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Word Count
    <paragraph>756</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Authors
    <paragraph>Leite A, Oliveira N, Rocha M (Modified by Kaylynn Schwamb and Michael Helton)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>McArdle's Diseaseis a recessive inherited disorder that presents as an inability to metabolizeglycogen, the storage form of glucose. This results in a variety of symptoms affecting the musculoskeletal and urinary systems, with the most common symptom being muscle fatigue. This case study adapted from Leite et al. and expanded by Kaylynn Schwamb and Michael Helton, DPT students at Bellarmine University. This disease can be well managed with a holistic and multidisciplinary approach that involves physical therapy.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>This case demonstrates some of the day-to-day struggles of living with McArdle's Disease along with associated signs and symptoms of the disease. It also discusses abnormal lab values and possible physical therapy interventions and outcomes.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Case presentation
    <paragraph>Subjective: A 54-year-old man presented to physical therapy with a lifelong history of fatigability that worsened on exertion. Even as a child, he had experienced difficulty going up hills and lagged behind when he went out for a walk with friends. Since his childhood, he had been labeled as “lazy” by family and friends. He consulted several doctors, who were unable to provide an explanation for his symptoms, adding to his unhappiness and resulting in depression. He presented with early fatigue complaints and contractures triggered by dynamic exercise (climbing stairs) during a visit to his mother in hospital. He described a sensation of his legs becoming “stiff like a board” after walking for a while; this symptom was relieved by rest. These symptoms were worse if he was hungry and were alleviated after meals. There were no diurnal fluctuations in symptoms. There was no neuromuscular disease in his family history. He had depression and a long history of alcohol abuse. He had been receiving long-term treatment with tianeptine, bromazepam, omeprazole, and silymarin.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[1]Demographic Information: 54 y/o male; currently employed as a CPAMedical Diagnosis: N/ACo-morbidities: Obese, long history of alcohol abuse, 1 pack per day smokerPrevious care or treatment: Received physical therapy three years ago following R TKRSelf-Report Outcome Measures: Pain at rest 2/10; RPE with moderate activity 12Physical Performance Measures: During 5 Time Sit to Stand, pt expressed fatigue following one repetition; global MMT of UE is a 4-/5, global MMT of LE is a 3+/5; ROM 50% for hamstrings, gastrocs, and hip flexors</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Physical therapist referred the patient to his primary care provider for additional testing. Results were as follows.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Impression
    <paragraph>Pt has significantly decreased aerobic capacity, decreased strength in all large muscle groups, decreased ROM in the LE, and general intolerance to exercise.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>Outcomes (PT 8 weeks)</section>
  <section>
    Outcomes (medical)
    <paragraph>Repeat check performed after cessation of treatment revealed a CK level of 2945 U/L. There was no myoglobinuria</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Pt was discharged from therapy after reaching goals and demonstrating an active role in his disease management. He began managing his diet well per McArdle's Disease diet recommendations and lost 10 pounds throughout his 8 weeks in physical therapy.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Acknowledgements
    <paragraph>Case adapted from “McArdle Disease: A case report and review”</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Related Pages
    <paragraph>Physiopedia: McArdle's Disease</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.1Leite A, Oliveira N, Rocha M. McArdle disease: a case report and review. International Medical Case Reports Journal. 2012.</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
</document>
