<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Hamstring strain</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Alchemy in motion</source>
  <url>https://www.alchemyinmotion.com.au/case-studies/sports-musculoskeletal-case-studies/hamstring-strain-case-study/</url>
  <parent_folder>Hamstring</parent_folder>
  <section>
    HAMSTRING STRAIN CASE STUDY
    <paragraph>This case study explores a patient we had a little while ago who experienced a hamstring strain.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    How they presented / Mechanism of Injury:
    <list>
      <item>73 y.o. Male</item>
      <item>Reported “He forgot he was no longer 40 and decided to join a social soccer team.”</item>
      <item>Played a game 3 days prior to presenting. He reported that during the game he went to kick the ball and felt a big pull up the back of his thigh. He decided it was okay and continued to play on. He got through the remainder of the game walking, but was sore.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Self management (between injury and presenting to physio):
    <list>
      <item>He iced his thigh that night and woke up the next morning stiff and sore. He reported that since the injury (3 days prior), he had been limping every day.</item>
      <item>He was stretching every day but was experiencing a lot of pain while stretching.</item>
      <item>He was taking nurofen 2x daily.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Aggravating activities / factors:
    <list>
      <item>Walking</item>
      <item>Stairs</item>
      <item>Getting out of car</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Assessment:
    <list>
      <item>Squat – to 90 degrees okay but quads a bit sore</item>
      <item>Lunge – 1/2 range and pain in quads on forward leg</item>
      <item>Double leg bridge – able nil pain</item>
      <item>Single leg bridge – x3 able, pain mid muscle belly left biceps femoris (hamstring) pain rating: 5/10</item>
      <item>Passive Straight Leg Raise: L) 45 degrees pain in mid belly of left hamstring + R) 55 degrees pain mid hamstring</item>
      <item>Observation: large bruise covering distal ⅓ of posterior thigh on left</item>
      <item>Resisted knee flexion supine: minor awareness but okay Gr 4 strength, able to feel fibres in biceps femoris (hamstring) – not ruptured.</item>
      <item>Palpation: Tender on palpation mid belly biceps femoris (hamstring)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Impression / Diagnosis:
    <image src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="/>
    <image src="https://www.alchemyinmotion.com.au/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Hamstring-Case-Study-768x1024.png"/>
    <paragraph>Left Grade 2 biceps femoris strain, overload bilateral hamstring and quads due to poor conditioning prior to return to soccer.In carrying out a thorough assessment of hamstring strength and length, it was clear that more than 50% of the hamstring fibres were strained but the hamstring did not sustain a full thickness tear.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Treatment:
    <list>
      <item>Education re: needing to hold off stretching for a few days to ensure that the tear did not worsen. Gentle stretching okay but no more than 1/10 pain rating</item>
      <item>Soft Tissue Massage to hamstrings and glutes.</item>
      <item>Education Re: conditioning and need to prepare the body for new activity.</item>
      <item>Home exercise programme:Progressed through concentric (shortening) then eccentric (lengthening) hamstring programGradual return to running drills</item>
      <item>Progressed through concentric (shortening) then eccentric (lengthening) hamstring program</item>
      <item>Gradual return to running drills</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Progressed through concentric (shortening) then eccentric (lengthening) hamstring program</item>
      <item>Gradual return to running drills</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome:
    <paragraph>Patient successfully returned to play 6 weeks post injury!</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
