<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title> Physical Therapy &amp; Myesthenia Gravis</title>
  <source>PT Case Study extracted from Capital Area Physical Therapy &amp; Wellness</source>
  <url>https://capitalareapt.com/case-study-physical-therapy-myesthenia-gravis/</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>PT for Myesthenia Gravis Case Study</section>
  <section>
    History
    <paragraph>A 67-year-old female presented to the clinic approximately 2 weeks after being discharged from the hospital with a diagnosis of an acute Myesthenia Gravis (MG) crisis. MG is a neuromuscular (effecting nerves that tell muscles what to do) autoimmune disease that causes muscle weakness throughout the body, especially through the proximal (trunk) muscles. The patient had been hospitalized for difficulty with eye movements, inability to swallow, and respiratory failure. The patient underwent medical management and when appropriate, was discharged home and referred to physical therapy.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Evaluation
    <paragraph>At the patient’s first visit, a variety of objective measurements were taken to assess baseline function and assist the therapist in building an individualized plan of care. Some of these measurements included:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Treatment
    <paragraph>Visit 1:Education was provided on activity modification, monitoring fatigue levels, etiology of the current problem, importance of home exercise participation and the plan for future treatments. The patient was educated on exercises to start between the first and second sessions, which included seated exercises to begin to increasing tolerance to exercise.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Follow ups
    <paragraph>As stated, special attention was paid to fatigue levels throughout all remaining sessions, as excessive fatigue can set off a MG flare-up. The patient worked toward their functional goals (independent bed mobility, gait, transfers, navigating stairs, and returning to work). She also began using the recumbent bicycle to increase cardiovascular endurance as well. Therapeutic activities included: sit to stand practice, step up endurance, balance activities, postural strengthening and core activation.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Results
    <paragraph>After 1 month of physical therapy the patient improved:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The patient continues to attend physical therapy 2-3 days/week to progress strength, endurance and overall function.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For more information on this case study, PT for myesthenia gravis, or to make an appointment for an evaluation or treatment, contact us at one of ourthree physical therapy clinicsin Queensbury, Malta or Saratoga NY at518-289-5242.</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
