<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Commercial Determinants of Health Case Study</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Commercial_Determinants_of_Health_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>Commercial Determinants of Health Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Maya is a physiotherapist working at a community health centre located in an urban neighbourhood with high rates of chronic diseases. The area has limited green spaces, a high density of fast-food outlets, and aggressive street marketing of alcohol and tobacco products. Many residents have low incomes and limited health literacy.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Maya has noticed a concerning pattern among her rehabilitation patients who have co-morbidities, such as type 2 diabetes and obesity: many of her patients struggle to adhere to their rehabilitation plans and maintain healthy behaviours outside the clinic.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Maya's patient is Carlos, a 45-year-old warehouse worker. Carlos is attending physiotherapy for a low back injury. Carlos's medical history includes type 2 diabetes and obesity. Despite initial progress in his rehabilitation programme, Carlos is finding it increasingly difficult to reach his exercise targets. He has also put on 2 kilograms and is struggling to stick to a healthy eating plan, despite multiple education sessions on proper nutrition.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>In their discussion, Maya discovers several factors, or commercial determinants of health, that appear to be impacting Carlos.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Exposure to marketing: Carlos's daily commute takes him past numerous fast-food outlets with prominent billboards advertising value meals. His neighbourhood has three times more fast-food establishments than grocery stores.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Economic practices: Carlos mentions that healthier food options cost significantly more than processed alternatives, especially since a major supermarket chain closed its local store.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Digital influence: Carlos has been using a "free" fitness app that continuously promotes premium supplements and meal replacement products as necessary for recovery.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Workplace environment: Carlos's employer has vending machines filled with ultra-processed snacks and sugary drinks but limited facilities for storing or preparing healthy meals.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Maya recognises that education on healthy eating and exercise is insufficient as Carlos is constantly bombarded by advertisements for fast-food and snacks, all at a lower-price to healthier food options. Maya took a number of steps to help address these issues with Carlos.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Maya worked with Carlos to increase his health literacy. She helped Carlos recognise marketing tactics used by food and beverage companies. She showed how certain food manufacturers use terminology to describe their food products to make them sound healthier than they are, which creates a false impression about the nutritional value of this product.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>She also helped Carlos develop critical evaluation skills. Together, they reviewed the fitness app Carlos was using, identifying how it subtly promotes unnecessary products through testimonials and "scientific claims."</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Maya helped Carlos find practical alternatives solutions. Together, they identified affordable, healthier food options. They also explored exercise and movement options that don't require expensive equipment or supplements.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Maya also helped create personalised strategies for Carlosto navigate his food environment, such as planning routes that avoid fast-food stores and triggering marketing. They also explored options to prepare meals at home.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Maya realises that Carlos's challenges reflect systemic issues affecting many patients in her community. She decided to involve her coworkers in activities that address these issues. As a team, theydeveloped a community-based programme.This involved a weekly group session held at the health centre that focused on building "commercial determinant resilience" through shared experiences and solutions.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>They alsocollaboratedwith a local community garden to provide affordable access to fresh produce and create a social support network for physical activity, anddeveloped health literacy materialsin three languages. These materials explained how commercial interests shape health environments and behaviours. These materials were distributed throughout the health centre.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Maya understands that lasting change requires action and structural change at a higher level. She became involved with policy-level advocacy in a number of ways.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Professional leadership: Maya presented data from her practice at professional physiotherapy conferences, highlighting the impact of commercial determinants on rehabilitation outcomes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Institutional policies: She successfully advocated for her health centre to implement a policy refusing sponsorship from ultra-processed food and beverage companies for health events.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Local government engagement: Maya joined a coalition of healthcare professionals providing testimony to the city council about the relationship between fast-food outlet density and rehabilitation outcomes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Media engagement: She started writing evidence-based articles for local newspapers about how commercial forces influence recovery from injury and chronic disease management.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>The combined interventions at the individual, population, and policy levels have contributed to Carlos's progress in his rehabilitation programme and initiated changes that benefitted the entire community. Carlos reported that he has become more aware of marketing influences and has developed strategies to navigate his environment more effectively.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The community-based programme started at Maya's health centre has grown to include 30 regular participants who support each other in recognising and resisting harmful commercial influences. The health centre has implemented a comprehensive policy on commercial relationships and expanded its focus on commercial determinants of health in patient education. Finally, the city council has begun considering zoning regulations to limit the concentration of fast-food outlets near healthcare facilities and schools.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Conclusion
    <paragraph>Rehabilitation professionals have a unique opportunity to identify and address commercial determinants due to their ongoing relationships with patients and focus on function in real-world environments. They can contribute to meaningful improvements in health equity by operating at the individual, population, and policy levels.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>When working with patients, it's important to recognise that effective interventions will address individual behaviours while recognising the powerful commercial forces that shape those behaviours. Understanding commercial determinants of health can help achieve sustainable rehabilitation outcomes, particularly for vulnerable populations.</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
