<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Continuum of Care of a Patient with Burns</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Continuum_of_Care_of_a_Patient_with_Burns</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>Continuum of Care of a Patient with Burns</section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>Burn injuries are a global public health problem.[1]They can cause significant disability, and recovering from burn injuries can be a long, painful, and traumatic journey. Burn injuries can impact an individual's family life, work, school, recreation, and social life. Therefore, rehabilitation professionals must have knowledge of effective burn management to optimise quality of life in burn survivors. This article reviews the fundamentals of burn injury evaluation and treatment for rehabilitation professionals from the early acute phase to the community / outpatient phase.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Factors Impacting Recovery
    <paragraph>Many factors can impact post-burn recovery. The following factors can have anegative impacton successful post-burn recovery.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medical factors:[2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Psychosocial factors:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The ability to adaptto the post-burn state can be facilitated by (1) good social and peer support, (2) adaptive coping mechanisms,[6][7]and (3) critical thinking.[4]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Initial Assessment
    <paragraph>Burn location and depth:[2]burn wounds are classified by location and depth (superficial, superficial partial thickness, deep partial thickness, full thickness and subcutaneous). Please seeClassification by Depthfor a detailed discussion.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Total body surface area (TBSA): is commonly calculated using the Lund and Browder chart.[8]This method includes burn areas that are partial thickness and full thickness, but excludes superficial areas.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Wound assessment:it is important to assess the wound when the dressing is taken down. When assessing the wound without the dressing, check for the following wound characteristics:[2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Please seeBurn Wound Assessmentfor more information.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Pain assessment:the depth of the burn determines the degree of pain.[2]In the acute phase, superficial burns cause greater pain while areas of full-thickness burns are usually pain-free because of damage to nerve endings. However, full-thickness burns are typically surrounded by areas of more superficial injury. Therefore, patients with full-thickness burns can report as much pain as patients who sustained a superficial injury.[9]Burn pain mechanisms vary, and include:[9]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Each type of pain requires different interventions. For in-depth information on pain management in individuals with burn injuries, please see this optional article:Burn Injury Management Considerations for Rehabilitation Professionals.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    PreoperativeManagement
    <paragraph>Goals include:[2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Interventions can include:[2]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Surgical Management for Burn Injuries
    <paragraph>Early excision and closure of the burn wound help prevent infection and reduce secondary complications associated with burn scars. Reconstructive burn surgery helps to restore function to the affected area, thus improving the quality of life of individuals with burn injuries.[11]It is important to note that patients with burn injuries typically requiremultiple rounds of surgery.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Surgical Procedures
    <paragraph>The International Society for Burn Injury recommends early excision and grafting of deep partial-thickness burns. This approach shortens the recovery time, reduces pain and improves long-term scar outcomes.[12]In addition, early wound closure enables an earlier transition into rehabilitation programmes.[13]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The following treatment strategies are used in burn care:[2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>More information on skin grafts is availablehere. Please watch the following optional videos if you would like to see how hand and elbow splints are applied:</paragraph>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/3sk8nqL1hJ0?"/>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/pT6KJ0HeAY8?"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Splint Schedule
    <paragraph>When considering a splint schedule for a patient with burn injuries, remember the following. (1) A splint is typically kept on for five days, (2) daily splint checks should be performed, and (3) the splint should be taken down at the same time as the postoperative dressings are taken down. This enables visualisation of the grafts so a decision can be made on continued splint use and if the patient can begin active range of motion exercises.[2]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Postoperative Management
    <paragraph>Goals include:[2]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Physiotherapy Interventions
    <paragraph>General guidelines:[2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Interventions include:[2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>If you want to learn more about interventions for burn injuries, please see:Burn Wound Healing Considerations and Recovery Care InterventionsandBurn Injury Management Considerations for Rehabilitation Professionals.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outpatient and Community Phase of Burn Rehabilitation Process
    <paragraph>Once discharged home, burn survivors will transition to outpatient and community-based care. The rehabilitation team will establish an individualised patient-centred programme to achieve lasting outcomes. The following interventions may be included in the programme:</paragraph>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/oKszhYKy-9w?"/>
    <paragraph>[22]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Resources</section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑World Health Organization.Burns. 2020. Available from: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/burns [Accessed 15 May 2024].</item>
      <item>↑2.002.012.022.032.042.052.062.072.082.092.102.112.12Webster L. Rehabilitation of a Patient with Burns from Hospital to Home Course. Plus, 2024.</item>
      <item>↑Dukes K, Baldwin S, Assimacopoulos E, Grieve B, Hagedorn J, Wibbenmeyer L.Influential Factors in the Recovery Process of Burn Survivors in a Predominately Rural State: A Qualitative Study.J Burn Care Res. 2022 Mar 23;43(2):374-380.</item>
      <item>↑4.04.14.24.34.4Woolard A, Bullman I, Allahham A, Long T, Milroy H, Wood F, Martin L.Resilience and Posttraumatic Growth after Burn: A Review of Barriers, Enablers, and Interventions to Improve Psychological Recovery.European Burn Journal. 2022; 3(1):89-121.</item>
      <item>↑Browne G, Byrne C, Brown B, Pennock M, Streiner D, Roberts R, Eyles P, Truscott D, Dabbs R. Psychosocial adjustment of burn survivors. Burns Incl Therm Inj. 1985 Oct;12(1):28-35.</item>
      <item>↑Zare-Kaseb A, Hajialibeigloo R, Dadkhah-Tehrani M, Otaghsara SMT, Zeydi AE, Ghazanfari MJ. Role of mindfulness in improving psychological well-being of burn survivors. Burns. 2023 Jun;49(4):984-985.</item>
      <item>↑Al-Ghabeesh SH. Coping strategies, social support, and mindfulness improve the psychological well-being of Jordanian burn survivors: A descriptive correlational study. Burns. 2022 Feb;48(1):236-243.</item>
      <item>↑Rice PL, Orgill DP. Assessment and classification of burn injury. Available fromhttps://www.uptodate.com/contents/assessment-and-classification-of-burn-injury[last accessed 8/5/2024].</item>
      <item>↑9.09.1Morgan M, Deuis JR, Frøsig-Jørgensen M, Lewis RJ, Cabot PJ, Gray PD, Vetter I.Burn Pain: A Systematic and Critical Review of Epidemiology, Pathophysiology, and Treatment. Pain Med. 2018 Apr 1;19(4):708-734.</item>
      <item>↑Cartotto R, Johnson L, Rood JM, Lorello D, Matherly A, Parry I, Romanowski K, Wiechman S, Bettencourt A, Carson JS, Lam HT, Nedelec B.Clinical Practice Guideline: Early Mobilization and Rehabilitation of Critically Ill Burn Patients. J Burn Care Res. 2023 Jan 5;44(1):1-15.</item>
      <item>↑Żwierełło W, Piorun K, Skórka-Majewicz M, Maruszewska A, Antoniewski J, Gutowska I.Burns: Classification, Pathophysiology, and Treatment: A Review.Int J Mol Sci. 2023 Feb 13;24(4):3749.</item>
      <item>↑Salemans RFC, van Uden D, van Baar ME, Haanstra TM, van Schie CHM, van Zuijlen PPM, Lucas Y, Scholten-Jaegers SMHJ, Meij-de Vries A, Wood FM, Edgar DW, Spronk I, van der Vlies CH; National Burn Care, Education &amp; Research group, the Netherlands.Timing of surgery in acute deep partial-thickness burns: A study protocol.PLoS One. 2024 Mar 11;19(3):e0299809.</item>
      <item>↑Wong L, Rajandram R, Allorto N. Systematic review of excision and grafting in burns: Comparing outcomes of early and late surgery in low and high-income countries. Burns. 2021 Dec;47(8):1705-1713.</item>
      <item>↑14.014.1Niţescu C, Calotă DR, Florescu IP, Lascăr I.Surgical options in extensive burns management.J Med Life. 2012 Oct-Dec;5(Spec Issue):129-136.</item>
      <item>↑15.015.115.2Wong L, Robert J. Spence RJ. Escharotomy and fasciotomy of the burned upper extremity. Hand Clinics 2000; 16(2):165-174.</item>
      <item>↑Parry IS, Schneider JC, Yelvington M, Sharp P, Serghiou M, Ryan CM, Richardson E, Pontius K, Niszczak J, McMahon M, MacDonald LE, Lorello D, Kehrer CK, Godleski M, Forbes L, Duch S, Crump D, Chouinard A, Calva V, Bills S, Benavides L, Acharya HJ, De Oliveira A, Boruff J, Nedelec B.Systematic Review and Expert Consensus on the Use of Orthoses (Splints and Casts) with Adults and Children after Burn Injury to Determine Practice Guidelines.J Burn Care Res. 2020 May 2;41(3):503-534.</item>
      <item>↑UW Surgery. Burns 403: Hand Splints.  Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3sk8nqL1hJ0[last accessed 10/5/2024]</item>
      <item>↑UW Surgery. Burns 402: Elbow Splints.  Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pT6KJ0HeAY8[last accessed 10/5/2024]</item>
      <item>↑Richard RL, Lester ME, Miller SF, Bailey JK, Hedman TL, Dewey WS, Greer M, Renz EM, Wolf SE, Blackbourne LH.Identification of cutaneous functional units related to burn scar contracture development.J Burn Care Res. 2009 Jul-Aug;30(4):625-31.</item>
      <item>↑Parry I, Richard R, Aden JK, Yelvington M, Ware L, Dewey W, Jacobson K, Caffrey J, Sen S.Goniometric Measurement of Burn Scar Contracture: A Paradigm Shift Challenging the Standard.J Burn Care Res. 2019 Jun 21;40(4):377-385.</item>
      <item>↑Ault P, Plaza A, Paratz J. Scar massage for hypertrophic burns scarring-A systematic review. Burns. 2018 Feb;44(1):24-38.</item>
      <item>↑Asociación Pro-Niños Quemados de Nicaragua. Massage Techniques - Burned Patient Rehabilitation. Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oKszhYKy-9w[last accessed 10/5/2024]</item>
      <item>↑Robertson K, Wang D, Tran K, Yun E, Stevens K, Hartman B. 571 Effectiveness of Compression Garments with Silicone versus Compression Garments Alone on Hypertrophic Scar. J Burn Care Res. 2023 May 15;44(Suppl 2):S118.</item>
      <item>↑Van den Kerckhove E, Anthonissen M. Compression Therapy and Conservative Strategies in Scar Management After Burn Injury. 2020 Dec 8. In: Téot L, Mustoe TA, Middelkoop E, Gauglitz GG, editors. Textbook on Scar Management: State of the Art Management and Emerging Technologies [Internet]. Cham (CH): Springer; 2020. Chapter 27.</item>
      <item>↑De Decker I, Beeckman A, Hoeksema H, De Mey K, Verbelen J, De Coninck P, et al. Pressure therapy for scars: Myth or reality? A systematic review. Burns. 2023 Jun;49(4):741-56.</item>
      <item>↑Merwarth D. Management of Burn Wounds Programme. Burn Wound Healing and Recovery Care Course. Plus, 2024.</item>
      <item>↑Lanham JS, Nelson NK, Hendren B, Jordan TS.Outpatient Burn Care: Prevention and Treatment. Am Fam Physician. 2020;101(8):463-470.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
