<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Gastric Cancer Case Studies</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Gastric_Cancer_Case_Studies</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>Title: The Management Of Double Neoplasms: A Case Of A Patient With Small Cell Lung And Gastric Cancer Successfully Treated With Chemotherapy</section>
  <section>
    Authors
    <paragraph>David Rossi Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro ItalyPaolo Alessandroni Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro ItalyStefano Luzi Fedeli Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro ItalyAnna Fedeli Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro ItalyPaolo Giordani Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro ItalyVincenzo Catalano Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro ItalyAnna Maria Balzelli Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro ItalyV. Casadei Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro ItalyGiuseppina Catalano Medical Oncology Unit, S. Salvatore Hospital Pesaro Italy</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Case report involving a patient with double synchronous neoplasm, small cell lung and gastric cancer, successfully treated with chemotherapy. The cancers responded well to the treatment of chemotherapy, with partial remission of the gastric cancer and complete remission of the lung cancer.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Patient Characteristics</section>
  <section>Examination</section>
  <section>Clinical Impression</section>
  <section>
    Summarization of Examination Findings
    <paragraph>It was the patient’s first time in the oncology unit, and his physical examination was unremarkable. After he was given a gastroscopy, it was suspected he had gastric cancer (confirmed by biopsy). The patient was also given a CT scan which found lung cancer (confired through bronchoscopy).</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>
    Outcomes
    <paragraph>Treatment led to complete remission of lung cancer and partial remission of gastric cancer, however cancer did metastasize to the brain and the pt. rapidly regressed and died.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>This case could show the optimal treatment for pt’s with double neoplasms. While the pt’s ultimate outcome was death, the purpose of the case study was to show the effects of this particular chemotherapy treatment cycle, which showed significant improvement in the pt’s original dx. The downfall to this study was it did not recognize any outcome measures, and it failed to measure the pt’s quality of life throughout their treatment regimen.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Related Pages
    <paragraph>add links to related pages here</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <paragraph>References will automatically be added here, seeadding references tutorial.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>1. Balat O., Kudelka A.P., Ro J.Y., Edwards C.L., Balbay D., Dinney C., Kavanagh J.J.: Two synchronous primary tumors of the ovary and kidney: a case report. Eur. J. Gynecol. Oncol 1996, 17: 257-2592. Arimura T., Mitani M., Shimotakahara T., Maenohara S., Yamamoto S., Baba K., Tanaka T., Yunoki K., Takenoshita M., Nishi M.: Three operated cases of synchronous double cancers in the lung and stomach. A review of the Japanese Literature. Gan. No. Rinsho 1984, 30: 283-2913. Nosaka S., Yamauchi N., Sasaky T., Hanada T., Tamura K.: Clinical study of synchronous double cancer of the lung and digestive tract. Kyobu Geka 1998, 51: 400-4024. Morimoto M., Ohno T., Yamashita Y., Honda M., Asada S.: Two surgical cases of synchronous double carcinoma of the lung and esophagus and review of 10 documented cases in Japan. Nippon Kyobu Geka Gakkai Zasshi 1991, 39: 245-2505. Fukuda H., Ogino N., Takao T., Kobayashi S., Kido T. A case report of synchronous double cancer of the lung and esophagus: Nippon Kyobu Geka Gakkai Zasshi 1990, 38: 1053-10586. Morio A., Miyamoto H., Ou T., Izumi H., Futagawa T., Hosoda Y.: A case of synchronous resection of double cancers in the lung and stomach through median sternotomy and abdominal incision. Kyobu Geka 1998, 51: 338-3417. Kogan E.A., Sklianskaia O.A., Denisova O.P., Berestova A.V., Uspenskii L.V.: Association of small peripheral lung cancer and early stomach cancer. Arkh. Patol. 1983, 45:60-668. Sano T., Saijo N., Sasaky Y., Shinkai T., Eguchi K., Tamura T., Sakurai M., Takahashi H., Nakano H., Tajiri H.: A case report of synchronous small cell lung cancer and gastric cancer successfully treated with carboplatin. Jpn. J. Cancer Res. 1986, 77: 790-7989. Yamamoto S., Yokoama K., Kusaka Y.: An autopsy case of pulmonary asbestosis with synchronous multiprimary lung cancers, early gastric cancer and atypical micobacteriosis. Nihon Kyobu Shikkan Gakky</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
