<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Hashimoto's Thyroiditis Case Study</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Hashimoto%27s_Thyroiditis_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Hashimoto's Thyroiditis Case Study
    <paragraph>Original Editor-Kerri Falk</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Top Contributors-Kerri FalkandRucha Gadgil</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Hashimoto’s thyroiditis is an autoimmune disease.Hashimoto’sthyroiditis is often associated with arthralgia, myalgia, can lead to myopathy. Physical therapy can assist with the neuromuscular and musculoskeletal materializations that are seen in many patients with the condition.[1]Physical therapy emphasis is on restoring the secondary effects of the disease such as restoration of joint range of motion, alleviation ofpainin joints and muscles, and restoring strength due to muscle weakness. This case study depicts what may be seen in a patient coming to Physical therapy with Hashimoto’s thyroiditis as well as clinical impression, interventions, and outcomes.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>Hashimoto’s thyroiditis was first discovered in 1912 by Japanese physician Hakaru Hashimoto (1881−1934). Hashimoto's thyroiditis or chronic lymphocytic thyroiditis is an organ specificautoimmunedisease in which thethyroidgland is attacked by cell and antibody mediated responses[1]. Hashimoto’s is the most common cause ofhypothyroidismin the United States[2]. Incidence is estimated to be 3.5 per 1000 per year in women and 0.8 per 1000 per year in men, or 1-2% of the population.[2]The disease slowly can progress over time into thyroid deficiency. Musculoskeletal and neuromuscular manifestations can occur at any time during the disease process.[1]According to a study by Cakir M, Samanci N, Balci N, Balci MK adhesive capsulitis,Dupuytren’scontracture,triggerfinger, limited joint mobility andcarpal tunnel syndromehave all been found in patients with hypothyroidism.[3]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Case Presentation
    <paragraph>Susan is a 46 year old elementary school teacher. She reports that she has been feeling more fatigued over the last couple of months compared to previously. She attributed it to beginning a new school year. Susan complains of feeling overall muscle aches and stiffness especially at her neck during that time that was not progressed or lessened. It has not been relieved with ibuprofen or heat. Patient has a tender palpable mass on the anterior aspect of her neck. Personal and familial history of hypothyroidism. Cervical and thoracic ROM limited in several directions.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Clinical Impression</section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Referred patient to her PCP for follow up and called physician to discuss findingsDiscussed POC with patient 2x week for 4 weeks</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Outcomes:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The Anti-thyroid Antibody test run on Susan showed she was positive for the antibodies indicating she was experiencing Hashimoto’s thyroiditis. Her doctor changed her Synthroid dose and referred her back to physical therapy for treatment of carpal tunnel. After having her medication dosage changed coupled with the physical therapy she received for her carpal tunnel symptoms, Susan was able to increase her range of motion:45ocervical extension20ocervical flexion50ocervical rotation25ocervical side-bending bilaterally25ospine flexionThe goiter in her neck prevented her from achieving more range of motion in her neck.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>There is limited research on physical therapy to treat Hashimoto’s thyroiditis, however, Physical therapists are able to treat the musculoskeletal impairments secondary to the disease. Recent studies show it is not uncommon for persons with hypothyroidism to have carpal tunnel syndrome[4]among other musculoskeletal impairments. Physical therapist discretion must be used and thorough differential diagnosis must be performed in order to carefully screen for rheumatic and certain neurological diseases which are a contraindication for manipulation. More research must be performed in the area of how physical therapy can assist patients who are experiencing musculoskeletal impairments secondary to hypothyroid dysfunction.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.11.2http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/120937-overviewaccessed 3/21/17</item>
      <item>↑2.02.1https://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/condition/hashimoto-thyroiditis#statisticsaccessed 3/21/17</item>
      <item>↑Cakir M, Samanci N, Balci N, Balci MK. Musculoskeletal manifestations in patients with thyroid disease. Clinical Endocrinology. 2003;59(2):162-7</item>
      <item>↑Karne SS, Bhalero NS. Carpal Tunnel Syndrome in Hypothyroidism. (internet).           Journal of clinical and diagnostic research : JCDR. U.S. National Library of Medicine; 2016 (cited 2017Mar24). Available from: https//:www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27042500</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
