<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Hypokalemia Case Study</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Hypokalemia_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Abstract - Hypokalemia Characteristics
    <paragraph>Hypokalemiais defined by potassium serum levels below 3.5mEq/L. Patients commonly diagnosed with thiselectrolyteimbalance include individuals who are ondiureticssuch as Lasix or laxatives. Other common causes may include chronic diarrhea, vomiting,malnourishment,alcoholism,burns, gastric suction-NG. Individuals withCushing's syndromemay experience hypokalemia, however those withGuillain Barre syndromemay mimic the signs and symptoms of hypokalemia[1].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Patients with hypokalemia may present with signs and symptoms of:
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>muscle cramping/damagefasiculationsparalytic ileustetanyrhabdomyolysisweakness (can lead to paresis/paralysis)</td>
        <td>anorexianauseafatigue/confusion/lethargyedemarespiratory failurehypoventilationat very low levels ventricular tachycardia may occur</td>
        <td>arrhythmiasabdominal distentionconstipationhypotensioncardiac arrest/rhythm disturbance</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>[2][3][4]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Associated Co-morbidites:</section>
  <section>Differential Diagnosis:</section>
  <section>
    Patient Characteristics
    <paragraph>Patient:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medical Diagnosis:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Co-morbidities:PMH ofCoronary Artery disease. S/P CABG,IDDM,HTN, CKD stage 3.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Previous care or treatment:Patient has had multiple hospital admissions for acute exacerbation of systolic heart failure and respiratory distress secondary to fluid overload.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination
    <paragraph>Algorithm for the evaluation and treatment of nocturnal leg cramps.[5]</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/c/ce/Leg_cramp.gif"/>
    <paragraph>Shortly after medical attention was provided:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gross MMT:UE: Shoulder abduction: 2-/5Bilat.; Shoulder flexion: 2/5 Bilat.; Shoulder Extension: 2-/5 Bilat.;  Elbow Flexion: 2+/5 Bilat.; Elbow extension: 2/5 Bilat.; Wrist Flexion: 3+/5 Bilat.; Wrist Extension: 3+/5 Bilat.; and Grip strength: 3+/5 Bilat.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>LE: Hip Flexion: Hip Ext: 2-/5 Bilat.; Hip Abd: 2/5 Bilat.; Knee Flexion:2/5 Bilat.; Knee Extension: 2+/5 Bilat.; Ankle DF: 2/5 Bilat.; Ankle PF: 2+/5</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Reflexes:UE: Bilat. 2+;  LE: Bilat 1+</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Sensation:Normal</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Bed Mobility: Pt unable to perform; maximum assistance would be required</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Transfers: Pt unable to perform; maximum assistance would be required</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Posture:Pt unable to stand; presents in supine with bed intrendelenburgposition</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Static Stance:Pt unable to stand due to weakness</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gait:Unable to assess</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ambulation:Unable to assess</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Impression:
    <paragraph>Physician's Impression:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>1. Acute hypoxic respiratory failure secondary pulmonary edema2. Acute on chronic CHF exacerbation3. Hypokalemia and hypomagnesium secondary to loop diuretics</paragraph>
    <paragraph>ICF Findings:[6]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Impairments:Patient is lethargic and has difficulty breathing on minimal exertion (appears winded at rest).Patient exhibits a decrease in overall muscle strength and diminished reflexes in the LE.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Activity Limitations:Patient is unable to ambulate due to weakness and fatigue.Patient is unable to complete simple task due to fatigue and respiratory distress.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Summarization of Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Based on the patient's subjective and objective findings, patient's cardiopulmonary complications and co-morbidities have lead to an exacerbation of her CHF and hypokalemia in symptoms. The targeted interventions include replacing potassium via IV and monitor for other possible electrolyte imbalances. The patient's diuretics should be monitored accordingly since it may lead to unwanted side effects such as this. The goal is to make patient euvolemic, and if the patient is unable to do so with diuretics a nephrologist should be consulted for possible for hemodialysis. Upon discharge the patient will need potassium supplements in accordance with her loop diuretic therapy. BMP will need to be re-checked in 1 week and the patient should be referred to a heart failure clinic or rehab in one week for monitoring.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Targeted Intervention (Medical):</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Targeted Intervention (Physical Therapy):</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Once potassium levels have normalized, physical therapist will reassess the patient. Before ambulating patient from bed, physical therapist will continue to monitor vitals throughout treatment session. Therapist should address any impairments and functional deficits patient may display during treatment session. Since patient presents with respiratory insufficiency, PT is encouraged to perform exercises and educate patient on breathing exercises to improve oxygen consumption and energy conservation. PT should assist physician in deciding if the patient should return back to nursing home or be referred to skilled nursing facility for further treatment and monitoring.Phases of Interventions:Phase 1- Since patient is suffering from pulmonary edema secondary to acute hypoxic respiratory failure, physical therapy will assist pt on breathing exercises, postural drainage (precaution for PE), vibration and percussion. Educate patient on deep breathing and sitting posture to minimize the fluid accumulation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Phase 2- Patient is classified as NYHA class 3 meaning patient has marked limitation of physical activity. She is comfortable at rest but less than ordinary activity causes fatigue, palpitation, dyspnea or anginal pain.[7]Physical therapy should be aware of these symptoms and get the patient out of bed to work on mobility. Physical therapy will monitor O2 sats before, during, and after the treatment sessions and patient will be able to rate their fatigue level on Perceive Level of Exertion Scale. Physical therapy will teach and educate patient on energy conservation technique.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Phase 3- Usually patients with pulmonary edema have an average stay of 5-7 days. During this time physical therapy should work with patient everyday to improve their physical limitations while monitoring vitals and fatigue levels.</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>IV Lasix 40mg q8hr</item>
      <item>IV potassium chloride bolus 40mg times 2 and recheck potassium in 4 hours</item>
      <item>IV magnesium sulfate bolus 2gm</item>
      <item>Consult cardiologist</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Deep breathing, percussion and vibration: Initiate first with deep breathing exercises.</item>
      <item>Percussion and Vibration 3-5 minute per segment, perform on most congested area on first day.</item>
      <item>Follow with deep breathing, coughing, suctioning as needed.</item>
      <item>Aerobic: low impact and short distance ambulation as per patient's tolerance. Progress to longer distance and stairs while monitoring O2 sats and patient's fatigue levels.</item>
      <item>Strength: In-bed exercises to strengthen weakened muscles and increase blood flow throughout body. Exercises may include ankle pumps, isometric quad/hamstring contractions, heel slides, straight-leg raises, glute isometrics, 4-way Thera-band hip flexion, abduction, adduction, and extension: 2-3 sets x 10 reps (or to patient tolerance).</item>
    </list>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/3/3c/Percussion_and_vibration.jpeg/450px-Percussion_and_vibration.jpeg"/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>Photo: Examples of positioning for percussion and vibration</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Goal is to progress patient to or near their prior level of function.</item>
      <item>Increase endurance to decrease fatigued levels and improve quality of life.</item>
      <item>Increase patients activity tolerance level while minimizing NYHA classification level.[7]</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcomes
    <paragraph>According to the physician's recommendation, patient was treated with potassium chloride, magnesium sulfate, and lasix. Patient's potassium levels were normalized in about 4 hours. According to Turcotte et al., treatment of any acute episode of muscle weakness includes providing a secure airway, effective ventilation, and circulatory stabilization. Normalization of potassium may include an oral supplement of 0.2 to 0.4 mmol/kg every 15 to 30 minutes over 1 to 3 hours with a total dose nto to exceed 200 mEg in 24 hours in order to avoid rebound hyperkalemia and its associated sequelae.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Pt Case: PT Assessment five hours after treatment was provided and Potassium level retured to normal:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gross MMT:UE: Shoulder abduction: 4/5Bilat.; Shoulder flexion: 4/5 Bilat.; Shoulder Extension: 4-/5 Bilat.; Elbow Flexion: 4/5 Bilat.; Elbow extension: 4-/5 Bilat.; Wrist Flexion: 4/5 Bilat.; Wrist Extension: 4/5 Bilat.; and Grip strength: 4+/5 Bilat.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>LE: Hip Flexion: Hip Ext: 4-/5 Bilat.; Hip Abd: 3+/5 Bilat.; Knee Flexion:4+/5 Bilat.; Knee Extension: 4+/5 Bilat.; Ankle DF: 5/5 Bilat.; Ankle PF: 4+/5</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Reflexes:UE: Bilat. 2+; LE: Bilat 2+</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Sensation: Normal, slight edema still noted on the ankles.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Bed Mobility:Pt able to perform bed mobility transfers (rolling, sitting edge of bed, supine to side-lying to prone to side-lying and supine) in both directions independently.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Transfers:Pt able to perform transfer from chair to bed and bed to chair with contact-guard assistance.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Posture:Pt's posture presents with forward-head and rounded shoulders, kyphotic posture noted. Patient is able to weight bear evenly on both feet.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Static Stance:Pt able to stand for 25 seconds with contact-guard assistance before postural sway was noted.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gait:Pt presented with slow steppage gait pattern with and without use of cane. Pt still remained in kyphotic posture with limited arm swing and trunk mobility.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ambulation:Pt able to ambulate 43 feet down the hall before becoming fatigued and HR increased by 15bpm. After sitting and resting for two minutes pt was able to return to her room without any complications.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Unlesslab valuesare obtained, the presentation and diagnosis of hypokalemia can be hard to detect and differentially diagnose in some individuals. For patients who have had a history of these attacks, they will eventually become familiar with the symptoms and be able to intervene appropriately by taking prescribed potassium pills/fluids or reporting to the hospital. Although this patient developed hypokalemia secondary to other medical complications and co-morbidities, it is imperative that therapists and other health professionals be aware of the signs and symptoms of this treatable electrolyte imbalance before it becomes fatal. Initially the patient presented with decreased reflexes and muscle strength. Within a few hours after receiving the appropriate care, the patient's levels were able to normalize and previous strength was regained. Hypokalemia also affects the respiratory system and can lead to shallow breathing and tachypnea which can be distressful to the patient.[1]With education, therapy, and proper medications the symptoms of hypokalemia should improve along with respiration. According to Allen et al, evidence has suggested that mildexercise, such as a few minutes on a stationary bike or treadmill before bedtime, can relieve nocturnal leg cramps. If muscle fatigue is a cause, graded exercise and/or physical therapy might be of benefit for some patients.[5]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Related Pages
    <paragraph>http://www.airmedicaljournal.com/article/S1067-991X(13)00079-5/abstract?showall=true=</paragraph>
    <paragraph>http://www.physio-pedia.com/Hypokalemia</paragraph>
    <paragraph>http://www.aafp.org/afp/2012/0815/p350.html</paragraph>
    <paragraph>http://www.mayoclinic.org/symptoms/low-potassium/basics/definition/sym-20050632</paragraph>
    <paragraph>http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/Conditions/HeartFailure/AboutHeartFailure/Classes-of-Heart-Failure_UCM_306328_Article.jsp</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.11.21.3Jackie et al. ( 2013) 'Hypokalemic Periodic Paralysis: Two Cases of Profound Weakness', Air Medical Journal, 32(4), pp. 181-183.</item>
      <item>↑2.02.12.22.31. Lonnemann, E. (2015) Pathophysiology of Complex Patient Problems: Fluid and Electrolyte Disorders Powerpoint, Bellarmine University.</item>
      <item>↑3.03.13.2Goodman, Catherine Cavallaro, and Snyder, Teresa E. Kelly. Differential Diagnosis for Physical Therapists: Screening for Referral, 5th ed. St. Louis, MO: Saunders/Elsevier; 2013.</item>
      <item>↑4.04.14.2Medline Plus. Low potassium level.http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000479.htm(accessed 27 March 2015).</item>
      <item>↑5.05.1Allen, R et al. (2012) 'Nocturnal Leg Cramps', American Family Physician, 86(4) pp. 350-355.</item>
      <item>↑World Health Organization. Towards a Common Language for Functioning, Disability and Health ICF. Geneva, Switzerland: ; 2002.</item>
      <item>↑7.07.1American heart association (2014) Classes of heart failure, Available at:http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/Conditions/HeartFailure/AboutHeartFailure/Classes-of-Heart-Failure_UCM_306328_Article.jsp(Accessed: 29th March 2015).</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
</document>
