<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Low energy</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Witty, Pask &amp; Buckingham</source>
  <url>https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/case-studies/low-energy-red-s/</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Low energy / RED-S
    <paragraph>Presentation:</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/race-695303_1920-306x204.jpg"/>
    <paragraph>Medical</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Dietary assessment</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Goal setting from initial consultation:</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/food-2673724_1920-306x204.jpg"/>
    <paragraph>Monitoring tools: weight, body composition (sum of skinfolds), menstruation</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Review sessions planned at 4, 8 and 12 weeks during which her sum of skinfolds increased 8mm, she felt energy increased during training and had increased running up to 15 minutes. Her periods had still not returned at this point (this can be highly individual even after some weight restoration). She had her first period 5 months after the initial meeting.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The focus of the intervention was education around RED-S, the signs to look out for and a stepwise approach to improving energy availability and confidence in her ability to manage her own nutrition. In this case, she had fallen into a pattern of low energy availability inadvertently following a change in environment and training group. Her training load increased but she didn’t recognise that her fuelling hadn’t increased to compensate. A lot of encouragement was given to ensure she notices the warning signs of low energy availability and to talk with others in the training group about the importance of fuelling well.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Cara Slossworks closely with you, the countries top sports medicine doctors and our physios to resolve these issues as comprehensively as possible.Click herefor more information.</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/themes/wpb2017/images/footer-logos.jpg"/>
  </section>
 
</document>
