<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Mental Health Concerns in Rehabilitation Case Study</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Mental_Health_Concerns_in_Rehabilitation_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>Mental Health Concerns in Rehabilitation Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>This case study illustrates mental health concerns in rehabilitation.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Fatima is a 35-year-old female who was admitted to the hospital following injuries that she sustained from intimate partner violence. During her rehabilitation, she exhibited very high levels of pain catastrophising, low self-efficacy and expressed discomfort with physical touch during therapy sessions. The doctor attending to Fatima recognised that she was in a high level of distress and may feel less comfortable with a male doctor than other patients, given the nature of her reason for attending the hospital, which was due to violence from a male. The doctor offered the opportunity for a female chaperone in the form of a nurse, and Fatima accepted.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>The doctor explained that it was important to conduct an assessment of Fatima's injuries, which would require him to touch her near the site of her injuries. However, he asked her for her consent, which she provided. The doctor followed the steps of seeking consent before acting. So given Fatima's high levels of distress, the doctor thought it was necessary to conduct a brief risk assessment as well, using theSAFE-T framework.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>There were some risks identified, but Fatima was not deemed to be an immediate risk of self-harm or suicide. However, the doctor acknowledged this was not an area of his expertise, and he decided to write to Fatima's general practitioner (GP) to raise concerns about her and her emotional well-being. The doctor also referred her to the in-house psychology service for a more detailed risk assessment. He informed Fatima about these decisions to ensure trust was maintained. The doctor was not going behind the patient's back and doing things without permission. He told Fatima what he was going to do before he did it.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>As mentioned, the doctor wrote to the GP and the psychology service. However, he was also aware of interventions Fatima was likely to need, including physiotherapy and occupational therapy. The doctor asked permission from Fatima to discuss her case with the other professionals involved in her care so that they could approach her with a level of sensitivity that they might not have otherwise. The patient consented to this.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The doctor also asked Fatima if she wanted to be referred to local domestic violence charities, which she said she did. And the referral was made to them.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>In terms of support, a simple but effective form of support was to contact Fatima's extended family and invite them to spend time with her. This helped her feel more at ease in the hospital environment and to get sleep because she felt safe enough to sleep.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Fatima was also assured that her partner would not be able to visit her at the hospital, which further reassured her that she was safe, enabling her to focus on her recovery and rehabilitation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The Pain Catastrophising Scale was used to assess her levels of catastrophic thinking. All therapeutic interventions, including the CBT techniques to help address negative thought patterns related to pain and enhanced self-efficacy, were conducted by a female practitioner where possible, as per Fatima's request. When this arrangement was not possible, the need for a different practitioner was discussed with the patient. And again, Fatima's consent was provided as well as trauma-informed care. These approaches allowed Fatima to set boundaries regarding physical contact, which was extremely important.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Over time, Fatima's pain catastrophising scores decreased, her self-efficacy improved, and she became more engaged with the rehabilitation process.</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
