<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Physiotherapy management of Acute Concussion via Telehealth; a Case Study</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Physiotherapy_management_of_Acute_Concussion_via_Telehealth;_a_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Other</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Clients referred to concussion services in New Zealand during periods of heightened pandemic response primarily received their health care via some form telehealth. Physiotherapy might be considered a ‘hands on’ discipline, however, with no alternative during level 4 and 3 restrictions, Physiotherapists attempted to address the needs of their clients remotely. This case study discusses the achievements and limitations of delivering the physiotherapy component of a concussion service to a client sustaining a non-sports related concussion.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>In mid-March 2020 the New Zealand Government put the country into 7 weeks of significant restrictions as part of the nation-wide Covid-19 pandemic response[1]. These restrictions extended into the delivery of health care, with very little ‘hands-on’ therapy available. This response was repeated again in 2021, with Auckland working and living under level 4 and then 3 restrictions for over 100 days. The health care system had to adapt to these restrictions and utilisation of telehealth became commonplace. Telehealth has successfully been utilised for the management of musculoskeletal injuries[2]and neurological conditions[3]however little or no evidence is available related to the use of telehealth in non-sport related concussion management.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Case Presentation
    <paragraph>The client, a 42 year old woman sustained a concussion when hit in the right side of the head by a car door falling closed. She reported no loss of consciousness but she described immediate pain “like an explosion” at the site of impact. Over the next two days she experienced worsening symptoms of dizziness, nausea, fatigue, headache, cognitive changes, stuttering, light and sound sensitivity and the sensation of being off balance. She then presented to the local emergency care centre where they diagnosed her with concussion and requested ACC refer her to a concussion service for ongoing management.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Due to the Covid-19 restrictions in place at the time, home visits were not possible and the entire concussion service was delivered remotely via Zoom. Her symptom reporting at the time of her initial contact with the concussion service is provided in Table 1.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Table 1: Symptom reporting at initial review by the concussion service, 2 weeks post injury</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Symptom</th>
        <th>Rate: 0 = No symptoms and 5 = High impact</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Mood changes</td>
        <td>3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Visual disturbances</td>
        <td>3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Muscular aches</td>
        <td>1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Memory problems</td>
        <td>3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Headaches</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Loss of balance</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Fatigue</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Nausea</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Dizziness</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Difficulty concentrating</td>
        <td>3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Noise intolerance</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>During the initial physiotherapy assessment the client identified dizziness and nausea as her most concerning symptoms. Dizziness was described as “whirling” and provoked by postural changes. Nausea worsened when travelling in a car or being in a supermarket. She had returned to walking her dog daily, but was only managing 10 minutes compared to her usual 30 minutes and was walking more slowly. She was unable to drive her car due to the severity of the symptoms.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Assessment via telehealth was limited but appeared to demonstrate:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Analysis
    <paragraph>The client had a medical diagnosis of concussion sustained from a car door hitting her head. She required education about concussion, symptom management and principles of recovery, which in this service this is primarily provided by the Occupational Therapist. The somewhat limited assessments able to be done by Physiotherapy suggested she had some oculomotor dysfunction and difficulty processing moving and peripheral visual information. Benign paroxysmal peripheral vertigo (BPPV) was unlikely, although unable to be excluded completely. The Physiotherapist also suspected that some symptoms were cervicogenic in nature but it was not able to be confirmed or excluded at this time.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Physiotherapy Management</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>It has been the experience of this physiotherapist, like others[4], that telehealth can be an effective modality for assessment and treatment of concussion when no other alternative is available. The therapist must be able to adapt assessments, depending on safety and the limitations of technology, without compromising the quality of the results. Additional support was also required to optimise assessment and treatment techniques.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For example, extra time for education was provided prior to doing BPPV testing and treatment, including watching an educational video demonstrating the technique. The evidence does support the effectiveness of home treatment of BPPV[5][6][7].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The initial balance assessment must be undertaken with more caution, ensuring that the client is in as safe a position as possible to reduce their fall risk[8]. There may be some clients for whom the fall risk is too great to assess via zoom. As it is not possible to provide a written session summary with the client in person, it appears to be more effective if all instructions for exercises are emailed out to them after each session, to improve compliance. This is especially true for a balance program.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Other barriers with telehealth include patient technical literacy, their ability to access appropriate technology[9], cost, and lack of desire to use the modality. This was often overcome by providing technical support on operation of the telehealth technology over the telephone.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>One of the most important aspects of telehealth is client compliance and satisfaction. Telehealth is becoming an accepted method of delivery of service[10], especially during the Covid-19 lockdown[11]. It is harder to establish rapport, but this can be done with patience and effective client communication. Overall client satisfaction levels are acceptable[12].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>It was felt by this therapist that this client was receiving an adequate level of care, the client indicated she was happy with her care, and she was making consistent improvements. It would have been easier if she had been able to tolerate looking at the computer screen for longer so that sessions were not quite so rushed. She found it uncomfortable to look  directly at the screen for pursuits/saccades to be assessed; and having family members look for nystagmus for BPPV was not ideal, but was the best possible option at the time. Visual motion sensitivity exercise was chosen to minimise neck discomfort from movement. If she had had access to musculoskeletal physiotherapy to have her neck treated it would have been beneficial.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The table below describes the effectiveness of various assessment and treatment techniques delivered by telehealth to Miss Z.</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Action</th>
        <th>Able to be done without modification</th>
        <th>Some modification to testing required</th>
        <th>Unable to do via telehealth</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Assessments:</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Neck Range of Movement</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Smooth pursuit</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Saccadic movements</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Vergence</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>HIT</td>
        <td/>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>DVA</td>
        <td/>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>VOR</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Dix Hallpike</td>
        <td/>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>mCTSIB</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Treatments:</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Smooth pursuit exercise</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Peripheral vision exercise</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Epley</td>
        <td/>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>VOR exercise</td>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Habituation exercise</td>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Tandem standing</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Single Leg Stance</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Tandem walking</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Gait training</td>
        <td/>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Exercise advice</td>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Concussion information</td>
        <td>x</td>
        <td/>
        <td/>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section>
    Conclusion
    <paragraph>For this client the delivery of the physiotherapy component of a concussion service via telehealth appears to have been successful. Whilst there were some assessments that needed to be modified and some that were not able to be completed at all, the client reported improvements in all the relevant areas and reported high satisfaction in the service delivered.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Some research has been done on concussion and telehealth with regards the sports athlete[4][13][14]and USA veterans[9][15], and it is becoming recognized that telehealth does have an impact on the therapist clinical decision making process[16]. More research is needed specifically in the field of concussion care via telehealth for the general population, to gain a better understanding of benefits and limitations.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Resources
    <paragraph>[17]</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Michael G. Baker,  Nick Wilson, Andrew  Anglemyer. Successful Elimination of Covid-19 Transmission  in New Zealand.  N Engl J Med. 2020 Aug 7</item>
      <item>↑M Nelson, M Bourke,  K Crossley, T Russell.  Telerehabilitation is non-inferior to usual care following total  hip replacement - a randomized controlled non-inferiority trial. Physiotherapy 2020 Jun;107:19-27</item>
      <item>↑Kate  E Laver, Zoe Adey-Wakeling,  Maria Crotty, Natasha A Lannin, Stacey George, Catherine Sherrington. Telerehabilitation  services for stroke. Cochrane Database Syst  Rev. 2020 Jan 31;1(1)</item>
      <item>↑4.04.1R J Elbin,  Katie Stephenson, Damon Lipinski, Kristin  Maxey, Melissa  N Womble, Erin  Reynolds, et al.  In-Person Versus Telehealth for Concussion  Clinical Care in  Adolescents: A Pilot Study of Therapeutic Alliance and  Patient Satisfaction. J Head Trauma Rehabil.  2021 Jul 26.</item>
      <item>↑Patorn Piromchai, Nuntakarn Eamudomkarn, Somchai Srirompotong, Teeraporn Ratanaanekchai, Kwanchanok Yimtae. The Efficacy of a Home Treatment Program Combined  With Office-Based Canalith  Repositioning Procedure for Benign  Paroxysmal Positional  Vertigo-A Randomized Controlled  Trial. Otol Neurotol 2019 Aug; 40(7):951-956.</item>
      <item>↑You J, Yu D,  Yin S, Feng Y, Tan J,  Song Q, Chen B. Lin  Complementary self-treatment for posterior canal  benign paroxysmal positional vertigo. Journal  of clinical otorhinolaryngology, head,  and neck surgery, 2014,28 (10); 693‐696</item>
      <item>↑Khalid Bashir, Abdulla  Yousuf, Lubna Rauf, Mohamed  Dewji, Amr Elmoheen.  Curing Benign Paroxysmal Positional Vertigo (BPPV) Through Telehealth: A Case Series. Cureus. 2021  Jul; 13(7)</item>
      <item>↑Janice Kuang Yeung Chan, Piyanee  Klainin-Yobas, Yuchen  Chi, Javeil Ke En Gan,  Gigi Chow , Xi  Vivien Wu. The effectiveness of e-interventions on fall, neuromuscular  functions and quality of life in community-dwelling older  adults: A systematic review and meta-  analysis. International Journal of Nursing Studies.  Volume 113, January 2021, 103784</item>
      <item>↑9.09.1Cindie Slightam,  Amy J Gregory, Jiaqi Hu,  Josephine Jacobs, Tolessa  Gurmessa, Rachel Kimerling, et al. Patient Perceptions  of Video Visits Using Veterans Affairs  Telehealth Tablets: Survey  Study. J Med Internet Res 2020 Apr  15; 22(4):e15682.</item>
      <item>↑John K Yue, Pavan  S Upadhyayula, Lauro  N Avalos, Ryan  R L Phelps, Catherine G Suen, Tene  A Cage. Concussion and  Mild-Traumatic Brain Injury in Rural Settings: Epidemiology and  Specific Health Care Considerations. J Neurosci Rural Pract. 2020 Jan;11(1):23-33</item>
      <item>↑Diego Garcia-Huidobro, Solange  Rivera, Sebastián Valderrama Chang,  Paula Bravo, Daniel  Capurro. System-Wide Accelerated Implementation of Telemedicine in Response to COVID-19: Mixed Methods Evaluation,  J Med Internet Res. 2020 Oct 6;22(10)</item>
      <item>↑Ashwin Ramaswamy, Miko Yu,  Siri Drangsholt,   Eric Ng,  Patrick J Culligan, Peter N Schlegel , Jim C Hu. Patient Satisfaction  With Telemedicine During the COVID-19 Pandemic: Retrospective  Cohort Study. J Med Internet  Res. 2020 Sep 9;22(9)</item>
      <item>↑Brett  G Toresdahl, Warren K Young,  Brianna Quijano, Daphne A Scott. A Systematic Review of Telehealth and Sport-Related Concussion: Baseline  Testing, Diagnosis, and Management.  HSS J. 2021 Feb;17(1):18-24</item>
      <item>↑Cydne Marckmann, Diane John. Telemedicine, Quality Initiative for Concussion Management. Journal  for Nurse Practitioners. Volume 16, Issue  1, January 2020,  e9-e12</item>
      <item>↑Kathleen R Bell, Jo Ann Brockway, Jesse R Fann, Wesley  R Cole,  Jef St De Lore, Nigel  Bush. Concussion treatment  after combat trauma: development of a telephone based, problem solving intervention for service members.  Contemp Clin Trials. 2015 Jan; 40:54-62.</item>
      <item>↑Jason S. Taddeo, Sunddip Panesar-Aguilar &amp;  Paolo Sanzo.  Physiotherapists’ Perspectives Towards  Using Telehealth for Acute Concussion  Care. Global Journal of Health  Science; Vol. 13, No. 11; 2021</item>
      <item>↑Telehealth Easy. #16: Brain Injury &amp; Concussion Management Telemedicine. Available from:http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q9eCIcwg_fc[last accessed 28/01/2023]</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
