<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Course Case Study - Tendinopathy 2</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Course_Case_Study_-_Tendinopathy_2</url>
  <parent_folder>Tendinopathy</parent_folder>
  <section>Course Case Study - Tendinopathy 2</section>
  <section>
    History of Present condition
    <paragraph>Betty is a 38 year old female has been having a mild dull ache at the back of her left ankle for the past 12 months that over the past 2 months has become unbearable when she is training. She has been to see her doctor who has given her some NSAIDs but she didn’t take them as she doesn’t like taking medication.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Presenting Condition
    <paragraph>Dull constant ache at the back of her left ankle with intermittent sharp pain.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Aggravating factors – running uphill and trying to increase her speed. Walking after being sat for more than 30 minutes, touching the back of her ankle.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Easing factors – Rest</paragraph>
    <paragraph>24 hour pattern –</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Social History
    <paragraph>Part time administrative assistant at an insurance firm works 25 hours a week. The majority of the work involves data inputting and customer phone calls.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>She is married with no children. She has a dog which she takes out for 2 hours a day on long walks.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Her hobbies include going to a high intensity interval plyometric training class at the gym and she enters 10km races regularly every year. Although she has signed up to run a half marathon in 2 months.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Drug History
    <paragraph>None</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Objective Summary
    <paragraph>Observation - local swelling to left distal portion of theAchilles TendonAlignment - nothing of note on the position of the heel and foot. Neutral posture.</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td/>
        <td>Active ROM</td>
        <td>Passive ROM</td>
        <td>Ressisted ROM</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Dorsiflex</td>
        <td>Plantargrade discomfort</td>
        <td>+10degrees Pain</td>
        <td>5/5 Oxford Scale no pain</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Plantarflex</td>
        <td>-4/4 discomfort</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
        <td>4/5  pain +</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Eversion</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Inversion</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
        <td>Full no pain</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Palpation - Tender over insertion and distal portion of achilles tendon.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Functional assessment:</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
