<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title> Gait Analysis and Treatment of Maureen</title>
  <source>Parkinson’s Case Study 2 extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Parkinson%E2%80%99s_Case_Study_2:_Gait_Analysis_and_Treatment_of_Maureen</url>
  <parent_folder>Parkinson's </parent_folder>
  <section>
    Gait Analysis
    <paragraph>Dr Ramaswamy’s analysis of Maureen’s gait can be seen in the table below.</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Parameters</td>
        <td>Forward and backward walking pre-treatment</td>
        <td>Forward and backward walking post-treatment</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Walking speed and cadence</td>
        <td>Forwards:14 steps over an 8m distance in 8 seconds.Cadence:105 steps/minuteBackwards:17 steps over an 8m distance</td>
        <td>Similar cadence, slightly slower walking speed due to fatigue</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Step/stride length</td>
        <td>Forwards: stride length over 50cm - good for age and condition</td>
        <td>Similar step length</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Step width</td>
        <td>Backwards: Increased adduction of the leg</td>
        <td>Less adduction of the hips and a more consistent step width</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Floor clearance</td>
        <td>Each foot clears the floor, no concerns</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Posture and biomechanics</td>
        <td>Backward walking:Increased trunk rotation to adapt for limited hip extensionIncreased knee flexion to pull the leg back, placing the toes on the floor and then extending the leg over that - not a normal patternPoor loading over the left hipPosture:Thoracic kyphosis and forward stoopNeck hinge following the kyphosisIncreased extension of the arms to accommodate for the kyphosis and forward stoop</td>
        <td>Backward walking:Improved activity in the extensors of the bodyLess rotation of the trunkImproved hip extensionMore freedom of movement of the right armUsing less knee flexion to get the leg backBetter loading over the left hip as she shifts weightBetter control of walking</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>14 steps over an 8m distance in 8 seconds.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Cadence:105 steps/minute</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Backwards:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>17 steps over an 8m distance</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Posture:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Treatment
    <paragraph>It is essential to keep the patient’s goals in mind when considering choices for treatment. Maureen’s goals when attending this session was to:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>To improve Maureen’s activity levels, Dr Ramaswamy aimed to loosen Maureen’s body so that it will be in a good starting position for her to quickly recruit the muscles and joints while also working to improve the loading through her left side, which is more affected by the Parkinson’s. Any trunk rotation movement gained would also aid to improve Maureen’s wheezing. Treatment included:</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
</document>
