<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Wheelchair Service Provision Case Studies - Transfers</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Wheelchair_Service_Provision_Case_Studies_-_Transfers</url>
  <parent_folder>Wheelchair Service Provision</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Wheelchair Service Provision Case Studies - Transfers
    <paragraph>Original Editor-Naomi O'Reillyas part of the Wheelchair Service Provision Content Development Project.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Top Contributors-Naomi O'Reilly,Kim JacksonandRucha Gadgil</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Faridah
    <paragraph>Faridah is 60 years old. She was referred to the wheelchair service by the local hospital. She has recently had a stroke, and needs a wheelchair as she cannot walk. Faridah can stand up a little and take her own weight. However she is very unsteady on her feet. Faridah lives with her daughter and her family.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Her daughter does not work and is able to help her mother at home. She has a four- wheel wheelchair with swing-away footrests.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Jose
    <paragraph>Jose is 45 years old and has been using a wheelchair for 10 years. He has a bilateral above-knee amputation and works in a radio repair workshop in the local market. Jose has come to the wheelchair service to get a new wheelchair as his old one is very worn.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Tahir
    <paragraph>Wheelchair user Tahir is 14 years old and has recently been referred for a wheelchair after falling from a tree and having a spinal cord injury. Tahir has good use of his arms but he is not yet very strong. He cannot use his legs at all..[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.11.2Sarah Frost, Kylie Mines, Jamie Noon, Elsje Scheffler, and Rebecca Jackson Stoeckle. Wheelchair Service Training Package - Reference Manual for Participants - Basic Level. World Health Organization, Geneva. 2012</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
