<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Wheelchair Service Provision Case Studies - Follow Up</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Wheelchair_Service_Provision_Case_Studies_-_Follow_Up</url>
  <parent_folder>Wheelchair Service Provision</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Wheelchair Service Provision Case Studies - Follow Up
    <paragraph>Original Editor-Naomi O'Reillyas part of theWheelchair Service Provision Content Development Project</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Top Contributors-Naomi O'Reilly,Kim Jackson,Simisola AjeyalemiandRucha Gadgil</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Hala
    <paragraph>Hala lives at home with her grown up daughter and her family. She received a wheelchair through the wheelchair service six months ago. She had a stroke just over a year ago, and is unable to walk. When she received her wheelchair, she learnt how to do a standing transfer with help from her daughter. She said she wanted a wheelchair so that she could be more help in the home, and be able to go to church.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>At the follow up visit, Hala said that she has not left her house for some months.The path to her house is quite rough, and there is a step leading up to the house from the path. She is, however, using the wheelchair at home, and has been able to help her daughter</paragraph>
    <paragraph>by helping to look after her grandchildren. She sits upright in the wheelchair and the wheelchair is in good repair. She was able to transfer from the chair herself without her daughter’s help.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Darn
    <paragraph>Daarun has a spinal cord injury. He works in a radio repair workshop in the local market. He received his wheelchair and pressure relief cushion two years ago. At the follow up visit, he said that he uses his wheelchair every day to get to and from the market. He does not have any pressure sores.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Daarun has had two flat tyres and has repaired them himself. When checking the wheelchair, the service worker notices that the spokes are loose and two bolts are missing on the seat base.The soft foam on his cushion has become very flat. He sits well in the wheelchair and says that he is very satisfied with the chair.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Talha
    <paragraph>Talha is 10 years old. He has mild cerebral palsy and goes to the local school. He was prescribed a four wheel wheelchair with a postural support cushion one year ago.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>At the follow up visit, Talha said that he uses his wheelchair every day to get to school. His father pushes him as he does not have the strength to push himself.The wheelchair is in good repair. His father says that he has repaired the tyre once.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The wheelchair service worker notices that Talha has grown, and his legs are now not properly supported by the wheelchair seat as the footrests are too high for him.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Sabina
    <paragraph>Sabina is 56 years old and lives in a small island community. After the birth of her fourth child many years ago, she lost most of the use of her legs. She can stand a little, but she cannot walk. She has never had a wheelchair.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Sabina lives in a small village near the sea and the surface around her home and the village is rough and sandy. She spends her time helping to care for her grandchildren, cooking and weaving. There is no room inside her home for a wheelchair, but it can be stored underneath, as her home is on stilts.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Resources</section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.11.21.3Sarah Frost, Kylie Mines, Jamie Noon, Elsje Scheffler, and Rebecca Jackson Stoeckle. Wheelchair Service Training Package - Reference Manual for Participants - Basic Level. World Health Organization, Geneva. 2012</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
