<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Wheelchair Service Provision Case Studies - Assessment</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Wheelchair_Service_Provision_Case_Studies_-_Assessment</url>
  <parent_folder>Wheelchair Service Provision</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Felicia
    <paragraph>Felicia is an elderly woman with severe arthritis. She has pain in her arms, hands and legs. She is unable to walk more than a few steps because of the pain and finds it difficult to look after herself.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Felicia has attended the assessment with her daughter who also helps her at home. She lives in a small town and her house has three steps at the front entrance. She does not have any health problems apart from the arthritis. She used to go to church regularly, but is no longer able to do so.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Her family do not own a car, and rely on public transport. To come to the assessment, the family hired a taxi. However, this is expensive for them. She does not currently have a wheelchair.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Anton
    <paragraph>Anton has polio. He is 26 years old and lives in a small town. He is studying computer skills and wants very much to start his own business in the future. He has attended the assessment with his wife.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A long time ago he received a donated orthopaedic-style wheelchair.The chair is rusted and the seat upholstery has ripped. The front castor wheels are small and thin. The rear wheel tyres are very thin and worn.The wheelchair is uncomfortable and difficult to push.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The paths in the town are very rough and his wheelchair gets stuck often. However, he would like to be able to travel from his home to the vocational training centre on his own. The distance is about 11⁄2 km. At present, he needs help from his younger brother, who cannot always take him on time.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Chantou
    <paragraph>Chantou is 13 years old. She lost both of her legs above the knee during an earthquake. She lives with her family in an apartment in a nearby town. She has attended the assessment with her mother and older sister. She has a wheelchair which was donated to her. It is an adult size orthopaedic-style wheelchair, which is too big for her. She has to reach up over the armrests to reach the push rims. This is difficult for her. The backrest is also very high and there is no cushion.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Chantou would like to go back to school, but she feels physically uncomfortable in the wheelchair. She also feels embarrassed that she cannot move herself around. She would like a wheelchair that she can push herself, and which gives her more support. She says she would use the school bus if her wheelchair could travel with her.[1]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.11.2Sarah Frost, Kylie Mines, Jamie Noon, Elsje Scheffler, and Rebecca Jackson Stoeckle. Wheelchair Service Training Package - Reference Manual for Participants - Basic Level. World Health Organization, Geneva. 2012</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
