<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Wheelchair Service Provision Case Studies - Wheelchair Skills</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Wheelchair_Service_Provision_Case_Studies_-_Wheelchair_Skills</url>
  <parent_folder>Wheelchair Service Provision</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Wheelchair Service Provision Case Studies - Wheelchair Skills
    <paragraph>Original Editor-Naomi O'Reillyas part of theWheelchair Service Provision Content Development Project</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Top Contributors-Naomi O'Reilly,Kim Jackson,Rucha GadgilandJess Bell</paragraph>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/juLFv9kmpPs?"/>
    <paragraph>A transcript of this video is available at the bottom of this page.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Moses
    <paragraph>Moses is 23 years old. He fell from the back of a truck two years ago and became paraplegic. He spent one year in the hospital and then returned to his home village with an old donated wheelchair.The wheelchair broke very quickly and he was unable to move around. He developed a pressure sore which has now healed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Moses has just received a new wheelchair with a pressure relief cushion through the wheelchair service.This wheelchair is designed to go over rough ground. He is very excited about going home with this wheelchair and is hopeful that he will be more independent.[2]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Sian
    <paragraph>Sian is 40 years old and has a bilateral above knee amputation. He has been a wheelchair user for 20 years and has had five wheelchairs over that time. He finds that the wheelchairs he has break down quickly.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>He is very active and works in a local shop. He travels from his home to the shop every day, on rough, bumpy and often muddy paths. He demonstrated for the wheelchair service personnel how he can do wheelies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>He has just been prescribed a new wheelchair. He is hoping that this wheelchair will last longer than his last one, which broke down after six months.[2]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Zoe
    <paragraph>Zoe is 16 years old. She had polio as a young girl, and now cannot walk. She is very shy,and has not been to school.Her mother has given her lessons at home and she can read and write well. She has just received a new wheelchair and has shown the wheelchair service personnel how she can transfer easily into and out of the chair.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Zoe is interested in attending a local vocational school, however, she does not think that she can manage getting to the school and back. There are a few steps into the school building. She is also worried about how she would go to the toilet while at the school.[2]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Transcript of Video
    <paragraph>[On-screen text]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A series of wheelchair mobility skills:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Pushing</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Pushing correctly takes less effort</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Push from 10 o’clock to 2 o’clock position</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Use long smooth action to push</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lalithamma: Our village roads are full of rocks and uneven surfaces. With this new wheelchair, I feel confident. So it is easy to cross over rock and sandy surfaces independently.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[On-screen text]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Turning</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Hold one push rim towards the front and the other towards the back</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Simultaneously pull the front hand backwards and push the back hand forwards</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Cassidy</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Cassidy’s mother: Cassidy is an inspiration to a lot of people in her church, and all over where she goes. Everyday she loves to go to school, she loves to come to church, she loves to do everything. She needs a wheelchair that’s equipped for her, she’s very strong in the hands. And here is a typical example of a miracle to the world, to say what disabled children can do.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[On-screen text]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Up slopes</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lean forward</paragraph>
    <paragraph>To stop - park the wheelchair sideways</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Down slopes</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lean backwards</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Let the push rim slide slowly through the hands</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Sai: My mother used to struggle a lot. It was very rough for her to carry me over the steps. Once the ramp was made, it was easier for me to move around, and I can now go to school independently.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[On-screen text]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Up steps with assistance</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Go up backwards</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Tilt wheelchair onto back wheels</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Assistant pulls backwards and upwards</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Wheelchair user can assist by pulling the push rims</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Down steps with assistance</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Go forwards</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Tilt the wheelchair onto back wheels</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Assistant lets the back wheels slowly roll down one step at a time</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Wheelchair user can assist by controlling the push rims</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Partial wheelie</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Roll wheelchair backwards until hands at 10 o’clock, then push forwards quickly</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Castor wheels should come up</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Full wheelie</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This is an advanced skills</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Practise with an experienced trainer</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Cedric</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Elsie Ningalo (CBR Coordinator, Solomon Islands): Some of the wheelchair users think that when they receive a wheelchair they just have someone else to push them around, but if they have the power to do it, they can do it themselves. And even some, if they see the road is too rough they think that they cannot go by themselves and they need someone to help them, but with these little techniques of mobility skills they’ve been taught, they’ve learnt “I can do things on my own with this wheelchair”. So they become independent and can do things for themselves. And that’s what we really want to see and help and work with wheelchair users out in the community to be independent and do things on their own without relying on other family members to assist them.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>[On-screen text]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Safety Precautions:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Assistive Technology for All. WSTP Basic Video Series: 4. Wheelchair Mobility Skills. Available from:https://youtu.be/juLFv9kmpPs[last accessed 30/06/18]</item>
      <item>↑2.02.12.2Sarah Frost, Kylie Mines, Jamie Noon, Elsje Scheffler, and Rebecca Jackson Stoeckle. Wheelchair Service Training Package - Reference Manual for Participants - Basic Level. World Health Organization, Geneva. 2012</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
