<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Hodgkin's Lymphoma Case Study</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Hodgkin%27s_Lymphoma_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Lymphoma</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Author/s
    <paragraph>A.J. Costin, Callie Eaves, Dan Purdy, and Lauren Willis from theBellarmine University Physical Therapy Program's Pathophysiology of Complex Patient Problems Project.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Hodgkin's Lymphoma is a form of cancer with unknown etiology. Important clinical features include: origination and spread of cancer within lymph nodes. The most frequently listed symptoms include: painless, swollen lymph nodes, and constitutional symptoms. A non-specific symptom not commonly mentioned in research but commonly experienced by patients is low back pain (LBP). Perhaps, LBP and lymphoma are rarely linked due to the sheer commonality of LBP. Lymphoma related LBP can occur due to swollen lymph nodes in the abdominal region putting pressure on the muscles, nerves, and other tissues complimenting to LBP, and the incidence of metastases is high, such as in this case. The following case presents a 61-year-old male complaining of LBP and hip pain that is not reproduced with movement and is accompanied by symptoms of fatigue and generalized deconditioning.[1][2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/02/Reed-Sternberg_lymphocyte_nci-vol-7172-300.jpg/800px-Reed-Sternberg_lymphocyte_nci-vol-7172-300.jpg[3]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Patient Characteristics
    <paragraph>http://www.med-ed.virginia.edu/courses/path/innes/images/wcdgifs/hodgclinic.gif[5]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination
    <paragraph>Subjective:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mr. Hodgkins reports a four month history of pain in his low back and recently the pain has moved into his left hip. He states this pain is different from his previous low back pain; it is lower into his hip and this is the first time that he has experienced hip pain. His chief complain is that when he comes home from work he is too tired to go fishing or work in his wood shop. He states his doctor instructed him on dieting and exercise to lose weight and decrease his HTN and cholesterol, but he states he just hasn't had the energy to exercise or perform his usual hobbies. However, he has lost some weight even though he's not sure how much. Pt reports the pain wakes him up at night and can't seem to get comfortable and sitting for long periods of time at work bothers him. He says he recently started doing some of the stretches and light exercises that were given to him by his last therapist; they helped a little at first but doesn't seem to be making much of a difference.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Objective :</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Impressions
    <paragraph>Mr. Hodgkin's presents to physical therapy with LBP and left hip pain. He has a history of LBP and has responded well to prior physical therapy. The symptoms that he presents with now are inconsistent with his former symptoms and inconsistent with musculoskeletal pain.[4]The following symptoms warrant the need for further systemic screening by his primary care physician: pain is constant and not reproduced with movement, fatigue present with low intensity activity, general malaise, history of cancer in primary family member, history of infectious mononucleosis, non-intentional weight loss, + Castell's, and positive lumbar percussion test.[4][12]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>http://seer.cancer.gov/i/factsheets/hodg-lg.jpg[13]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Summarization of Examination Findings
    <paragraph>1. Cancer - Metastasis to the Lumbar/Sacral Area[4]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The following findings pointed toward this potential working diagnosis:age, constant, non-acute pain that is not reproduced with movement and wakes patient up at night, fatigue, deconditioning, weight loss, no improvement with pain with exercise program, history of infectious mononucleosis, pain increases with drinking alcohol, primary family member has had CA, and positive Castell’s Percussion and lumbar percussion tests.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>2. Biomechanical Lumbar Dysfunction (possible herniation) with referred pain to hip area[14]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The following findings pointed toward this potential working diagnosis:previous history of disc herniation and positive response to physical therapy, age, possible radiculopathy, complains of increased pain in flexion (seated position), decreased lumbar ROM, and positive Slump’s Test.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>3. Reoccurence of Epstein Barr Virus/mononucleosis[15]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The following findings pointed toward this potential working diagnosis: weight loss, fatigue, positive Castell’s Percussion, and history of the disease.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>Mr. Hodgkin's returned to his PCP. After further medical screening and testing, he was diagnosed as having Hodgkin's lymphoma with metastasis to lumbar spine area (L5-S1). Patient began chemotherapy and radiation treatment after having surgery to remove pelvic malignant lymph nodes. He continued physical therapy per PCP order to increase cardiovascular/pulmonary health, improve strength and flexibility, improve lymphedema and reduce fatigue and symptoms produced from the cancer and treatments.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>Phases of Interventions</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>Dosage and Parameters:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Rationale for Progression</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Co-interventions:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcomes
    <paragraph>The Patient Health Questionaire (PHQ-9) was administered to assess quality of life/risk of depression once the patient was diagnosed with CA. Mr. Hodgkin's initial score was 14 indicated moderate depressive symptoms.[17]At discharge, his score was 9 indicating he had moved from moderate depressive symptoms to mild depressive symptoms.[17]The patient reported that therapy gave him something to do, helped him feel better throughout his CA treatment, and increased his quality of life.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>At discharge, the patient's 2 minutes walk distance had increased[8]and his RPE during the test had decreased to 12; the oswestry score had decreased to 27% disabled[7]; and the patient's pain in his low back and hip had decreased. He did experience other side effects from the chemotherapy and radiation treatment, but these were non-PT related.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Low back pain, as in this case, is a very common musculoskeletal condition treated by physical therapy; however, it is also a common referral site for other systemic causes.[4]In Mr. Hodgkin’s situation, it was critical that the physical therapist could correctly identify the red flags presented and was able to determine when it was necessary to refer to the appropriate discipline in order to not delay proper treatment.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>According to Goodman and Fuller, “At the present time, standard protocols do not exist for problems associated with cancer and cancer treatments encountered by the physical therapist.” However, due to the side effects of cancer including cognitive impairments and post-surgical problems including limited ROM, soreness, disuse, pain, sensory loss, weakness, DVT, and lymphedema, the physical therapist can play a huge role in maintaining a cancer patient’s functional abilities and quality of life.[18]Furthermore, emerging research suggests that physical exercise works to increase physical activity, improve general self-efficacy and mastery, decrease fatigue and distress, and leads to an increased quality of life in patients who complete cancer treatments. This research also demonstrated a direct correlation between physical activity and quality of life.[19]This can be used to support the need for physical therapy for all cancer patients undergoing treatment and post-treatment. Currently, a protocol does not exist for these patients, but due to the support of the emerging research, one should be developed for this population. This also opens up the door for niche practices of physical therapy in oncology.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Related Pages
    <paragraph>Hodgkin's Lymphoma - Physiopedia</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Hodgkin's Lymphoma - American Cancer Society</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lymphoma Research Foundation</paragraph>
    <paragraph>What You Need To Know About Hodgkin Lymphoma</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Patterns of presentation of Hodgkin disease. Implications for etiology and pathogenesis.fckLRMauch PM1, Kalish LA, Kadin M, Coleman CN, Osteen R, Hellman S</item>
      <item>↑Lymphoma Info.  Lymphoma and Back Pain.http://www.lymphomainfo.net/articles/lymphoma/lymphoma-and-back-pain.  Accessed March 27, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Wikipedia. Reed-Sternberg Cell.http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reed–Sternberg_cell. Accessed March 29, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑4.04.14.24.34.44.5Goodman CC and Snyder TK. Differential Diagnosis for Physical Therapists: Screening for Referral. 4th edition. St. Louis, Missouri: Saunders Elsevier, 2007.</item>
      <item>↑The Lymphoma Club. What is Hodgkin's Lymphoma.http://www.lymphomaclub.com/lymphoma-101/what-is-hodgkins-lymphoma/. Accessed March 29, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Rehab Measures.  Numeric Pain Rating Scale.http://www.rehabmeasures.org/Lists/RehabMeasures/DispForm.aspx?ID=891. Accessed March 26, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑7.07.1Rehab Measures. Oswestry Disability Index.http://www.rehabmeasures.org/Lists/RehabMeasures/PrintView.aspx?ID=1114.  Accessed on March 27, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑8.08.1Rehab Measures.  2 Minute Walk Test.http://www.rehabmeasures.org/Lists/RehabMeasures/DispForm.aspx?ID=896. Accessed March 26, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Physiopedia.  Slump Test.http://www.physio-pedia.com/Slump_Test. Accessed March 27, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Physiopedia. Straight Leg Raise Test.http://www.physio-pedia.com/Straight_Leg_Raise_Test. Accessed March 27, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Physiopedia. FABER Test.http://www.physio-pedia.com/FABER_Test. Accessed March 27, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Mayo Clinic.  Hodgkin's Lymphoma Symptoms.http://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hodgkins-lymphoma/basics/symptoms/con-20030667. Accessed March 27, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑National Cancer Institute. Hodgkin Lymphoma.http://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/hodg.html. Accessed March 29, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Olson K. Manual Therapy of the Spine. Saunders, Elsevier. 2008.</item>
      <item>↑Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.  Epstein-ball Virus and Mononucleosis.http://www.cdc.gov/epstein-barr/about-ebv.html.  Accessed March 26, 2015</item>
      <item>↑American College of Sports Medicine. ACSM's Guidelines for Exercise Testing and Prescription. Lipincott; Williams and Wilkins, 2013.</item>
      <item>↑17.017.1Rehab Measures.  Patient Health Questionnaire.http://www.rehabmeasures.org/Lists/RehabMeasures/PrintView.aspx?ID=954.  Accessed March 27, 2015.</item>
      <item>↑Goodman C, Fuller K.  Pathology:  Implications for the Physical Therapist.  Philadelphia, WB Saunders. 3rd edition, 2009.</item>
      <item>↑Buffart, L. M., Ros, W. J. G., Chinapaw, M. J. M., Brug, J., Knol, D. L., Korstjens, I., van Weert, E., Mesters, I., van den Borne, B., Hoekstra-Weebers, J. E. H. M. and May, A. M. (2014), Mediators of physical exercise for improvement in cancer survivors' quality of life. Psycho-Oncology, 23: 330–338.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
