<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Coronavirus, Ribs and Breathing</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Witty, Pask &amp; Buckingham</source>
  <url>https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/case-studies/coronavirus-ribs-and-breathing/</url>
  <parent_folder>Covid</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Coronavirus, Ribs and Breathing
    <paragraph>Ribs and Breathing</paragraph>
    <paragraph>If you are recovering from illness or struggling with breathlessness, or even fear, anxiety or panic, learning some simple breathing techniques can really help. It is essential to keep good lung function and breathing patterns to ventilate all the lung to reduce infection by mobilising and clearing the whole of the lung of fluids.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Your lungs sit within the protective cage of your ribs, with the diaphragm – the dome-shaped muscle, at the bottom. It is the diaphragm that plays a major role in breathing.</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/anatomy-117148_1280-306x356.png"/>
    <paragraph>When we get breathless or spend hours slumped on the sofa or over your laptop, we do not effectively use the diaphragm and we revert to breathing only with the top of the lungs, and the lower parts become stagnant. This then in turns reduces the oxygen uptake in the blood and leads to more feelings of breathlessness…..a vicious cycle.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>Posture</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Key start. Sit back in a chair and take the pressure off your tummy and allow space for diaphragm to move.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Breathing Exercises</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The active cycle of breathing techniques (ACBT) is an effective way to help clear sputum from your chest. ACBT is simply a set of exercises that helps loosen and remove secretions from deep in your lungs and airways.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <list>
      <item>Breathing Control</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>Breathing control is slow, controlled breathing, using as little effort as possible.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <list>
      <item>Deep Breathing</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>Deep breathing allows the lungs to fully expand, especially the lower parts.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <list>
      <item>Huffing or Coughing</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>Huffing is brilliant at shifting reluctant materials from the depths of the lungs to the central tubes ready to be coughed out. Better than coughing and nicer on the throat. If when performing you hear a rattling sound, you are doing it right.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>If you have found this sequence of exercises has not completely cleared the chest it may then be worth performing a couple of coughs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>Working on these exercises several times a day will help enormously to ventilate the lungs and prepare you to better fight the worst effects of this virus.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Further Information &amp; Case Studies
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/corona-5069862_1920-375x200.jpg"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Coronavirus / Covid 19
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/IMG_0385-375x200.jpg"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Rib Pain
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/IMG_0333.2-375x200.jpg"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Upper Back Pain
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/themes/wpb2017/images/footer-logos.jpg"/>
  </section>

</document>
