<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Covid 19 Corona Recovery</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Witty, Pask &amp; Buckingham</source>
  <url>https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/case-studies/covid-19-coronavirus-recovery/</url>
  <parent_folder>Covid</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Covid 19 Corona Recovery
    <paragraph>Each of us will recover at different paces and involve different strategies.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>If you have spent time in bed or hospital you will be much weaker and less fit than you were. You typically start to lose fitness after a few days of no activity so this has to be taken into consideration.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>You will find everyday jobs tiring as you didn’t before. Simple things like stairs or just short walks will make you breathless and your legs ache.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The aim has to be to get back fit or even fitter again. You will at first feel more tired but this is part of the process.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Regular activity will make you feel better, will reduce the aches and pains in the joints, and start to rebuild your muscle strength.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Activity will help you sleep properly at night.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>How do you do it?</paragraph>
    <paragraph>What are my aims?</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Tips.</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/walking-5357721_1920-306x201.jpg"/>
    <paragraph>Pick a time of day that suits you – we each have better, more energetic times of the day.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Give it an hour after eating and take a drink along with you.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Use a walking pole or two for balance.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Walk with a partner or friend – at a distance – if you are worried about your balance.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Record your progress to give a sense of progress.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>You will have days when you are not as perky but the record will show your overall, week by week, progress which is a much better gauge. You can use your phone health app or simply note in on pen a paper – how far and how long it took and how you felt. Athletes use this method to bring perspective to that bad run!</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Rib pain</paragraph>
    <paragraph>With persistent coughs, you can develop rib joint dysfunctions. We can help with this with an assessment of the specific issues, mobilisation of the dysfunction and breathing exercises, and rib self-help techniques.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Please read this before startingAny exercise could lead to the risk of physical injury.You should feel good when participating in an activity or exercise.If you experience any extreme pain, shortness of breath, or dizziness, stop and seek advice.Following this, activity and exercise advice, is at your own risk. You are agreeing to undertake these activities voluntarily and as such assume all risk of injury to yourself.If you feel unwell before, during, or after, stop immediately and seek advice.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Details can be found here on theNHS website</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Further Information &amp; Case Studies
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/coronavirus-4844592_1920-1-375x200.jpg"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Coronavirus, Ribs and Breathing
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/corona-5069862_1920-375x200.jpg"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Coronavirus / Covid 19
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/IMG_0385-375x200.jpg"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Rib Pain
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/themes/wpb2017/images/footer-logos.jpg"/>
  </section>

</document>
