<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>A 10-Week Physical Activity Program for a Hypertensive Obese Adult</title>
  <source>nan extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/A_10-Week_Physical_Activity_Program_for_a_Hypertensive_Obese_Adult</url>
  <parent_folder>Physical Activity </parent_folder>
  <section>
    A 10-Week Physical Activity Program for a Hypertensive Obese Adult
    <paragraph>Original Editor-Elsa Ptsias an assignment for thePhysical Actvitiy course</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Top Contributors-Laura Ritchie,Admin,Uchechukwu Chukwuemeka,Kim Jackson,Lucinda hamptonandCarina Therese Magtibay</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Obesityis achronic health problemaffecting increasing numbers of people worldwide and is now recognized as a globalepidemic. Many serious medical problems, includinghypertensionwhich is a predisposing factor forcardiovascular disease, are associated with obesity. In adults, the occurrence of hypertension rises with increasing body weight.[1]This study outlines the case of a hypertensive obese man witha BMIof 30 kg/m2. The BMI test was used to measure the percentage of his body fat.[2][3]Hisblood pressurewas under good control using medication.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Bothaerobic(endurance) and muscle strengthening (resistance)exercises were included in hisphysical activityprogram.[4][5][6]Before and after each exercise session, a sphygmomanometer was used to measure blood pressure (BP) in order to avoid the risk of a hypertensive event by stopping exercise if BP became too elevated.[7]Exercise programs of this type have been shown to result in beneficial effects for the obese adult. After ten weeks of matched, evidence-based intervention, Mr X showed a loss of weight and improved cardiorespiratory and muscularfitness. He no longer had pain in his back orkneesbecause of his weight loss.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Introduction</section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Mr X was a 45-year-old man with a history of hypertension that was under good control using medication. He worked as a taxi driver for eight hours per day. He smoked one and a half pack of cigarettes per day and had done so for over 20 years. His father died from a heart attack at age 60. He had no signs or symptoms of cardiorespiratory disease. He had just completed a medical check-up, and the report showed a body height of 173cm and body weight of 88kg, total cholesterol of 8 mmol/L and fasting glucose of 5.4 mmol/L. His BMI was 30 kg/m2, his hip circumference was 40 inches (102 centimeters) and his waist girth was 47 inches (119 centimeters).[2][3][8]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Case Presentation
    <paragraph>Mr X had many risk factors;[8][4][5]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mr X did not have a family history of heart disease that require specific screening because his father’s heart attack occurred after the age of 60. His fasting glucose was normal. Although he was young at less than 45 years old, he was in the moderate risk category because he did not have any signs or symptoms of cardiorespiratory disease but was sedentary. He was concerned about his body shape and about the symptoms of the overweight such as joint pain.[8][9]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Management and Outcomes
    <paragraph>Mr X was started on a program of regular aerobic and muscle strengthening exercises as a primary preventative measure against cardiovascular events.[8]To start him on low- to moderate- intensity physical activity, further medical work-up and exercise testing was unnecessary (although a sub-maximal exercise test of his cardiovascular fitness would have provided a comprehensive appraisal of his condition). Before embarking on a vigorous exercise program after completion of the initial ten-week program, however, he would need further medical clearance from specialists according to the recommendations from the American College of Sports Medicine: Prescribing Exercise to Obese Adult Program.[8][10][4][11][5][12]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mr X was sedentary therefore he had to build up his physical activity targets over several weeks, starting with 10-20 minutes of physical activity every other day during the first week or two in order to minimise potential muscle soreness and fatigue (which could negatively affect compliance with the program). If he had showed difficulty completing the initial level, the physiotherapist would have reduced the intensity/duration. If Mr X had found the initial level very easy, the physiotherapist would have increased the intensity/duration until it felt somewhat hard.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Walking is the most commonly recommended type of physical activity. Weight-bearing physical activity may be difficult for an obese man, however. Gradually increasing moderate-intensity physical activities was therefore encouraged.[4]Based upon Mr X's information, the program was designed to be of moderate intensity. This meant he exercised for at least five days a week at a moderate intensity. Considering he had four risk factors and had led a sedentary lifestyle up to that point, his target heart rate was kept at about 40% of his VO2R.[11][5]To calculate this, his resting HR and age-predicted HRmaxwere put into the Karvonen equation and the desired intensity was between 40% and 50% of that number.[13]From this equation, Mr X's target HR was calculated and then monitored throughout his workouts to determine if an increase or decrease in intensity of any exercise component was required.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Program
    <paragraph>Aerobic Exercise- Five times per week for 20 minutes.[4][5]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Resistance Training:[4][6]Two times per week after the aerobic exercise. The goal was to improve Mr X's muscular endurance and technique. Each exercise required approximately one minute of rest in between each set. The program was designed so that while one muscle group was resting, another could be worked by alternating the exercises in each set.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>After ten weeks of the above exercise program, Mr X demonstrated some weight loss with the BMI test showing a loss of 5 kg/m2. His cardiovascular endurance had improved and his responsiveness to antihypertensive medications and increased.[4]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Studies have shown that physical activity provides many health benefits. Being physically active and fit reduces obesity-related chronic diseases and decreases the risk of premature death. Here study, Mr X demonstrated a loss of weight after ten weeks of physical activity.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The authors of several systematic reviews have consistently reported a decrease in Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) of about 1 mmHg per kg of weight loss with follow-up of 2 to 3 years.[14][15][16][17]There is also attenuation in the longer-term with a decrease of about 6 mmHg in SBP per 10 kg of weight loss. Intervention programs appropriate for obesity-hypertension combine diet, physical activity and behavioural modification, aiming to achieve long-term changes in health-related behaviours. Aerobic exercise can reduce weight and BP. In a meta-analysis that included an assessment of ambulatory BP, it was reported that in programs lasting 4 to 52 weeks (with physical activity as the only intervention) aerobic exercise reduced BP by 3/2.4 mmHg.[18]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The effects of resistance training on BP have also been studied.[18]The estimated decrease in was like the effects of aerobic exercise, although not statistically significant for SBP and without statistically significant weight change.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>In conclusion, a moderate intensity exercise intervention produced improvement in body weight, BMI,waistand hip circumferences and blood pressure.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Kannel WB, Zhang T, Garrison RJ. Is obesity-related hypertension less of a cardiovascular risk? The Framingham Study. Am Heart J. 1990;120: 1195–1201.</item>
      <item>↑2.02.12.2BMI Database. World Health Organization. Available athttp://apps.who.int/bmi/index.jsp?introPage=intro_1.htmlLast accessed 01/09/2016</item>
      <item>↑3.03.13.2Physical status : the use of and interpretation of anthropometry , report of a WHO expert committee. World Health Organization. Available at:http://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/37003Last accessed 01/09/2016</item>
      <item>↑4.04.14.24.34.44.54.6MacKnight JM. Exercise considerations in hypertension, obesity, and dyslipidemia. Clin Sports Med 2003; 22:101– 121.</item>
      <item>↑5.05.15.25.35.4McQueen MA. Exercise Aspects of Obesity Treatment. The Ochsner Journal 2009;9:140–143/</item>
      <item>↑6.06.1Messier S,Loeser R et al. Exercise and Dietary Weight Loss in Overweight and Obese Older Adults With Knee Osteoarthritis.The Arthritis, Diet, and Activity Promotion Trial. Arthr and Rheum. 2004;50:1501–1510</item>
      <item>↑Blumenthal JA, Sherwood A. Exercise and Weight Loss Reduce Blood Pressure in Men and Women with Mild Hypertension. Effects on Cardiovascular, Metabolic, and Hemodynamic Functioning. Arch Intern Med. 2000;160(13):1947-1958.</item>
      <item>↑8.08.18.28.38.4Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network 2010.Management of Obesity. A national clinical guideline. 1-88.</item>
      <item>↑Felson D. Does excess weight cause osteoarthritis and, if so,why? Ann Rheum Dis. 1996 Sep; 55(9): 668–670.</item>
      <item>↑10.010.1Jakicic J, Marcus B. Effect of Exercise Duration and Intensity on Weight Loss in Overweight, Sedentary Women. A Randomized Trial. JAMA. 2003;290(10):1323-1330</item>
      <item>↑11.011.1American College of Sports Medicine. Position Stand Exercise and Hypertension. 2004;533-553.</item>
      <item>↑American College of Sports Medicine. Position Stand. Physical activity, physical fitness, and hypertension. Med Sci Sports Exerc 1993;25(10):i –x.</item>
      <item>↑She J, Nakamura H et al. Selection of Suitable Maximum-heart-rate Formulas for Use with Karvonen Formula to Calculate Exercise Intensity International Journal of Automation and Computing 2015;12(1): 62-69</item>
      <item>↑Neter JE, Stam BE, Kok FJ, et al. Influence of weight reduction on blood pressure: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Hypertension.2003;42:878–884.</item>
      <item>↑Aucott L, Poobalan A, Smith WC, et al.Effects of weight loss in overweight/obese individuals and long-term hypertension outcomes: a systematic review. Hypertension.2005;45:1035– 1041.</item>
      <item>↑Aucott L, Rothnie H, McIntyre L, et al. Long-term weight loss from lifestyle intervention benefits blood pressure?: a systematic review. Hypertension.2009;54:756–762.</item>
      <item>↑Siebenhofer A, Jeitler K, Berghold A, et al.Long-term effects of weight-reducing diets in hypertensive patients. Cochrane Database Syst Rev.2011;9:CD008274.</item>
      <item>↑18.018.1Fagard RH. Exercise is good for your blood pressure: effects of endurance training and resistance training. Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol.2006;33:853–856.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
