<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Treating Arthritic Joints</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Witty, Pask &amp; Buckingham</source>
  <url>https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/case-studies/arthritic-joints-a-bit-of-wear-and-tear/</url>
  <parent_folder>Joint</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Treating Arthritic Joints
    <paragraph>Pain from stiff and degenerative, “worn” joints, can be quite debilitating and interfere massively with your activities of daily living. Physiotherapy can help significantly to reduce:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>With the aim to allow you to return to the activities you would normally enjoy. My approach is simple. Look at what the patient in front of you can do now, consider what that patient would like to do in the immediate short term and then consider the longer term. A joint protection programme is decided upon beginning with the acute treatment of pain, swelling and stiffness followed by a strengthening regime to help regain functional activity. How would you expect to be treated? An example of an arthritic knee is outlined below.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>At the first treatment, I need to find out quite a lot about the condition by a series of questions about the following.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A subjective measure of your pain and dysfunction.</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>How long have you been suffering?</item>
      <item>How do you feel the knee is letting you down?</item>
      <item>When is at its worst and what helps ease it?</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>Any other medical conditions that may influence the treatment of your affected knee. Have you had a previous injury to the arthritic knee?Social history.  The sorts of activities you like to do that may be affected by your condition.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Objective measures are taken that include:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A list of your main problems is drawn up. For example:</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Pain: 8/10</item>
      <item>Early morning stiffness [EMS]: 5+ mins</item>
      <item>Walking 10+ increases pain</item>
      <item>Decreased muscle bulk [with actual measures]</item>
      <item>Unable to deliver a ball in short mat bowling.</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>A treatment plan is then devised to tackle these problems.Short term objectives [STO] Between us we decide on some achievable STO,s that match the problem list</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Reduce pain to 3/10</item>
      <item>EMS &lt; 1 min</item>
      <item>Walk dog 20” without pain</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>A longer-term aim is agreed and a target set.For example – “A return to bowls 4 to 6 weeks please”</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Treatments. The actual treatment itself can comprise a variety of different techniques and approaches to suit the individual patient. The evidence says ‘There is strongest evidence to support the use of exercise to improve pain, function and quality of life.‘ Ref 1.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The combination of therapies shows the best treatment for arthritis. ‘An Exercise therapy intervention provides short-term as well as long-term benefits in terms of reduction in pain, and improvement in physical function among people with hip osteoarthritis.’ ref 2.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A typical treatment programme for an arthritic knee would include:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>You will be given a series of exercises to perform at home to help you maintain the improvements you have made. These will not be too demanding or time-consuming. Hopefully, they will help keep you away from people like me!</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Phil Pask</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ref 1.Outline of research into arthritis and physiotherapy</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Ref 2.Exercise therapy intervention provides short-term as well as long-term benefits</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.wpbphysio.co.uk/wp-content/themes/wpb2017/images/footer-logos.jpg"/>
  </section>
  
</document>
