<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Neck Pain &amp; Upper Limbs</title>
  <source>PT Case Study extracted from Capital Area Physical Therapy &amp; Wellness</source>
  <url>https://capitalareapt.com/case-study-physical-therapy-neck-upper-limb-pain/</url>
  <parent_folder>Neck</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Capital Area PT Case Study: Neck Pain &amp; Upper Limbs
    <paragraph>In this physical therapy case study, neck pain and upper limb pain is addressed, focusing on helping resolve pain without injections or surgery!</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    History
    <paragraph>A 45 year old woman presented with complaints of recent increase in a chronic issue ofneck pain, this episode also including pain in her left shoulder and arm and tingling in all fingers of her left hand. Her symptoms were worse with prolonged sitting at work when she uses her computer and with turning her head when driving and grocery shopping. X-rays showeddegenerative disc diseaseand narrowing within her spine.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Evaluation
    <paragraph>At the patient’s first visit, a variety of objective measurements were taken to assess her baseline function and assist the therapist in building an individualized plan of care. Some of these measurements included: neck and arm range of motion, strength, nerve functioning and tension, palpation of muscles in and around the upper quarter, and postural assessment.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Treatment</section>
  <section>
    Results &amp; Follow up
    <paragraph>The patient returned to PT following a two week hiatus in services. She reported full return to her daily work and leisure activities without pain or limitations. She reported continuation of her neck stretches and the use of the lumbar support roll at work regularly.  If she experienced signs of possible symptom provocation, her home exercise program helped lessen or totally eliminate her symptoms. The objective measures initially assessed on her first visit were re-assessed and significant improvements were observed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For more information on this case study on physical therapy for management of neck and upper limb pain, or to make an appointment for an evaluation or treatment, contact us at one of ourtwo physical therapy clinicsin Malta and Queensbury NY.</paragraph>
  </section>
</document>
