<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Adult Spastic Cerebral Palsy: A Case Study Amidst A Lack of Evidence</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Adult_Spastic_Cerebral_Palsy:_A_Case_Study_Amidst_A_Lack_of_Evidence</url>
  <parent_folder>Adult Spastic Cerebral Palsy</parent_folder>
  <section>Adult Spastic Cerebral Palsy: A Case Study Amidst A Lack of Evidence</section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This fictional case is presented in order to share the impact that a physiotherapy intervention can have on the body structure, activity, and participation of an adult with spasticcerebral palsy. Additionally, this case adds to the limited evidence and case studies done to examine adults with cerebral palsy, a population that is severely under-reported. This case demonstrates the importance of physiotherapy in chronic conditions such as cerebral palsy, and the changes that exercise-based interventions can have for an adult who is deteriorating due to this condition.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This fictional 24 year old patient with acquired right-sided hemiplegic spastic cerebral palsy was referred to physiotherapy due to a recent decline in his walking abilities and functional ability. He presented with physical impairments and was classified as a level 3 on the Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS). The interventions used were based on the International Classification of Functioning (ICF) model to address the body structure, activity and participation components.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>Cerebral palsy(CP) is a non-progressive permanent condition that is associated with a variety of movement, mobility, and postural challenges as well as occasionally neurological changes.  Despite CP being a lifelong condition, the majority of research is based on children with little to no attention to those with CP whom are 18 years of age or older[1]despite a trend toward increased life expectancy[2]. As individuals with CP age, they are at risk for secondary impairments, including stiffness, pain,fatigueand decreased mobility. These challenges can lead to loss of mobility and participation in early adulthood and continues into one’s later years. According to Bottos et al. (2001), between 30% and 52% of adults with CP  experience deterioration in their ability to ambulate[3]. This loss is most often seen in adults 20 and 40 years of age[3]. Loss of mobility will often lead to a decrease in participation in activities of daily living (ADLs) as well as the overall quality of life.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This fictional case study follows a 24 year old male with acquired CP who experienced a deterioration of his gait and ability to participate in ADLs when he entered young adulthood. He was a level 3 on the Gross Motor Classification Scale. The physiotherapy program implemented in this case study hopes to share with physiotherapists the impact that physical therapy can have on the mobility, participation in ADLs and overall quality of life for young adults with CP in lieu of the lack of research in this area.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>24 year old male with acquired right-sided hemiplegicspasticCPfrom an episode ofencephalitisat age 1.  He has recently started experiencing a decline in walking abilities. He is from a low/mid class household with two working parents and currently lives at home with them. He has one younger sibling who is also living at home. The patient presented to physiotherapy to help reverse his decline in walking function and with the goal to be able to perform ADLs more independently. The patient has several conditions associated with his cerebral palsy such as epilepsy, a behavioral disorder and a learning disability, but has no relevant non-CP co-morbid conditions.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>
    Subjective Assessment
    <paragraph>During the subjective assessment, the patient’s parents were present to assist the patient in answering questions. The patient was referred to physiotherapy from his family doctor because of his difficulty in managing the physical symptoms of his cerebral palsy and recent functional decline as a result of a decline in walking ability. The patient was previously using forearmcrutchesfor ambulation but has recently transitioned to using a posterior posture four-wheeledwalkerdue to his recent decline in walking ability.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The patient has been experiencing symptoms of right-sided hemiplegic spastic cerebral palsy since the age of one due to a bout of encephalitis, a common cause of postnatal acquired cerebral palsy[4].  The condition has affected mostly his right arm and leg, leading to motor and sensory impairments, pain, and has led to secondarylow back pain[5]. Commonly associated with his condition, the patient has occasional seizures that are well managed by medication and a mild-moderate cognitive impairment that limits his ability to learn, comprehend and remember[5].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The patient lives with both parents in a one storey home. The patient graduated from high school at the age of 21 and now attends a day program a few days a week and works part-time as an office assistant. The patient is able to complete the majority of his ADLs, such as dressing, feeding, bathing and walking with assistive devices; however, he and his parents are noticing increasingly that he is limited by pain, physical limitations and fatigue. In his instrumental activities of daily living (IADLs), the patient requires assistance, which is common for many individuals with cerebral palsy[6]. The patient does not currently participate in any structured physical activity and walks only when needed due to increased fatigue and associated difficulty with movement. The patient appears to have very low motivation to be involved in the community and with physical activity. The patient and his parents would like to reverse his decline in walking function, returning to using his forearm crutches and hopefully improve to be able to perform ADLs more independently.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medications: Baclofen and Diazepam</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Objective Assessment
    <paragraph>The patient appears to be underweight, have milddysarthriaand difficulty managing saliva[6].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Upper Limb: The patient presents with right arm resting posture of shoulder adduction, elbow, wrist and finger flexion, and forearm pronation[6].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Lower Limb: Resting right leg posture showed slight hip and knee flexion, and significant plantarflexion of the ankle[6].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Tone:  The patient had increased tone and spasticity in the right upper limb and lower limb throughout the available range of motion as well as decreased passive range of motion with hip and knee extension, hip abduction, elbow and wrist extension, shoulder abduction and forearm supination[6]. There was also a notable contracture of the gastroc-soleus complex[6].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The patient had reduced strength in both the right upper and lower extremities[6]. Left side strength and range of motion were within normal limits.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The patient had impaired sensation in the right upper and lower extremities, with decreased 2 point discrimination, proprioception, and astereognosis. Deep tendon reflexes were brisk with clonus and the Babinski sign was present. The presentation of decreased sensation and hyperreflexia are common in people with spastic cerebral palsy[5].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>During gait, the patient used his posterior posture four wheeled walker. The patient demonstrated circumduction and adduction of the right hip during the swing phase. Initial contact was made on metatarsal heads, demonstrating foot equinus. The patient had a flexed and stiff right knee and hip throughout the gait cycle, and anterior pelvic tilt. The patient's gait was slow and he demonstrated shortened stride length, decreased stance time on the right side and minimal trunk movement. The patient’s gait pattern was similar to those previously described in cerebral palsy[7].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Outcome Measures at Baseline</section>
  <section>
    Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS)
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/7/7d/Screen_Shot_2019-05-07_at_3.26.54_PM.png/300px-Screen_Shot_2019-05-07_at_3.26.54_PM.png"/>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/1/1f/Screen_Shot_2019-05-07_at_3.27.08_PM.png/300px-Screen_Shot_2019-05-07_at_3.27.08_PM.png"/>
    <paragraph>The GMFCS is a classification tool used in children with cerebral palsy up to age 18[8]. The classification for this patient was based on the description in figure 1 and 2 of level 3 for children between 12 and 18[9], as there is currently no classification system for adults with cerebral palsy[8].  The patient is classified as a level 3 within this system.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For more information on this scale please refer toGross Motor Function Classification System - Expanded and Revised (GMFCS-ER)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>To see a video demonstrating this system pleaseclick here</paragraph>
    <video src="//player.vimeo.com/video/293380093"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    SF-36 Health Survey
    <paragraph>TheSF-36health survey is used to measure a patient's health quality of life. This assessment can be separated into 8 separate domains. Results for this patient according to the 8 domains are presented here, and are common in patients with this presentation[10].</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Vitality (energy/Fatigue): score = 60</item>
      <item>Role limitations due to emotional problems: score = 100</item>
      <item>Social functioning: score = 75</item>
      <item>Emotional well-being: score = 80</item>
      <item>Bodily Pain: score = 65</item>
      <item>Physical functioning: score = 50</item>
      <item>Role limitations due to physical problems: score = 100</item>
      <item>General Health: score= 50</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Body Mass Index (BMI)
    <paragraph>The patient has a height of 5’5 inches and a weight of 110 lbs, making hisBMI18.3. This BMI indicates that the patient is underweight[11], which is a common presentation in adults with cerebral palsy, as they often have trouble eating[6].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Functional Independence Measure (FIM)
    <list>
      <item>Self care: score = 37</item>
      <item>Sphincter control: score = 14</item>
      <item>Transfers: score = 18</item>
      <item>Locomotion: score = 12</item>
      <item>Social Cognition: score = 10</item>
      <item>Communication: score = 12</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>TotalFIMscore = 103</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Results for this outcome measure were predicted using Gannotti et al.’s[12]and Sandström et al.’s[13]articles.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    6 Minute Walk Test
    <paragraph>There is little consensus in the literature as to which balance tests are valid in the population of adults with cerebral palsy. However this test has been shown to be reliable in adults with cerebral palsy[14]and it is used by researchers to record the effectiveness of their intervention with a population of people with cerebral palsy (average age of 15.5 years old)[15].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Meters walked in6 minutes: 239 m</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Balance Evaluation Systems Test (BESTest)
    <paragraph>There is little consensus in the literature as to which balance tests are valid in the population of adults with cerebral palsy. However this test is used by researchers when examining an adult population with spastic cerebral palsy[16]and so we will use it here.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The following indicates the 6 subsystems measured using theBESTest. The score is presented as a percentage of the total possible score in each section.</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Biomechanical constraints: score =57</item>
      <item>Stability limits/verticality: score =76</item>
      <item>Anticipatory postural adjustments: score =39</item>
      <item>Postural responses: score=28</item>
      <item>Sensory orientation: score=64</item>
      <item>Stability in gait: score=67</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>Results for this outcome measure were predicted using Opheim et al.’s[16]article.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Physiotherapy Diagnosis
    <paragraph>Functional motor impairments affecting the right side and resulting in decreased ability to ambulate and engage in activities of daily living.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Impairments</section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>Patient-Centred Treatment Goals</section>
  <section>Short Term (0-8 weeks)</section>
  <section>Long Term Goals (9-24 weeks)</section>
  <section>
    Intervention Approach: Body, Structure, and ICF Domain
    <paragraph>To reach his body, structure, and function goals that are the basis for more functional goals presented in the next section we targeted three main areas with interventions</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>StrengtheningWith the goal increasing gait and ADL abilities</item>
      <item>With the goal increasing gait and ADL abilities</item>
      <item>Range of motionWith the goal of caring for skin and easing contractures</item>
      <item>With the goal of caring for skin and easing contractures</item>
      <item>BalanceWith the goal increasing gait and ADL abilities</item>
      <item>With the goal increasing gait and ADL abilities</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Techniques Used:
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Joint</td>
        <td>Muscles</td>
        <td>Exercises</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Shoulder[18]*</td>
        <td>Biceps brachii</td>
        <td>Biceps curls with light dumbells secured to hands as needed10 reps, 3 sets, 3 times a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by the end of the day</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Triceps brachii</td>
        <td>Triceps brachii extensions with light resistance theraband, secured to hands as needed.10 reps, 3 sets, 3 times a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by the end of the day</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Pectoralis major</td>
        <td>Seated chest press with light resistance therabands, secured to hands as needed.10 reps, 3 sets, 3 times a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by the end of the day</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Deltoid</td>
        <td>Seated arm abduction with light resistance therabands, secured to hands as needed.10 reps, 3 sets, 3 times a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by the end of the day</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip</td>
        <td>Flexors</td>
        <td>Seated hip flexion with progression including resistance band as needed10reps, 3 sets, 3 times a day, 3 days a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by end of the day</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle</td>
        <td>Dorsiflexors</td>
        <td>Seated dorsiflexion strengthening with light resistance theraband10reps, 3 sets, 3 times a day, 3 days a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by end of the day</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>[18]*</paragraph>
    <paragraph>10 reps, 3 sets, 3 times a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by the end of the day</paragraph>
    <paragraph>10 reps, 3 sets, 3 times a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by the end of the day</paragraph>
    <paragraph>10 reps, 3 sets, 3 times a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by the end of the day</paragraph>
    <paragraph>10 reps, 3 sets, 3 times a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by the end of the day</paragraph>
    <paragraph>10reps, 3 sets, 3 times a day, 3 days a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by end of the day</paragraph>
    <paragraph>10reps, 3 sets, 3 times a day, 3 days a week, to an intensity of light fatigue by end of the day</paragraph>
    <paragraph>*Article specifies muscle groups and parameters but not specific exercises. Exercises were thus chosen by us editors as appropriate for patient.</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Joint</td>
        <td>Muscle Group</td>
        <td>Stretch</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Shoulder</td>
        <td>Adductors</td>
        <td>Passive shoulder abduction by therapist or caregiver</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Wrist and hand</td>
        <td>Wrist flexors</td>
        <td>Passive wrist flexion by therapist or caregiver or his unaffected arm</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Finger flexors</td>
        <td>Passive finger flexion by therapist or caregiver  or his unaffected arm</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Forearm pronators</td>
        <td>Passive forearm pronation by therapist or caregiver or his unaffected arm</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip</td>
        <td>Adductors</td>
        <td>Lying supine with knees out to the sides</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Flexors</td>
        <td>Lying prone</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee</td>
        <td>Flexors</td>
        <td>Lying prone with very light weight on ankles to extend knees</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle</td>
        <td>Plantar flexors</td>
        <td>Treadmill walking on an incline for 30min everyday to decrease joint contractures. Progression included increasing the incline weekly[19].</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Exercise:  Balance via APA training as per the Su and Chow[20]study with parameters determined by implementing therapists in this case study</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention Approach: Activity and Participation
    <paragraph>To address all domains under the ICF, we also implemented functional training exercises that helped our client reach his activity goals leading to the attainment of independent participation in daily activities.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>To reach his functional goals we targeted three main areas with interventions:</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Gait TrainingWith the goal of being able to ambulate with the use of forearm crutches independently for 150m</item>
      <item>With the goal of being able to ambulate with the use of forearm crutches independently for 150m</item>
      <item>Upper Extremity Fine Motor TrainingTo address the client’s desire to be able to participate in video games and use technology such as a cell phone with a touch screen</item>
      <item>To address the client’s desire to be able to participate in video games and use technology such as a cell phone with a touch screen</item>
      <item>Aerobic conditioningTo allow the client to participate in daily activities such as getting around the house, spending time with friends etc. without feeling tired</item>
      <item>To allow the client to participate in daily activities such as getting around the house, spending time with friends etc. without feeling tired</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Techniques Used:
    <paragraph>Week 0-8: TreadmillTraining</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A study by Hesse et al.,[21]shows that among individuals who are non ambulatory and have hemiparesis, weighted body treadmill training and can be effective in restoring normal walking abilities in a shorter amount of time compared to land training. This therapy has also been used in children with spastic cerebral palsy with good outcomes[22]. We decided to begin our patient’s gait training with weighted treadmill training as follows:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Weeks 9-16: Parallel Bar Training</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Weeks 17-24: Rhythmic Auditory Stimulation</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Weeks 0-4: Mirror Therapy and Motor ImageryTraining</paragraph>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/kc7OiOBv-t0?"/>
    <paragraph>Weeks 4-16: Computer Gaming Exercises</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Weeks 17-24: Internet-Based Exercises</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Patient education about when and how often to see health professionals was emphasized before discharge. The NICE guidelines indicate that adults with cerebral palsy should contact their interdisciplinary team when their ability to do activities of daily living deteriorates, or if they are considering a surgical treatment[28]. This patient has been living with cerebral palsy since the age of one, and already has a interdisciplinary health team in place, so no referrals were required. The patient met outpatient physiotherapy goals, and was discharged to home, with an exercise plan. The exercise plan will include similar exercises to the intervention, so the patient can maintain his function.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Outcome Measures Post Intervention</section>
  <section>
    Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS)
    <paragraph>Level 3 [no change]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    SF-36 Health Survey
    <list>
      <item>Vitality (energy/Fatigue):score = 80 [score was 60 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Role limitations due to     emotional problems: score = 200 [score was 100 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Social functioning: score = 125 [score was 75 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Emotional well-being: score = 120 [score was 80 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Bodily Pain: score = 90 [score was 65 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Physical functioning: score = 200 [score was 50 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Role limitations due to physical problems: score = 200 [score was 500 at baseline]</item>
      <item>General Health: score= 50 [score was 50 at baseline, no change]</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    BMI
    <paragraph>5’5 inches and a weight of 120 lbs, making his BMI 20, compared to a BMI of 18.3 at baseline.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    FIM
    <list>
      <item>Self care: score = 40 [score was 37 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Sphincter control: score = 14 [score was 14 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Transfers: score = 20 [score was 18 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Locomotion: score = 13 [score was 12 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Social Cognition: score = 12 [score was 10 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Communication: score = 13 [score was 12 at baseline]</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>Total FIM score = 112 [score was 103 at baseline]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    6 Minute Walk Test
    <paragraph>Meters walked in 6 minutes: 302 m [239 m at baseline]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    BEST
    <list>
      <item>Biomechanical constraints: score =65 [score was 57 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Stability limits/verticality: score =79 [score was 76 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Anticipatory postural adjustments: score =50 [score was 39 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Postural responses: score=55 [score was 28 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Sensory orientation: score=82 [score was 64 at baseline]</item>
      <item>Stability in gait:score=70 [score was 67 at baseline]</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>Other Noted Outcomes</section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>This 24 year old patient with CP presented to physiotherapy to improve his ability to ambulate, perform ADLs and reduce pain. After 24 weeks of physiotherapy treatment the patient showed measurable improvements in gait, balance as well as increased independence with ADLs. The patient was discharged with a home exercise program (HEP) after 24 weeks as he had met all of his outpatient physiotherapy goals.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This case study is highly transferable to other similar cases. The patient discussed in the case above represents a very common presentation of individuals with CP. The large majority of people experience spastic CP as this patient did. As well, this patient had many of the common symptoms associated with the condition.[5]This indicates that this case will likely be applicable to the majority of young adults with CP.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The interventions utilized during this 24 weeks treatment plan successfully showed that it is possible to increase independence with structural and function interventions in young adults with CP. These interventions can have a large impact on their functional ability to perform ADLs independently.  This case study also reiterated that for interventions to be successful they need to be to goal oriented and as well as meaningful to the patient. This was shown in the study above and is important to consider when designing interventions particularly to populations/patients who are lacking in motivation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A final implication of this study is in regards to the lack of evidence and research within this population. There is very little guiding material for practicing physiotherapists in regards to working  with this patient population. The above case study shows that when there is limited research regarding validated outcome measures, certain measures that have been validated in children (18 and younger) with CP are still used in adult populations both in clinic and research. The case study above shows that this is a successful way to approach the assessment and reassessment of young adults with CP.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Overall, this case was a success and is highly relevant to the current literature and transferable to similar cases, individual patients and populations. This case continues to add to the limited pool of knowledge regarding physiotherapy with young adults with CP. However the greatest implication of this case was that it shows that in situations where patients present with conditions where there is limited evidence, validated interventions from similar populations with similar symptoms and presentation can be utilized and success can be found.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Peterson, M., Lukasik, L., Muth, T., Esposito, P., Haapala, H., Gordon, P., Hurvitz, E et al. Recumbent Cross-Training is a Feasible and Safe Mode of Physical Activity for Significantly Motor Impaired Adults with Cerebral Palsy. Archive of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitaiton, 2013; (94), 401-407.PMID: 23063881</item>
      <item>↑Blair E, Langdon K, McIntyre S, Lawrence D, Watson L. Survival and mortality in cerebral palsy: observations to the sixth decade from a data linkage study of a total population register and National Death Index. BMC Neurol. 2019 Jun 4;19(1):111. doi: 10.1186/s12883-019-1343-1. PMID: 31164086; PMCID: PMC6549269.</item>
      <item>↑3.03.1Shrader MW, Church C, Lennon N, Shields T, Salazar-Torres JJ, Howard JJ, Miller F. Well-being of ambulatory adults with cerebral palsy: education, employment, and physical function of a cohort who received specialized pediatric care. Frontiers in neurology. 2021 Sep 20;12:732906.</item>
      <item>↑Reddihough DS, Collins KJ. The epidemiology and causes of cerebral palsy. Australian Journal of Physiotherapy. 2003 Jan 1;49(1):7-12.PMID: 12600249</item>
      <item>↑5.05.15.25.3Odding E, Roebroeck ME, Stam HJ. The epidemiology of cerebral palsy: incidence, impairments and risk factors. Disability and Rehabilitation. 2006 Jan 1;28(4):183-91.PMID: 16467053</item>
      <item>↑6.06.16.26.36.46.56.66.7Rapp CE, Torres MM. The adult with cerebral palsy. Archives of Mamily medicine. 2000 May 1;9(5):466.PMID: 10810953</item>
      <item>↑Dobson F, Morris ME, Baker R, Graham HK. Gait classification in children with cerebral palsy: a systematic review. Gait &amp; Posture. 2007 Jan 1;25(1):140-52.PMID: 16490354</item>
      <item>↑8.08.1Palisano RJ, Rosenbaum P, Bartlett D, Livingston MH. Content validity of the expanded and revised Gross Motor Function Classification System. Developmental Medicine &amp; Child Neurology. 2008;50:744-50.PMID: 18834387</item>
      <item>↑CanChild Centre for Childhood Disability Research.GMFCS – E &amp; R Gross Motor Function Classification System Expanded and Revised. Classification system [internet]. Institute for Applied Health Sciences, McMaster University;2007[cited 2019 May]. Available from:https://canchild.ca/system/tenon/assets/attachments/000/000/058/original/GMFCS-ER_English.pdf</item>
      <item>↑Morgan PE, Soh SE, McGinley JL. Health-related quality of life of ambulant adults with cerebral palsy and its association with falls and mobility decline: a preliminary cross sectional study. Health and quality of life outcomes. 2014 Dec;12(1):132.PMID: 25176595</item>
      <item>↑Bhaumik S, Watson JM, Thorp CF, Tyrer F, McGrother CW. Body mass index in adults with intellectual disability: distribution, associations and service implications: a population‐based prevalence study. Journal of Intellectual Disability Research. 2008 Apr;52(4):287-98.PMID: 18339091</item>
      <item>↑Gannotti ME, Gorton III GE, Nahorniak MT, Masso PD. Gait and participation outcomes in adults with cerebral palsy: A series of case studies using mixed methods. Disability and health journal. 2013 Jul 1;6(3):244-52.PMID: 23769484</item>
      <item>↑Sandström K. Adults with cerebral palsy: living with a lifelong disability (Doctoral dissertation, Linköping University Electronic Press).2009.URN: urn:nbn:se:liu:diva-15771</item>
      <item>↑Andersson C, Asztalos L, Mattsson E. Six-minute walk test in adults with cerebral palsy. A study of reliability. Clinical rehabilitation. 2006 Jun;20(6):488-95.PMID: 16892931</item>
      <item>↑Brien M, Sveistrup H. An intensive virtual reality program improves functional balance and mobility of adolescents with cerebral palsy. Pediatric Physical Therapy. 2011 Oct 1;23(3):258-66.PMID: 21829120</item>
      <item>↑16.016.1Opheim A, Jahnsen R, Olsson E, Stanghelle JK. Balance in relation to walking deterioration in adults with spastic bilateral cerebral palsy. Physical Therapy. 2012 Feb 1;92(2):279-88.PMID: 22033070</item>
      <item>↑Opheim, Arve, Jahnsen, Reidun, Olsson, Elisabeth, et al. Walking function, pain, and fatigue in adults with cerebral palsy: a 7-year follow-up study. 2009;51(5):381-8.doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8749.2008.03250.x</item>
      <item>↑Hutzler Y, Rodrıguez BL, Mendoza Laiz N, Dıez I, Barak S. The effects of an exercise training program on hand and wrist strength, and function, and activities of daily living, in adults with severe Cerebral Palsy. 2013;34(12):4343-54.doi: 10.1016/j.ridd.2013.09.015.</item>
      <item>↑Lorentzen J, Kirk H, Fernandez-Lago H, Frisk R, Scharff Nielsen N, Jorsal M, et al. Treadmill training with an incline reduces ankle joint stiffness and improves active range of movement during gait in adults with cerebral palsy. Disability &amp; Rehabilitation. 2017;39(10):987-93.doi: 10.1080/09638288.2016.1174745</item>
      <item>↑Su IYW, Chow DHK. Anticipatory Postural Adjustments in Standing Reach Tasks Among Middle-Aged Adults With Diplegic Cerebral Palsy. Journal of Motor Behavior. 2016;48(4):309-18.doi: 10.1080/00222895.2015.1092938</item>
      <item>↑21.021.121.2Hesse S., Bertelt C., Jahnke M. T., Schaffrin A., Baake P., Malezic M., et al. Treadmill Training With Partial Body Weight Support Compared With Physiotherapy in Nonambulatory Hemiparetic Patients. Stroke. 1995 Jun 1;26(6):976–81.doi: 10.1161/01.STR.26.6.976</item>
      <item>↑Schindl MR, Forstner C, Kern H, Hesse S. Treadmill Training With Partial Body Weight Support in Nonambulatory Patients With Cerebral Palsy. 2000;81:6.PMID: 10724074</item>
      <item>↑23.023.1Kim SJ, Kwak EE, Park ES, Cho S-R. Differential effects of rhythmic auditory stimulation and neurodevelopmental treatment/Bobath on gait patterns in adults with cerebral palsy: a randomized controlled trial. Clinical Rehabilitation. 2012 Oct;26(10):904–14.doi:10.1177/0269215511434648</item>
      <item>↑24.024.1Steenbergen B, Crajé C, Nilsen DM, Gordon AM. Motor imagery training in hemiplegic cerebral palsy: a potentially useful therapeutic tool for rehabilitation. Developmental Medicine &amp; Child Neurology. 2009;51(9):690–6.doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8749.2009.03371.x</item>
      <item>↑Szturm T, Peters JF, Otto C, Kapadia N, Desai A. Task-specific rehabilitation of finger-hand function using interactive computer gaming. Archives of Physical Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation. 2008 Nov;89(11):2213–7.doi:10.1016/j.apmr.2008.04.021</item>
      <item>↑Brown SH, Lewis CA, McCarthy JM, Doyle ST, Hurvitz EA. The Effects of Internet-Based Home Training on Upper Limb Function in Adults With Cerebral Palsy. Neurorehabilitation and Neural Repair. 2010 Jul;24(6):575–83.doi: 10.1177/1545968310361956</item>
      <item>↑27.027.1Slaman, J., Roebroeck, M., van der Slot, W., Twisk, J., Wensink, A., Stam, H., van den Berg-Emons, R., and Learn 2 Move Research Group.  (2014). Can a Lifestyle Intervention Improve Physical Fitness in Adolescents and Young Adults with Spastic Cerebral Palsy? A  Randomized Controlled Trial. Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, 95, 1646-1655.PMID: 25067790</item>
      <item>↑National Institute for Health and Care Excellence. (2008). Cerebral palsy in adults, NICE guideline. Retrieved from:https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng119/resources/cerebral-palsy-in-adults-pdf-66141606816709</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
