<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease</title>
  <source> A Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Charcot-Marie-Tooth_Disease:_A_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Neurological </parent_folder>
  <section>Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease: A Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This is a fictional case presentation based on a university aged varsity male soccer player who incurred a recent diagnosis ofCharcot-Marie-Tooth Disease(CMT). The case study documents from the initial physiotherapy assessment and diagnosis through to follow up treatments throughout the patient’s lifespan. It highlights the primary challenges experienced by the patient, the patient-centered goals, the intervention methods and rehabilitation program, and the outcomes. The patient complained primarily of difficulties walking to and from class, increases in tripping while walking/running, a significant decrease in ability to play an entire game of soccer, and problems with cutting and shooting accuracy during soccer practices/games due to foot drop, calf pain, and lower extremity muscle weakness and fatigue. The initial assessment and use of specific outcome measures indicated bilateral antero-lateral muscle atrophy and increased tone of lower extremities, decreased DTR's, loss of ROM dorsiflexion on R side, reduced muscular strength bilaterally, fatigue, abnormal gait, and slight balance impairments. Interventions focused predominantly on the maintenance of lower extremity strength to preserve the patient’s functional ability and independence. Aerobic exercise was another large component of treatment due to the high risk of reduced peak oxygen consumption in CMT patients. Patient education regarding overtraining and self management will be a vital component throughout the progression of the disease as well as frequent balance assessments to reduce risk of falls. The prescription of stretching exercises and daily mobility is crucial to maintaining status. The use of an AFO will aid with dorsiflexion, improve gait, and decrease risk of falls. Through the use of manual muscle testing and the Fatigue Severity Scale, it was confirmed that the patient was able to maintain muscle strength and fatigue. The stretching and mobility exercises were successful at maintaining ROM and preventing the development of contractures. The use of the Community Balance and Mobility Scale as well as the 10 Meter Walk Test will be continued throughout the patient’s life to assess for balance and gait deficits. Follow up with the patient will take place every 4 months to assess the progression of the disease and adjust the rehab program as needed. This case study is written in the hopes that it will inform health care practitioners about common signs and symptoms of CMT, progression of the disease, the use of CMT specific outcome measures, evidence based intervention methods, and predicted outcomes for patients with CMT.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>This case study presents an 18-year-old male recently diagnosed with CMT disease type 1.  CMT disease is the most common genetically inherited neuromuscular disorder affecting approximately 1 in every 2500 people[1]. There are two major subtypes of the disease, with type 1 characterized by slow nerve conduction as a result of demyelination, and type 2 associated with axonal degeneration[2]. Both subtypes primarily affect motor neurons with sensory nerves affected to a lesser extent[2]. The onset of CMT disease typically occurs in the first 20 years of life and often has a slow progression[3]. Although the progression of the disease varies, symptoms commonly first arise in the distal lower extremities, with muscle weakness, sensory loss, and reduced reflexes[3]. As CMT disease progresses, the proximal lower extremities, as well as upper extremities can also become affected[2].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The purpose of this case study is to provide an example of how an individual may present with CMT disease in the early stages. This information may assist physiotherapists or other healthcare providers in recognizing the symptoms of CMT disease and knowing when to refer their patient to a neurologist to make a diagnosis. As previously mentioned, the onset and progression of the disease can vary. Therefore, this case represents how a more conventional patient may present. It is possible for the disease to have a much earlier onset and present with a more rapid progression, as seen in a case study on aParalympic swimmer with CMT disease[4]. Moreover, this case provides examples of outcome measures that can be used to measure the progression of CMT disease over time. Due to the degenerative nature of the condition, symptoms cannot be improved. However, various interventions are outlined in this case study that can be utilized to assist in slowing the progression of the disease.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>The patient is an 18 year old male Queen's University student and varsity soccer player. He was referred to physiotherapy by a neurologist with a recent diagnosis of Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease but was previously very fit with no significant medical history. He spends most of his time in class or at soccer practices/games. The patient complains of difficulties walking to and from class and around campus/town as well as significant decreases in ability to play a full game of soccer due to foot drop, calf pain, and bilateral lower extremity muscle fatigue and weakness. He also indicates tripping often while walking/running and problems with shooting accuracy and cutting during soccer practices/games. Finally, the patient reports a progressive decrease in his ability to sleep.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>Subjective</section>
  <section>
    Discomfort and Pain
    <paragraph>Onset: April 16th, 2019 (3 wks ago)</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/6/68/Body_Diagram.png/364px-Body_Diagram.png"/>
    <paragraph>Site: bilateral antero-lateral lower leg</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Characteristics: deep, dull ache or sharp and shooting</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Radiation: antero-lateral leg to dorsum of the foot</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Periodicity: intermittent, no discernable pattern</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Duration: varies from 10-30+ minutes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Aggravating factors: activities such as soccer or walking to class</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Alleviating factors: rest</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Intensity:McGill Pain Questionnaire[5]:Sensory: 8/33, Affective: 4/12,VAS: 4/10</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Objective</section>
  <section>
    Observation
    <paragraph>Lower extremities: slightly more right side calf muscle atrophy when compared to left but present bilaterally predominantly in the antero-lateral portion of the shank. Pes planus foot presentation bilaterally.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Palpation:increased tone bilaterally in the antero-lateral portions of the shank, gastrocnemius, and soleus muscles. Hypertrophic nerve, predominantly the common and superficial peroneal nerve, is palpable but not visible.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination</section>
  <section>
    Clinical Impressions
    <paragraph>PT Diagnosis:18 year old male recently diagnosed with Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease presenting with decreased muscle strength and endurance, increased muscle fatiguability, balance and sensory deficits, gait abnormalities, and pain in lower extremities. Condition is affecting patient’s ability to participate in sport and get to and from classes.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Problem List
    <list>
      <item>Decreased muscle strength and endurance</item>
      <item>Increased muscle fatiguability</item>
      <item>Minimal balance deficits</item>
      <item>Gait abnormalities (decreased dorsiflexion, tripping, foot drop)</item>
      <item>Pain in lower extremities</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>Intervention</section>
  <section>Short Term Goals</section>
  <section>
    Long Term Goals
    <paragraph>One of the main focuses for our patient is the maintenance of strength in the lower limbs. Although a disease such as CMT is progressive and strength gains will likely not be made, maintaining strength is important in optimizing the patient's functional ability, independence, and safety. The strength program developed will be a progressive home-based program using ankle weights. Research indicated that lower body exercise using ankle weights 3 days per week increased led to improvement in knee tension and increased type 1 fibre diameter[12]. Exercises would consist of resisted ankle dorsiflexion, eversion, and inversion as well as hip strengthening exercises such as abductions, flexion, and extension.   It is also common for CMT patients to develop reduced peak oxygen consumption and exhibit a decreased functional aerobic capacity, therefore we would suggest and prescribe an aerobic exercise 3 days per week at roughly 70% of the patient's max heart rate[12][13]. Education would also be a vital component, specifically on the importance of not overtraining that may lead to overwork weakness[14]. Through our assessment, we also found some small balance deficits. Ultimately these are likely due to strength in the lower limbs and will be addressed by the strength program, however, continual balance assessments will be completed to assess falls risk and would be addressed if a further decrease in balance was found.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Due to weakness found in the patient's ankle dorsiflexors, this could lead to increased tone and tightening of the gastrocnemius and soleus muscles as well as fibrosis of the achilles tendon. These changes could all put the patient at high risk for developing ankle contractures[15]. In order to avoid these changes and maintain appropriate joint range of motion the patient was prescribed to do a minimum of 2 to 3 hours a day of standing or walking as well as some passive stretching exercises 2-3 times per day for the structures at risk for contractures[15]. Passive range of motion exercises have been shown to be effective in delaying the development of contractures in CMT[15].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>With walking, because the patient has expressed tripping issues that can be attributed to drop foot and sensory deficits, a customankle-foot orthoses(AFO) has been recommended. There are many benefits in wearing an AFO for those with CMT, including improvement in walking economy by reducing the energy cost of walking compared to just wearing shoes[16]. AFO’s have also been shown to increase gait velocity, increase comfort, decrease pain, improve lower extremity control during walking, and very importantly increase dorsiflexion and therefore reducing foot drop in patients with CMT[7][17][18]. On top of this recommendation, the patient was also provided with gait training and education in order to allow for normal gait biomechanics in the hopes of decreasing compensatory muscle recruitment and improving energy efficiency[19].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>As the patient presented with symptoms of muscle fatigue, and with overwork weakness being a common finding in CMT, it was decided that education on energy conservation techniques would be one of the focal points during treatment[7]. The education included advice on pacing himself with activities and ensuring adequate rest periods, planning out the most efficient walking routes while on campus, and making sure he wears his custom AFO once received in order to optimize his biomechanics and improve his walking efficiency. Unfortunately, it was also recommended that the patient discontinues playing competitive soccer in order to prioritize other activities of daily living from an energy cost standpoint. Lastly, because the patient reported difficulties with sleep, and because it is known that CMT may predispose patients to sleep conditions such asobstructive sleep apnoeaandrestless leg syndrome, it was decided that the patient be referred back to his family doctor with the recommendation of seeing a sleep specialist[20].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Using the strength and aerobic protocols provided, our patient managed to maintain strength and fatigue. This was confirmed using manual muscle testing where it was found that the patient presented with 3+/5 for dorsiflexion bilaterally, and a score of 47/63 on the Fatigue Severity Scale. The ROM exercises combined with the 2-3 hours per day of standing or walking successfully prevented the patient from developing contractures in his gastrocnemius, soleus, and achilles tendon, and the patient reported no decreases in dorsiflexion ROM. This was confirmed through measurement as the patient maintained 14° of dorsiflexion. With this patient, there will be no formal discharge as CMT is a progressive disease and will require progressions and changes to treatment. The patient will be provided with the self-management techniques and training methods for at home use. Follow up approximately every 3 months to assess progression of the disease, re-test outcome measures, prescribe new exercises and self-management to ensure maximal retention of function. No issues were found with the upper extremities but would be monitored during follow up sessions using dynamometry, 9 hole peg test, CMT neuropathy score, ONLS to assess changes in function. The patient is, however, being referred out to both a clinic that specializes in custom orthotics in order to get him his custom AFO, as well as back to his family doctor with the recommendation of getting a referral to see a sleep specialist. These referrals are necessary in order to improve the patient's activity and participation impairments.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>A 18 year old male with a recent diagnosis of CMT 1 was referred to us for physical therapy treatments. An examination which brought to light the patients issues with tripping, playing soccer, intermittent pain, and fatigue in his daily life as well as visible muscle atrophy, decreased hot/cold sensation, diminished deep tendon reflexes, decreased dorsiflexion on the right side, decreased strength bilaterally, and gait abnormalities (hip hike, trunk lean, and foot drop) informed our interventions. All deficits were limited to the lower extremity, specifically the calf, ankle, and foot, and had not yet progressed to the upper extremity as shown by the normal performances on the 9-Hole Peg Test, the hand dynamometer, and the upper extremity portion of the ONLS. The FSS measured fatigue, activities of daily living, life participation, and sleep and found a relatively high score of 49/63 indicating fatigue issues. The patient scored a 12/36 on the CMT Neuropathy Score measuring disability which illustrates that the patient is able to walk independently however an AFO is required. This is supported by the fact that the patient scored a 2/7 on the lower limb score of the ONLS as they were able to walk independently but the gait was abnormal. Referrals to a sleep clinic and orthotics specialist were warranted as his lack of sleep was affecting his participation and activities of daily living and the AFO has been proven to decrease pain, increase gait speed, and improve overall function[16][17][18][19]. The focus of the physical therapy interventions were to maintain function and mobility and where possible increase these areas by decreasing pain and increasing the patient’s quality of life. Attention in the initial sessions was on maintaining aerobic capacity and muscle strength as balance, shown with the score of 81/96 on the CBMS, is only slightly impaired and may be a result of progressive weakness and can be addressed in subsequent sessions once strength is optimized. Treatments such as gait training, range of motion, and stretching exercises were also given to maintain the normal, yet slightly slower than average, gait speed of 1.1 m/sec on the T10MW. In cases of CMT, or other neuromuscular conditions such as Guillain Barre, Multiple Sclerosis, and Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis, interventions should be aimed at slowing the progression of the condition, optimizing function where possible, and educating the patient on proper self-management techniques to improve their participation and quality of life.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Szigeti K, Lupski J. Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease. European Journal of Human Genetics. 2009; 17(6): 703-710.doi 10.1038/ejhg.2009.31</item>
      <item>↑2.02.12.2Pareyson D, Marchesi C. Diagnosis, natural history, and management of Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease. The Lancet Neurology. 2009; 8(7): 654-667.doi: 10.1016/s1474-4422(09)70110-3</item>
      <item>↑3.03.1Krajewski K. Neurological dysfunction and axonal degeneration in Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1A. Brain. 2000;123(7):1516-1527.doi:10.1093/brain/123.7.1516</item>
      <item>↑Vita G, La Foresta S, Russo M, Vita G, Messina S, Lunetta C et al. Sport activity in Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease: A case study of a Paralympic swimmer. Neuromuscular Disorders. 2016;26(9):614-618.doi: 10.1016/j.nmd.2016.06.002</item>
      <item>↑Melzack R. The McGill pain questionnaire: from description to measurement. Anesthesiology, 2005; 103: 199-202.PMID:15983473</item>
      <item>↑Shirley Ryan Abilitylab. Fatigue Severity Scale. Available from:https://www.sralab.org/rehabilitation-measures/fatigue-severity-scale(accessed 7/05/2019)</item>
      <item>↑7.07.17.2McCorquodale D. Pucillo E. Johnson N. Management of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease: improving long-term care with a multidisciplinary approach. Journal of Multidisciplinary Healthcare. 2016; 9: 7-19.DOI: 10.2147/JMDH.S69979</item>
      <item>↑Graham R. Hughes R. A modified peripheral neuropathy scale: the overall neuropathy limitations scale. Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp; Psychiatry. 2006; 77: 973-976.DOI: 10.1136/jnnp.2005.081547</item>
      <item>↑Shirley Ryan Abilitylab. Nine-hole peg test. Available from:https://www.sralab.org/rehabilitation-measures/nine-hole-peg-test(accessed 7/05/2019)</item>
      <item>↑Shirley Ryan Abilitylab. Community Balance and Mobility Scale. Available from:https://www.uhn.ca/TorontoRehab/Health_Professionals/Documents/TR_HCP_SUPP_CBMScale.pdf(accessed 7/05/2019)</item>
      <item>↑Shirley Ryan Abilitylab. 10 meter walk test. Available from:https://www.sralab.org/rehabilitation-measures/10-meter-walk-test(accessed 7/05/2019)</item>
      <item>↑12.012.1Abresch T, Carter G, Han J, McDonald C. Exercise in Neuromuscular Disease. Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation Clinics. 2012; 23: 653-673.https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmr.2012.06.001</item>
      <item>↑Pareyson D., Marchesi C. Diagnosis, natural history, and management of Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease. THE LANCET Neurology. 2009; 8: 654-667.https://doi.org/10.1016/S1474-4422(09)70110-3</item>
      <item>↑Shy M. Therapeutic Strategies for the Inherited Neuropathies. NeuroMolecular Medicine. 2006; 8: 271. doi:10.1385/NMM:8:1-2:255https://link-springer-com.proxy.queensu.ca/article/10.1385%2FNMM%3A8%3A1-2%3A255</item>
      <item>↑15.015.115.2Skalsky AJ, McDonald CM. Prevention and management of limb contractures in neuromuscular diseases. Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation Clinics of North America. 2012; 23: 675-687.DOI: 10.1016/j.pmr.2012.06.009</item>
      <item>↑16.016.1Menotti F, Laudani L, Damiani A, Mignogna T, Macaluso A. An anterior ankle-foot orthosis improves walking economy in charcot–marie–tooth type 1A patients. Prosthetics and Orthotics International. 2014; 38: 387-392.https://doi.org/10.1177/0309364613506250</item>
      <item>↑17.017.1Phillips MF, Robertson Z, Killen B, White B. A pilot study of a crossover trial with randomized use of ankle-foot orthoses for people with charcot–marie–tooth disease. Clinical Rehabilitation. 2012; 26: 534-544.doi:10.1177/0269215511426802</item>
      <item>↑18.018.1Ramdharry GM, Day BL, Reilly MM, Marsden JF. Foot drop splints improve proximal as well as distal leg control during gait in charcot‐marie‐tooth disease. Muscle &amp; Nerve. 2012; 46: 512-519.doi: 10.1002/mus.23348</item>
      <item>↑19.019.1Dufek JS, Neumann ES, Hawkins MC, O’Toole B. Functional and dynamic response characteristics of a custom composite ankle foot orthosis for charcot–marie–tooth patients. Gait &amp; Posture. 2013;2014; 39: 308-313.doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2013.07.121</item>
      <item>↑Boentert M, Knop K, Schuhmacher C, Gess B, Okegwo A, Young P. Sleep disorders in charcot-marie-tooth disease type 1. Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery, and Psychiatry. 2014; 85: 319-325.doi:10.1136/jnnp-2013-305296</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
