<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Myasthenia Gravis</title>
  <source> Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Myasthenia_Gravis:_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Neurological </parent_folder>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This project is a fictional case study developed by Physical Therapy students fromQueen's Universityto help with the understanding of the implications of aMyasthenia Gravis(MG) diagnosis on physical therapy assessment and treatment. The case study shows the clinical presentation, expectation of symptoms, comorbidities, and impairments of a patient diagnosed with MG.  The case also presents some objective measures and treatment options based on individualities of the patient’s disease presentation. It is important to note that MG symptoms can vary among individuals, so the following assessment, outcome measures, and treatment plan may not be appropriate for all individuals diagnosed with MG, and an individual assessment would be necessary to determine the best course of action for other patients.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Introduction</section>
  <section>
    Pathophysiology
    <paragraph>Myasthenia Gravis (MG) is an autoimmune disease affecting the antibodies to receptors at the neuromuscular junction, causing muscle weakness and fatigue[1]. Individuals with MG have decreased acetylcholine and voltage-gated sodium channels due to damage of their postsynaptic membranes[2]. This dysfunction in the neuromuscular junction results in decreased response and amplitude of the corresponding muscles[2].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Comorbidities
    <paragraph>Patients diagnosed with MG may present with several comorbidities. Since it is an autoimmune disorder, patients are at an increased risk for other autoimmune diseases such as Thymoma (thymus tumor)[1][3],Systemic Lupus Erythematosus[1][4][5],Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA)[4][5], andDiabetes Mellitus Type 1[1][3][4]. Some other common comorbidities includeHypertension,COPD[4], and an increased risk for respiratory infections due to muscle weakness and other issues related to prolonged corticosteroid use[3].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Presentation
    <paragraph>This autoimmune disease is relatively uncommon with approximately 20 out of 100,000 individuals diagnosed with MG in the United States[6]. Reported prevalence in Ontario, Canada is similar with 32 out of 100,000 individuals[7]. In both Canada and the United States, there appears to be a greater incidence of younger women (&lt;60 and &lt;50 years old, respectively), diagnosed with MG[6][7]. Whereas, in Canada and the United States, incidence appears to be greater in older men (&gt;60 and &gt;50 years old, respectively)[6][7].</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/d/d3/Screen_Shot_2023-05-12_at_8.17.54_AM.png/300px-Screen_Shot_2023-05-12_at_8.17.54_AM.png"/>
    <paragraph>As seen in Table 1, the Myasthenia Gravis Foundation of America defines five main classes of MG with corresponding subclasses[8]. This system helps to determine a patient’s prognosis and potential response to treatment depending on their symptom severity[8].</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Signs and Symptoms
    <paragraph>The initial symptom that presents for two thirds of individuals:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The symptoms then typically progress to include:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>One of the primary symptoms of MG:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Physiotherapy Implications
    <paragraph>It is necessary for physiotherapists to take a comprehensive medical history to screen for the many comorbidities that might be associated with the diagnosis, including a screen forred flags. It is also important to take into consideration the patient's medications (especially corticosteroid use), and the presence of possible underlying conditions. These findings can limit some treatment approaches and be contraindications or precautions for some manual therapy or exercise treatments.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Maya Stevens is a 34-year-old, Caucasian woman who was recently diagnosed with MG two months ago. Mrs. Stevens reached out to her family doctor after experiencing a number of abnormal symptoms apart from her other diagnoses (rheumatoid arthritis and hypertension) and was referred to a neurologist who provided her with a diagnosis of MG. She was aware that a common comorbidity of these conditions is MG, and thought it was appropriate to seek medical advice. She was referred to physical therapy to address her concerns, and to learn preventative techniques to avoid a decline in function and to manage future symptoms associated with the disease. Mrs. Stevens is a motivated, pleasant individual who is prepared to take a rehabilitative approach to her diagnosis.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Subjective
    <paragraph>Patient reports feeling well in the morning, but becomes more fatigued in the afternoon as the day progresses. She has been increasingly stressed from returning back to work after maternity leave, taking care of her two young kids, and having a husband who works long hours. She has been taking care of many of the household duties and has a hard time caring for her kids. She initially noticed difficulty keeping her eyes open while attempting to take out her contacts at night, 9 months ago. Over the next month, her eye drooping became more persistent throughout the day and she began experiencing episodes of double vision. Additionally, she also noticed muscular fatigue in her shoulders while kayaking, as she isn’t able to paddle for as long without taking breaks. She describes her fatigue as more frequent, and like her “limbs aren’t working.” Other activities that are particularly bothersome are baking and grocery shopping. She also noticed increased shortness of breathing while kayaking, which has progressed to less exertional activities, such as entering the stairs into her home at the end of the day.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mrs. Stevens was diagnosed with RA five years ago and hypertension nine months ago, both of which are currently well maintained and have not caused any problems after giving birth to her second child.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Both of Mrs. Stevens’ parents are alive, and her father was diagnosed with hypertension at the age of 30. In addition, her Great Aunt was diagnosed with MG at 52 years old[9].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Patient lives in Kingston, Ontario in a bungalow with four steps to enter the home with a railing on both sides. She lives with her husband and two kids (one and four years old). Mrs. Stevens works at a dental clinic as a receptionist and spends most of her day sitting, using the computer, and answering client questions or calls.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mrs. Stevens does not smoke or use recreational drugs. She has one glass of wine every evening (6-7 drinks/week) to wind down.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Prior to diagnosis, patient was fully independent in all bADLs, iADLs, ambulation, and family activities.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>
    Observation
    <paragraph>Upon observation, Mrs. Stevens is alert and oriented, making light conversation. Patient demonstrates some hoarseness of speech and displays an apical breathing pattern. She has right-sided asymmetrical ptosis with exertion, as well as forward head posture.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Vital Signs</section>
  <section>
    Active and Passive Range of Motion
    <paragraph>Active and passive range of motion (AROM and PROM) were tested for all upper extremity and lower extremity joints. Mrs. Stevens demonstrates pain free AROM and PROM within normal limits bilaterally.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Strength
    <paragraph>Manual Muscle Testing(MMT) was performed for upper extremity and lower extremity joints bilaterally, as well as for the cervical spine. All MMT measures show bilateral symmetry, and Mrs. Stevens had the following results:</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/3/32/Screenshot_2023-05-11_at_1.25.02_PM.png/400px-Screenshot_2023-05-11_at_1.25.02_PM.png"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Neurological Scan
    <paragraph>A neurological scan was conducted to determine if the patient has any neurological deficits from her condition such as loss of sensation, loss of motor function, change to deep tendon reflexes, and assessment of upper motor neuron lesions.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mrs. Stevens' cervical and lumbosacral dermatomes were intact, while all myotomes were affected, likely due to muscular weakness which is characteristic of MG and RA. All upper motor neuron tests (Babinski, Hoffman, and Clonus) were negative, while lower motor neuron reflex tests (triceps, biceps, patellar, Achilles) were all normal (grade 2). The table below provides the cranial nerve test results:</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Cranial Nerves</th>
        <th>CN V (Trigeminal)</th>
        <th>CN VI (Abducens)</th>
        <th>CN X (Vagus)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Result</td>
        <td>(+) Motor(-) Sensory</td>
        <td>(+) Motor (Diplopia)</td>
        <td>(+) Motor (Dysphonia)(-) Sensory</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>(-) Sensory</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(-) Sensory</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Balance &amp; Gait Assessment</section>
  <section>
    Outcome Measures
    <paragraph>This 10-item scale measures primary signs and symptoms of MG based on physical exam and patient history[12]. Items include weakness of the ocular, neck, and proximal limb muscles, as well as patient-reported impairments in speech, chewing, swallowing, visual, and respiratory function[13]. Each item is scored on a weighted, ordinal scale, based on symptom severity[13].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Total score ranges from 0 to 50, in which higher scores indicate more severe impairment[12]. Improvement of 3-points in the total score on the MGC denotes clinically meaningful change[13].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The MGC has been found to be both a reliable and valid tool for the measurement of clinical status of MG patients, due to its excellent test-retest reliability and concurrent validity with other MG-specific measurement scales[11]. Since the MGC is simple and time efficient, it will be used to evaluate muscle strength as well as global functional impairments[14].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mrs. Stevens scored 20/50 on the MGS. Her results are displayed in Figure 2 below:</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/6/62/344270352_947340159923090_3510354440947505355_n.png/712px-344270352_947340159923090_3510354440947505355_n.png"/>
    <paragraph>This 15-item, patient-reported outcome is derived from the MG-QOL60 and measures health-related quality of life, specific to the MG patient population[14]. Items are related to physical, emotional, functional and social elements, such as mobility, well-being and symptoms, and each are scored on a Likert scale ranging from 0 to 4[14]. The total score ranges from 0 to 60, such that higher scores suggest poorer quality of life[14]. The MG-QOL15 has been translated and validated in numerous languages, has excellent test-retest reliability, and its scores correlate well with other MG-specific measurement tools, such as the MGC, Myasthenia Gravis Activities of Daily Living measure (MG-ADL), and Quantitative Myasthenia Gravis Score (QMGS)[14].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mrs. Stevens scored 32/60 on the MG-QOL15. Her results are displayed in Figure 3 below:</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/1/1e/344285520_1159429191390190_2347556601718842394_n.png/712px-344285520_1159429191390190_2347556601718842394_n.png"/>
    <paragraph>The BBS is a 14-item measurement that evaluates balance in the elderly, as well as several neurological conditions[16]. The scale assesses the patient’s ability to maintain balance throughout the performance of listed tasks[17]. When a patient achieves a score less than 42 and has no history of falls, this indicates the patient is at a greater risk of future falls[17].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The BBS has high test-retest reliability and internal validity for measuring balance in neurological conditions, independent of the etiology of the balance impairment[16].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mrs. Stevens scored 41/56 on the BBS. This indicates Mrs. Stevens has an increased risk of future falls.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Problem List</section>
  <section>Clinical Hypothesis/Impression</section>
  <section>Interventions</section>
  <section>
    Patient-Centered Goals
    <paragraph>Goal setting is an essential component of physiotherapy to outline a course of action for the patient and therapist to follow throughout the rehabilitation journey. Creating meaningful, patient-centered goals can enhance patient engagement, satisfaction, and adherence which will supplement recovery and improvement. Long-term and short-term goals (LTG and STG) for Mrs. Stevens will be outlined below, and were determined based off of the subjective interview and objective assessments.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Approaches and Techniques
    <paragraph>The following aerobic, resistance, and balance exercises are to be completed in one session, 2 times a week.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Innovative Technologies
    <paragraph>When implementing an exercise intervention with MG patients, it is important to consider heat as a factor that can exacerbate symptoms[6][21]. In addition to performing exercise at a low intensity and taking adequate rests, cooling technology has the potential to improve muscle strength, fatigue, and respiratory function in MG patients by maintaining lower muscle temperatures when exercising[21]. Cooling technology, such as cooling garments, may allow for patients to perform exercises for prolonged periods of time prior to the onset of fatigue. During Mrs. Stevens’ in-person treatment sessions, we propose the use of the cooling garment (Personal ICE Cooling System) which consists of a network of tubes that pump cold water throughout the garment by a battery-powered pumping system[21]. This may allow for improved adherence to exercise protocols which would result in increased muscular endurance and the ability to actively participate more in meaningful activities.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Challenges:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Regression of Exercises
    <paragraph>If the patient reports an adverse event in response to her intervention plan, regression of her exercises can be completed as follows:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome Measure Re-Assessment
    <paragraph>The outcome re-assessment was performed three months after the referral; results can be found below.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Following 3 months of participating in physiotherapy, Mrs. Stevens completed the MGC again and scored 15/50. This improvement in score suggests Mrs. Stevens’ symptom severity has decreased within the past 3 months. The minimal clinically important difference for the MGC is 3 points, therefore improvement in this outcome measure reflects meaningful change in symptom severity for Mrs. Stevens[13].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Upon reassessment, Mrs. Stevens scored 24/60 on the MG-QOL15. This suggests an improvement in her quality of life related to her MG. Subjectively, she reports feeling more motivated to participate in activities, such as kayaking due to reduction in her symptoms.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Following 3 months of physiotherapy, Mrs. Stevens was reassessed on the BBS and scored 48/56. This change in score suggests improvements in balance, leading to a decreased risk of falling. Subjectively, Mrs. Stevens describes feeling more steady on her feet as well as increased confidence when walking.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Interdisciplinary Care Management
    <paragraph>A Speech Language Pathologist (SLP) can help to identify and manage the presence of issues with speaking, chewing and swallowing[22]. This may include exercises that strengthen the muscles of the throat, vocal exercises to improve voice clarity, swallowing exercises, and the timing of pharmacological interventions. The results of the MGC suggests that the patient would benefit from SLP therapy.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>An Occupational Therapist (OT) can assist with the difficulties Mrs. Stevens faces with her ADLs due to generalized muscular weakness[22]. This could include tasks that require endurance of activities like food preparation, childcare and grocery shopping. This could help Mrs. Stevens to reach her goals, including playing with and caring for her children.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Studies have shown MG to be associated with mood disorders, which puts Mrs. Stevens at a higher risk of developing depression and anxiety[23]. Therefore, it is recommended for her to have a psychiatric evaluation to address any of these factors that may be present as well as the potential prescription of medication to assist with management.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Referral Form
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/3/39/Screen_Shot_2023-05-11_at_8.54.51_PM.png/712px-Screen_Shot_2023-05-11_at_8.54.51_PM.png"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discharge Planning
    <paragraph>Mrs. Stevens will be discharged from the Physiotherapist’s caseload once she has met all of her goals and is comfortable continuing all exercises independently at home. She is encouraged to continue to monitor her symptoms and return to physiotherapy should new challenges arise.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Myasthenia Gravis is a chronic condition, and there is currently no cure. In conjunction with other interdisciplinary health care professions, physiotherapy can help patients by providing exercise interventions and patient education. These interventions can increase patients’ endurance so that individuals with MG may enhance their participation in activities of daily living, various hobbies and social roles, leading to an overall better quality of life[18]. Physiotherapy plays an important role in the disease course management of MG and may reduce burden on patients and their families. By understanding the primary signs and symptoms of MG, as well as interventions that work best for these individuals, health care teams can provide better quality care for these patients.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Multiple Choice Questions
    <paragraph>(1) What are the main signs and symptoms noticed in the early presentation of Myasthenia Gravis?</paragraph>
    <paragraph>a) Eye drooping</paragraph>
    <paragraph>b) Sensory loss</paragraph>
    <paragraph>c) Loss of movement coordination</paragraph>
    <paragraph>d) Muscle weakness and fatigue</paragraph>
    <paragraph>e) Two of the above</paragraph>
    <paragraph>f) All of the above</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(2) What body functions wouldNOTbe affected in someone diagnosed with Myasthenia Gravis?</paragraph>
    <paragraph>a) Motor planning function</paragraph>
    <paragraph>b) Strength</paragraph>
    <paragraph>c) Breathing</paragraph>
    <paragraph>d) Endurance</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(3) What are the main physiotherapy interventions in Myasthenia Gravis?</paragraph>
    <paragraph>a) Improve muscle endurance and strength</paragraph>
    <paragraph>b) Address balance and ambulation issues</paragraph>
    <paragraph>c) Education on breathing exercises</paragraph>
    <paragraph>d) All of the above</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.11.21.31.4Gilhus, N.E., Nacu, A., Andersen, J.B. and Owe, J.F. Myasthenia gravis and risks for comorbidity. Eur J Neurol 2015; 22: 17-23. doi: 10.1111/ene.12599</item>
      <item>↑2.02.1Dresser L, Wlodarski R, Rezania K, Soliven B. Myasthenia Gravis: Epidemiology, Pathophysiology and Clinical Manifestations. Journal of clinical medicine. 2021;10(11):2235–. doi: 10.3390/jcm10112235</item>
      <item>↑3.03.13.2Gilhus N. E. Myasthenia gravis, respiratory function, and respiratory tract disease. Journal of neurology 2023; 1–12. Advance online publication. doi: 10.1007/s00415-023-11733-y</item>
      <item>↑4.04.14.24.3Misra, U. K., Kalita, J., Singh, V. K., &amp; Kumar, S. A study of comorbidities in myasthenia gravis. Acta neurologica Belgica 2020; 120(1), 59–64. doi: 10.1007/s13760-019-01102-w</item>
      <item>↑5.05.1Zhi-Feng Mao, Long-Xiu Yang, Xue-An Mo, Chao Qin, Yong-Rong Lai, NingYu He, Tong Li &amp; Maree L. Hackett. Frequency of Autoimmune Diseases in Myasthenia

Gravis: A Systematic Review, International Journal of Neuroscience 2011; 121:3, 121-129. doi: 10.3109/00207454.2010.539307</item>
      <item>↑6.06.16.26.36.46.56.66.7Jayam Trouth A, Dabi A, Solieman N, Kurukumbi M, Kalyanam J. Myasthenia Gravis: A Review. Autoimmune diseases. 2012;2012:874680–10. doi: 10.1155/2012/874680</item>
      <item>↑7.07.17.2Breiner A, Widdifield J, Katzberg HD, Barnett C, Bril V, Tu K. Epidemiology of myasthenia gravis in Ontario, Canada. Neuromuscular disorders : NMD. 2016;26(1):41–6. doi: 10.1016/j.nmd.2015.10.009</item>
      <item>↑8.08.18.2Jaretzki A, Barohn RJ, Ernstoff RM, Kaminski HJ, Keesey JC, Penn AS, et al. Myasthenia gravis : Recommendations for clinical research standards. Neurology. 2000;55(1):16–23. doi: 10.1016/S0003-4975(00)01595-2</item>
      <item>↑Green, Joshua D., Richard J. Barohn, Emanuela Bartoccion, Michael Benatar, Derrick Blackmore, Vinay Chaudhry, Manisha Chopra et al. "Epidemiological evidence for a hereditary contribution to myasthenia gravis: a retrospective cohort study of patients from North America."Bmj Open10, no. 9 (2020): e037909.</item>
      <item>↑National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences. Manual Muscle Testing Procedures. Available from: https://www.niehs.nih.gov/research/resources/assets/docs/muscle_grading_and_testing_procedures_508.pdf (accessed 11 May 2023)</item>
      <item>↑11.011.1Burns TM, Conaway M, Sanders DB. The MG Composite: A valid and reliable outcome measure for myasthenia gravis. Neurology. 2010;74(18):1434–40. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181dc1b1e</item>
      <item>↑12.012.1Eculizumab (Soliris): Alexion Pharma Canada Corporation (CAN). Clinical Review Report: Adult patients with generalized myasthenia gravis: Appendix 5, Description and Appraisal of Outcome Measures. Ottawa (ON): Canadian Agency for Drugs and Technologies in Health; 2020.https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK567509/#:~:text=Myasthenia%20Gravis%20Activities%20of%20Daily%20Living%20Scale%20(MG%2DADL),-The%20MG%2DADL&amp;text=Each%20of%20the%20items%20is,indicate%20greater%20severity%20of%20symptoms</item>
      <item>↑13.013.113.213.3Thomsen JLS, Andersen H. Outcome Measures in Clinical Trials of Patients With Myasthenia Gravis. Frontiers in neurology. 2020;11:596382–596382. doi: 10.3389/fneur.2020.596382</item>
      <item>↑14.014.114.214.314.4Barnett C, Herbelin L, Dimachkie MM, Barohn RJ. Measuring Clinical Treatment Response in Myasthenia Gravis. Neurologic clinics. 2018;36(2):339–53. doi: 10.1016/j.ncl.2018.01.006</item>
      <item>↑Burns TM, Conaway MR, Cutter GR, Sanders DB. Less is more, or almost as much: A 15-item quality-of-life instrument for myasthenia gravis. Muscle &amp; nerve. 2008;38(2):957–63. doi: 10.1002/mus.21053</item>
      <item>↑16.016.1La Porta F, Caselli S, Susassi S, Cavallini P, Tennant A, Franceschini M. Is the Berg Balance Scale an Internally Valid and Reliable Measure of Balance Across Different Etiologies in Neurorehabilitation? A Revisited Rasch Analysis Study. Archives of physical medicine and rehabilitation. 2012;93(7):1209–16. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2012.02.020</item>
      <item>↑17.017.1Berg, K., Wood-Dauphinee, S. L., Williams, J. I., &amp; Gayton, D. (1989).Berg Balance Scale (BBS)[Database record]. APA PsycTests.

https://doi.org/10.1037/t28729-000</item>
      <item>↑18.018.118.218.318.4Corrado B, Giardulli B, Costa M. Evidence-based practice in rehabilitation of myasthenia gravis. A systematic review of the literature. Journal of Functional Morphology and Kinesiology. 2020 Sep 27;5(4):71. https://doi.org/10.3390/jfmk5040071</item>
      <item>↑19.019.119.2Aupetitallot V, Franco AB. Effects of Physical Exercise on Functional and Respiratory Capacity, Quality of Life, and Fatigue Perception in Myasthenia Gravis Patients: A Systematic Review. Critical Reviews™ in Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine. 2021;33(1). https://doi.org/10.1615/CritRevPhysRehabilMed.2021037593</item>
      <item>↑Cup EH, Pieterse AJ, ten Broek-Pastoor JM, Munneke M, van Engelen BG, Hendricks HT, van der Wilt GJ, Oostendorp RA. Exercise therapy and other types of physical therapy for patients with neuromuscular diseases: a systematic review. Archives of physical medicine and rehabilitation. 2007 Nov 1;88(11):1452-64. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2007.07.024</item>
      <item>↑21.021.121.2Mermier CM, Schneider SM, Gurney AB, Weingart HM, Wilmerding MV. Preliminary results : Effect of whole-body cooling in patients with myasthenia gravis. Medicine and science in sports and exercise. 2006;38(1):13–20.doi: 10.1249/01.mss.0000180887.33650.0f.</item>
      <item>↑22.022.1Payedimarri A babu, Ratti M, Rescinito R, Vasile A, Seys D, Dumas H, et al. Development of a Model Care Pathway for Myasthenia Gravis. International journal of environmental research and public health. 2021;18(21):11591–. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph182111591.</item>
      <item>↑Law C, Flaherty CV, Bandyopadhyay S. A Review of Psychiatric Comorbidity in Myasthenia Gravis. Curēus (Palo Alto, CA). 2020;12(7):e9184–e9184.  https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.9184.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
