<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Post Concussion Syndrome Case Study</title>
  <source> Following a Fall extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Post_Concussion_Syndrome_Case_Study:_Following_a_Fall</url>
  <parent_folder>Neurological </parent_folder>
  <section>Post Concussion Syndrome Case Study: Following a Fall</section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>The following is a fictional case study that is intended for educational purposes. The patient is a 36 year-old female experiencingpost concussion syndromefollowing a fall while ice-skating. Four weeks after being diagnosed with a [[Assessment and Management of Concussion|assessment and management of concussion] the patient continued to experience prolonged symptoms including; persistent headaches, altered mood, impaired balance and decreased concentration, affecting her ability to work and quality of life. The purpose of this case study is to present to the readers, a typical patient with post-concussion syndrome, and the effects that post-concussion syndrome has on a patient's quality of life. Subsequently, this case study is intended to provide an example as to how post-concussion syndrome can be managed with physiotherapy.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/d/da/Post_concussion_syndrome.png/300px-Post_concussion_syndrome.png"/>
    <paragraph>assessment and management of concussionis a mild brain injury that is commonly seen in events such as sports and motor vehicle accidents. After the initial injury, symptoms such as headache and dizziness tend to persist for weeks, months, or even years; this phenomenon is referred to aspost-concussion syndrome (PCS).[2]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The consequences of concussion can include physical, cognitive and/or emotional abnormalities. The duration of concussion symptoms can range depending on the nature of the injury and the individual affected. Sport-related concussion symptoms typically resolve in 7-10 days in adults, and up to 3-4 weeks in children and adolescence. However, in some cases, these symptoms persist for a longer period of time, this is referred to as post-concussion syndrome.[3]Following a concussion, patients are typically advised to rest and avoid any strenuous physical or cognitive activity until the patient’s symptoms have diminished. This has also been the traditional approach for post concussion syndrome combined with education, support/reassurance, antidepressants, and neuro-cognitive rehabilitation.[4]However, more recent research has recommended that there are several active therapies that may benefit recovery if intensity is kept below the symptom threshold.[3]Some of these active approaches may include cognitive therapies, physical therapy, aerobic exercise, vestibular therapies and ocular therapies. Although rest may be important in the initial phases of recovery from concussion, there is evidence that low-level exercise and multimodal physical therapy is beneficial for patients who are recovering slowly following a sports related concussion.[5]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TF_xyN_yg44&amp;fbclid=IwAR1SN__FxhSENhvW5wVI-9msZtZizwrA1irCsVsmfT7fCnMHU4GIBhQDPO4[6]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This video reviews the definition and differences between concussion and post-concussion syndrome. It is important to distinguish between the two conditions as management is different for both. Ability to make a correct diagnosis and provide appropriate treatment leads to improved outcomes and quicker recovery times.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>A 36-year-old female with post-concussion syndrome; seeking help from physiotherapy due to persistent symptoms of headache and dizziness that are negatively affecting her quality of life. There are no other relevant comorbid conditions.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>
    Subjective
    <paragraph>History of Present Illness-Initial injury was sustained when the patient fell and hit the back of her head while ice-skating and lost consciousness. She was sent to the hospital and diagnosed with a concussion. The patient was discharged from the hospital the following day and returned home. Patient returned to work four days post injury, but was unable to continue after a few hours due to the presence of severe headache. She then remained off work for a few weeks with persistent symptoms, at which point the she made an appointment with her family physician. Her family physician referred her to see a physiotherapist for rehabilitation and management.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Past Medical History- Healthy prior to injury; no previous trauma, surgeries, or other serious health conditions/comorbidities noted</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Major Symptoms:Headache- constant, dull, diffuse headache, 2/10 at rest</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medications-occasionally takes Tylenol 2-3 days per week if headaches become unbearable (i.e., 8/10 pain)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Health Habits-Non-smoker; consumption of wine (2-3 glasses/week) prior to the injury - has ceased drinking any alcohol post-injury</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Social History-Registered Nurse (RN) for 11 years; practiced yoga for 10 years and has been teaching yoga for the past 5 years; currently living in a two-storey townhouse with her fiancé.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Current Level of Function-Able to ambulate normally at home and perform simple chores independently. Sleep quality has decreased markedly since the injury: has trouble falling asleep and wakes up 2-3 times on average at night. She is able to drive during the day time, but has difficulty at night time due to light sensitivity (i.e., bright lights from car); decreased concentration and memory has been noted. The patient is more likely to become emotional over relatively trivial issues (e.g., spilling milk). Tolerance for moderately challenging activities (such as work) has decreased drastically due to headaches, decreased cognitive capacity, moodiness. She also notes some tightness/discomfort around her shoulder and the back of her neck, which is similar to wearing a heavy backpack and is aggravated by stress. Furthermore, the patient also reports slight dizziness after certain activities, such as bending/squatting down to pick something up and quickly stand up, and frequent head turns during grocery shopping; but they usually resolve quickly with the cessation of the movements.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Objective
    <paragraph>Blood Pressure- 108 mmHg / 66 mmHg (within normal limits)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Heart Rate- 66 bpm (within normal limits)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>General Observation- no significant postural abnormalities</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gait- normal</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Speech- normal speech comprehension and fluency</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Upper Limb Scan Exam- normal</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Upper Limb Neurological Exam- normal dermatomes, myotomes &amp; reflexes</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Cranial Nerve Testing- normal</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Cervical Active ROM-all ranges within normal limits, no pain noted, patient notes tightness bilaterally with flexion, side flexion, and rotation</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Superficial and Deep Neck Flexors- normal activation and strength</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Palpation-increased tightness bilaterally in upper fibre trapezius and levator scapulae</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Outcome Measures</section>
  <section>
    Modified Clinical Test for Sensory Interaction on Balance (CTSIB-M)
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Condition</th>
        <th>Results (out of 30 sec)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Firm Surface, Eyes Open</td>
        <td>Trial 1: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Firm Surface, Eyes Closed</td>
        <td>Trial 1: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Foam Surface, Eyes Open</td>
        <td>Trial 1: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Foam Surface, Eyes Closed</td>
        <td>Avg: 19.3 sec(Trial 1: 18 sec;Trial 2: 21 sec;Trial 3: 19 sec)</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>(Trial 1: 18 sec;Trial 2: 21 sec;Trial 3: 19 sec)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Total Score:111 sec/ 120 sec (sum of best results from each condition)</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    StaticBalance
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Condition</th>
        <th>Results (out of 30 sec)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Tandem stance (eyes open)</td>
        <td>Left foot behind: 30 secRight foot behind: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Tandem Stance (eyes closed)</td>
        <td>Left foot behind:Avg: 15.3 sec(Trial 1: 15 sec;Trial 2: 17 sec;Trial 3: 14 sec)Right foot behind:Avg: 13.7(Trial 1: 12 sec;Trial 2: 15 sec;Trial 3: 14 sec)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Single Leg Stance (eyes open)</td>
        <td>Left foot: 30 secRight foot: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Single Leg Stance (eyes closed)</td>
        <td>Left foot:Avg: 7 sec(Trial 1: 5 sec;Trial 2: 9 sec;Trial 3: 7 sec)Right foot:Avg: 8.3 sec(Trial 1: 8 sec;Trial 2: 10 sec;Trial 3: 7 sec)</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Right foot behind: 30 sec</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(Trial 1: 15 sec;Trial 2: 17 sec;Trial 3: 14 sec)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Right foot behind:Avg: 13.7</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(Trial 1: 12 sec;Trial 2: 15 sec;Trial 3: 14 sec)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Right foot: 30 sec</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(Trial 1: 5 sec;Trial 2: 9 sec;Trial 3: 7 sec)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Right foot:Avg: 8.3 sec</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(Trial 1: 8 sec;Trial 2: 10 sec;Trial 3: 7 sec)</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Functional Gait Assessment
    <paragraph>Score: 29/30 - Mild difficulties for "Gait with Eyes Closed" condition (Score: 2/3)</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    The Headache Impact Test (HIT-6)
    <paragraph>Score: 61 - Severe impact on quality of life</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Vestibular-Oculomotor Screening (VOMS) Test
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Vestibular/Ocular Motor Test</th>
        <th>Headaches(0-10)</th>
        <th>Dizziness(0-10)</th>
        <th>Nausea(0-10)</th>
        <th>Fogginess(0-10)</th>
        <th>Comments</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Baseline Symptoms</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Constant dull headache at rest</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Smooth Pursuits</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Saccades - Horizontal</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>1</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Symptoms returned to baseline in less than 30s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Saccades - Verticle</td>
        <td>3</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Symptoms returned to baseline in less than 30s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Convergence (Near Point)</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Able to bring the tip of pen to nose, no double vision noted</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>VOR - Horizontal</td>
        <td>6</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>3</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Symptoms returned to baseline after ~1 min</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>VOR - Vertical</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Symptoms returned to baseline after ~30s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Visual Motion Sensitivity Test</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Symptoms returned to baseline after ~30s</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>(0-10)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(0-10)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(0-10)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(0-10)</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/c/ca/VOMS.jpg"/>
  </section>
  <section>Clinical Impression</section>
  <section>
    Diagnosis
    <paragraph>36 year-old female presenting with post-concussion syndrome 4 weeks after diagnosis of concussion from fall while ice skating on Jan 2, 2020. Patient has impaired balance, vestibular system, and motion sensitivity. She has a persistent headache, which can be exacerbated by motion, cognitive tasks, stress, and tightness in muscles such as upper fibre trapezius and levator scapulae. These symptoms are interfering with return to work, driving at night, getting a restful sleep, grocery shopping, spending time outside, and screen time. The patient is an excellent candidate for physiotherapy.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Problem List</section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>For physiotherapy intervention, multiple types of treatment may be used independently or in combination depending on the type and extent of the injury/condition. For this patient, it was decided to use a combination of education, manual therapy supplemented with stretches, along with balance and gaze stabilizing exercises in order to form a well-rounded treatment plan to address multiple items outlined in the above sections of the case study.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Patient-focused Goals
    <paragraph>Short-term goals:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Long-term goals:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Education</section>
  <section>
    Manual Therapy
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/0/01/Superficial-Muscles-of-the-Back.jpg/300px-Superficial-Muscles-of-the-Back.jpg"/>
    <paragraph>Soft Tissue Release Technique</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parameters:Passive approach with gliding pressure along muscle fibres in multiple planes, 10 reps, 1-2 sets each side</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Progression: Can progress to performing active-assisted and then active STR</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Trigger PointRelease Technique</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parameters:Apply pressure on trigger points for 30 seconds, 2 reps each side</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Exercises (Balance, Stretches, Gaze Stability)</section>
  <section>
    Balance
    <paragraph>Warrior Pose- Patient stands with one foot in front, the other foot takes a big step behind. With both feet facing forward, patient can bring arms out to the side for increased stability (may use wall or counter for extra stability if needed). Once in position, patient closes eyes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parameters: Hold position for 30 seconds with 2 repetitions on each side; perform daily</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Progression: Bring back foot closer to front foot (until in tandem stance), remove handheld support, bring arms down to side</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Tree Pose- Patient stands on one foot with the other out in front resting on a plastic cup. Patient performs static stance without crushing the cup under their foot. Patient may use handheld support (i.e., counter, wall, etc.). Once in position, patient closes eyes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parameters: Hold position for 30 seconds with 2 repetitions on each side; perform daily</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Progression: Remove handheld support, remove cup support, bring arms to centre, bring leg up to rest on weight bearing leg (to create yoga "tree pose")</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gait with Eyes Closed- Using a space with continuous support (i.e., area of wall available to walk beside), patient stands by hand support (wall, or parallel bars if in clinic) and attempts walking with eyes closed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parameters: Walk 5 steps one way, turn around and walk back to start, complete this 4 times (with proper guarding); perform daily</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Progression: Remove handheld support (always with proper guarding)</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Stretches
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/3/33/Levator_scap_stretch.jpg/300px-Levator_scap_stretch.jpg"/>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/d/d7/Upper_traps_stretch.jpg"/>
    <paragraph>Upper Fibers Trapezius (UFT)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>To stretch left upper fibres, patient moves right ear to right shoulder. The same is true for stretching right upper fibres, however, patient moves left ear to left shoulder. Can perform in seated or standing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Levator Scapula (LS)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>To stretch left side, patient moves left hand to apply downward pressure at the base of the neck (left side). Then patient rotates their head to the right and brings their chin to their armpit. Stretch for the right side is performed opposite to the left. Can be performed in seated or standing.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parameters(for both UFT and LS): Static stretch, 30 second holds x 2 repetitions 2-3xa day; performed until gentle stretch is felt (each side)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Progression: Apply overpressure in direction of head movement to increase stretch</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Gaze Stability Exercise
    <paragraph>VOR X1- In seated position, the patient holds an object stationary in front of face while turning their head from side to side as fast as they can without blurred vision, while maintaining visual fixation on the object (Note - patient must adapt their head speed to be slower if object becomes blurry)VOR X2- In seated position, the patient repeats VOR X1, but incorporates movement of the object in the opposite direction of the head movement</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parameters:1-2 minutes, 5x per day (can also perform with vertical head movements, but main focus with this patient is on horizontal movements)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Progression:Perform in standing position - work up to walking to make it more functional</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Outcome</section>
  <section>
    Change in Status Post Intervention
    <paragraph>After the patient completed physiotherapy treatment (duration: 8 weeks, 2 sessions per week), she noticed a marked change in the presence of her symptoms. The headaches completely disappeared compared to baseline, changing from a constant dull and aching pain to no pain. While completing her ADLs, the dizziness she previously experienced had become little to none and she began a gradual return to work at 3 weeks into treatment. Patient noticed that her moodiness was diminishing, and she no longer became annoyed by small inconveniences (such as spilling milk). She was able to get back into grocery shopping with her fiancé without any complaints of dizziness, and the sensitivity to light decreased. The tension in her shoulders and the back of the neck become unnoticeable. As well, the patient described her ability to sleep as one of the biggest improvements, leading to feeling more rested to take on the day.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome Measures
    <paragraph>Modified Clinical Test for Sensory Interaction on Balance (CTSIB-M)</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Condition</th>
        <th>Results (out of 30sec)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Firm Surface, Eyes Open</td>
        <td>Trial 1: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Firm Surface, Eyes Closed</td>
        <td>Trial 1: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Foam Surface, Eyes Open</td>
        <td>Trial 1: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Foam Surface, Eyes Closed</td>
        <td>Trial 1: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Total Score: 120 sec / 120 sec</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Static Balance</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Condition</th>
        <th>Results (out of 30 sec)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Tandem Stance (eyes open)</td>
        <td>Left foot behind: 30 secRight foot behind: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Tandem Stance (eyes closed)</td>
        <td>Left foot behind:30 secRight foot behind:30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Single Leg Stance (eyes open)</td>
        <td>Left foot:  30 secRight foot: 30 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Single Leg Stance (eyes closed)</td>
        <td>Left foot:30 sec(Trial 1: 24 sec;Trial 2: 30 sec)Right foot:30 sec(Trial 1)</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Right foot behind: 30 sec</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Right foot behind:30 sec</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Right foot: 30 sec</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(Trial 1: 24 sec;Trial 2: 30 sec)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Right foot:30 sec(Trial 1)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Functional Gait Assessment</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Score: 30/30</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The Headache Impact Test (HIT-6)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Score:42</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Vestibular-Oculomotor Screening (VOMS) Test</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Vestibular/Ocular Motor Test</th>
        <th>Headaches(0-10)</th>
        <th>Dizziness(0-10)</th>
        <th>Nausea(0-10)</th>
        <th>Fogginess(0-10)</th>
        <th>Comments</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Baseline Symptoms</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Smooth Pursuits</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Saccades - Horizontal</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Saccades - Verticle</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Convergence (Near Point)</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>No double vision noted</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>VOR - Horizontal</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>1</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Symptoms returned to baseline within 15s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>VOR - Vertical</td>
        <td>1</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Symptoms returned to baseline within 10s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Visual Motion Sensitivity Test</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>Symptoms returned to baseline within 10s</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>(0-10)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(0-10)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(0-10)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>(0-10)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Patient reported little to no symptoms throughout the VOMS test; where she did experience slight symptoms, they were resolved within 10-15 seconds of rest, which is significantly shorter compared to the initial assessment.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discharge Plan
    <paragraph>Patient has demonstrated immense improvement in symptoms since the initiation of physiotherapy. Throughout the 8-weeks of treatment she has met most, if not all of her goals. Although the patient still notes very mild symptoms with the VOR along with the Visual Motion Sensitivity Test, she is able to recover with a brief resting period. Moreover, she was able to return to work for 3 days per week, and start practicing yoga. Overall, she is satisfied with her progress and has decided to conclude her visits.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>It was recommended to the patient to continue the provided exercises to maintain her status and to further improve her symptoms. Thehome exercise programincluded static neck stretches, balance exercises (along with recommendation to incorporate yoga), and education on the use of heat to further relieve pain (after clearing contraindications and precautions). The patient was told to call or email if she had any further questions, or make a new appointment if her symptoms started to get worse.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Overall, this is a relatively straightforward case of PCS. Several important factors played a key role in the patient’s recovery. Firstly, the patient did not sustain any additional injuries during her initial fall. Because the injury was predominantly neurological, we were able to create a more focused assessment and treatment design. Due to the lack of secondary injury, considerations pertaining to musculoskeletal injuries and their impact on neurological findings did not require an in-depth investigation. Secondly, because the patient was fairly young and healthy prior to injury, the rate of recovery was predicted to be shorter, compared to an elderly patient with comorbidities such as diabetes or osteoarthritis. The patient has a background in health and fitness and was motivated to get back to pre-injury functions. As well, due to the patient’s background knowledge in nursing, the process of education was greatly facilitated. In regards to the patient's history of yoga practice, it was highly encouraged to begin and continue gradual return to practice within our treatment. Furthermore, the patient’s motivation and dedication to exercising prior to injury enabled her to persevere with her prescribed exercises, which were paramount to making progress towards recovery.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This case study is based on a real clinical case with modifications. The case does not capture all the common assessment and treatment techniques used, and serves as an introduction or overview of some of the positive impacts physiotherapy can bring to PCS patients. Other possible manifestations of post-concussion syndrome other than those represented in this case may include cervicogenic, autonomic, and visual presentations. Recommendations for assessment, education, and treatment regarding these symptoms can be found using theFowler-Kennedy Guidelines.[17]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Kenney L. Symptoms of Concussion [Internet]. 8 Sports Related Concussion Facts You Need To Know. 2015 [cited 2020May16]. Available from: http://www.lynnekenney.com/8-sports-related-concussion-facts-you-need-to-know/?fbclid=IwAR17B3F4buO2Xh-EmzTnAB_F5Y52CErbjQ2BvesOVnWfd0nzO33sbRLlc18</item>
      <item>↑Post-concussion syndrome [Internet]. Mayo Clinic. Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research; 2017 [cited 2020May11]. Available from: https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/post-concussion-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20353352</item>
      <item>↑3.03.13.2Leddy JJ, Baker JG, Willer B. Active Rehabilitation of Concussion and Post-concussion Syndrome. Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation Clinics of North America. 2016;27(2):437–54.</item>
      <item>↑Mcallister TW, Arciniegas D. Evaluation and treatment of postconcussive symptoms. NeuroRehabilitation. 2002;17(4):265–83.</item>
      <item>↑Schneider KJ, Iverson GL, Emery CA, Mccrory P, Herring SA, Meeuwisse WH. The effects of rest and treatment following sport-related concussion: a systematic review of the literature. British Journal of Sports Medicine. 2013Nov;47(5):304–7.</item>
      <item>↑American Academy of Neurology. Neurobytes: Concussion Versus Post-Concussion Syndrome - American Academy of Neurology [Internet]. 2019 [cited 16 May 2020]. Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TF_xyN_yg44&amp;fbclid=IwAR1SN__FxhSENhvW5wVI-9msZtZizwrA1irCsVsmfT7fCnMHU4GIBhQDPO4</item>
      <item>↑Evans RW. Post-traumatic headaches. Neurologic Clinics. 2004;22(1):237–49.</item>
      <item>↑Modified Clinical Test of Sensory Interaction on Balance [Internet]. Shirley Ryan AbilityLab. [cited 2020May12]. Available from: https://www.sralab.org/rehabilitation-measures/modified-clinical-test-sensory-interaction-balance</item>
      <item>↑Springer BA, Marin R, Cyhan T, Roberts H, Gill NW. Normative Values for the Unipedal Stance Test with Eyes Open and Closed. Journal of Geriatric Physical Therapy. 2007;30(1):8–15.</item>
      <item>↑El-Kashlan HK, Shepard NT, Asher AM, Smith-Wheelock M, Telian SA. Evaluation of Clinical Measures of Equilibrium. The Laryngoscope. 1998;108(3):311–9.</item>
      <item>↑Wrisley DM, Marchetti GF, Kuharsky DK, Whitney SL. Reliability, Internal Consistency, and Validity of Data Obtained With the Functional Gait Assessment. Physical Therapy. 2004Jan;84(10):906–18.</item>
      <item>↑Wrisley DM, Kumar NA. Functional Gait Assessment: Concurrent, Discriminative, and Predictive Validity in Community-Dwelling Older Adults. Physical Therapy. 2010Jan;90(5):761–73.</item>
      <item>↑Yang M, Rendas-Baum R, Varon SF, Kosinski M. Validation of the Headache Impact Test (HIT-6™) across episodic and chronic migraine. Cephalalgia. 2010Jun;31(3):357–67.</item>
      <item>↑Mucha A, Collins MW, Elbin R, Furman JM, Troutman-Enseki C, Dewolf RM, et al. A Brief Vestibular/Ocular Motor Screening (VOMS) Assessment to Evaluate Concussions. The American Journal of Sports Medicine. 2014Aug;42(10):2479–86.</item>
      <item>↑What Is Vestibular Ocular Motor Screening? [Internet]. ReThink Concussions. 2017 [cited 2020May11]. Available from: https://rethinkconcussions.upmc.com/what-is-voms/</item>
      <item>↑Duke Neurology. Sports Concussion Exam (7 of 9): Vestibular/Ocular-Motor Screening (VOMS) [Internet]. 2016 [cited May 16 2020]. Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CJF6kJcFGqE</item>
      <item>↑17.017.1Fowler Kennedy Sport Medicine. Post-Concussion Syndrome Management Guidelines. Available from: https://www.fowlerkennedy.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Post-Concussion-Treatment-Guidelines.pdf (Accessed 12 May 2019)</item>
      <item>↑18.018.1Herdman S, Clendaniel R, Mattox D, Holliday M, Niparko J. Vestibular adaptation exercises and recovery: Acute stage after acoustic neuroma resection. Otolaryngology - Head and Neck Surgery. 1995;113(1):77–87.</item>
      <item>↑Jones O. TeachMe Anatomy [Internet]. TeachMe Anatomy . 2020 [cited 2020May16]. Available from: https://teachmeanatomy.info/back/muscles/superficial/</item>
      <item>↑López CL, Jiménez JM, Aizpurúa JDLH, Grande JP, Peñas CFDL. Efficacy of manual therapy in the treatment of tension-type headache. A systematic review from 2000 to 2013. Neurología (English Edition). 2016;31(6):357–69.</item>
      <item>↑Fernández-De-Las-Peñas C, Ge H-Y, Arendt-Nielsen L, Cuadrado ML, Pareja JA. Referred pain from trapezius muscle trigger points shares similar characteristics with chronic tension type headache. European Journal of Pain. 2007;11(4):475–82.</item>
      <item>↑Tylosova N. 11 Stretches to Relieve Neck and Shoulder Pain [Internet]. 11 Stretches to Relieve Neck and Shoulder Pain. Bright Side ; [cited 2020May16]. Available from: https://brightside.me/inspiration-health/11-stretches-to-relieve-neck-and-shoulder-tension-656360/</item>
      <item>↑Head Tilt / Upper Trapezius Stretch (Flexibility) [Internet]. Head Tilt / Upper Trapezius Stretch (Flexibility). Sainte Luke's; [cited 2020May23]. Available from: https://www.saintlukeskc.org/health-library/head-tilt-upper-trapezius-stretch-flexibility</item>
      <item>↑Ellis MJ, Leddy JJ, Willer B. Physiological, vestibulo-ocular and cervicogenic post-concussion disorders: An evidence-based classification system with directions for treatment. Brain Injury. 2014;29(2):238–48.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
