<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Rood Approach</title>
  <source>nan extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Rood_Approach</url>
  <parent_folder>Neurological </parent_folder>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>Rood’s approach is  a neurophysiological and developmental treatment approach that was developed by Margret Rood to improve the tone of muscles (both flaccidity andSpasticity).</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Rood’s approach is based on the known physiological facts that sensory stimulation provides desired muscular response and was specially designed for patients with motor control problem.[1]developmental sequences are used, i.e. from lower to higher levels, and practice of sensory-motor response until learning is achieved. The rules of sensory input are: 1) a fast, brief stimulus produces synchronous movement output, 2) a fast, repetitive stimulus produces a sustained response , 3) a maintained sensory input produces a sustained response, 4) and a slow, repetitive, and rhythmical stimulus decreases the tone in muscle response. Additionally, we can use neck flexion, extension, rotation, and side-bending of the neck to stimulate the vestibular receptors. We can even use symmetric andAsymmetrical Tonic Neck Reflexto  generate tone in the flexors and extensors.[2][3]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>-Rood’s approach was based on four basic principles :[3]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Rood clarified four types of receptors which can be stimulated to acquire desired muscular response - proprioceptive receptors, exteroceptive receptors, vestibular receptors and special sense organs.[4]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>-In Rood approach ,sensory stimulationcauses ;</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>trophic change by axoplasmic flow in nerve processes over period of time.</item>
      <item>as well as immediate effect by transmission of nerve impulses.</item>
      <item>sensory stimulation can activate or deactivate the receptor by facilitation or inhibition, which makes it possible to get the desired muscular response.[1]</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>Principles</section>
  <section>Autonomic nervous system stimuli</section>
  <section>
    Facilitatory technique
    <list>
      <item>Fast tactile stimulation Exteroceptors are stimulated byFast Brushing, fast icing, quick stretching, mild stroking, and rubbing the skin, which results in a protective withdrawal response and consequent movement of the extremities.</item>
      <item>Proprioceptors, such as theGolgi Tendon Organ,Muscle Spindles, and receptors around the joint, are stimulated by tapping and touching the skin, which causes muscular contraction. Rubber, tapping on the belly of the muscle, and short stretches can all activate these sensory organs.</item>
      <item>Heat-facilitating icings A and C. ( A): Icing: apply ice cubes quickly in order to trigger a reflex withdrawal that resembles light touch. (C)  icing, or elevated stimulus threshold. Ice cubes are applied to theDermatomesor the belly of the muscle for 15 to 20 minutes.</item>
      <item>There is co-contraction around the Joint when there is severe joint compression exerted along the bone's longitudinal axis. It can be coupled with an ontogenetic pattern, including standing, sitting, quadrupedal stance, or prone on theElbow. There are two ways to apply pressure: manually and via weight cuffs.</item>
      <item>rapid light stretch and low threshold stimuli that cause the stretched muscle to initiate a phasic response. The rapid stretch has an instantaneous effect.</item>
      <item>It helps to facilitate the muscle by tapping over the Tendon orMuscle.</item>
      <item>Stretch reaction is triggered when pressure is applied to the belly of the muscle, stretching the muscle spindles.</item>
      <item>force applied on the prominence of the bones.[8][9]</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>[10]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Inhibitory techniques
    <list>
      <item>Joint approximation is another term for light joint compression. used in hypertonic muscl to suppress tone.</item>
      <item>Slow stroking: The tone is inhibited by gently pressing on the posterior rami slowly and firmly. After three to five minutes, the patient is allowed to relax.</item>
      <item>It is possible to roll the patient slowly from a supine position to a side laying position or to rock them slowly.</item>
      <item>Maintaining body heat by encircling the targeted area to be inhibited is referred to as neutral warmth. For 10 to 20 minutes, it is completed.</item>
      <item>Heat that is higher than body temperature is employed as a rebound effect, so neutral heat is used.</item>
      <item>Through the presence of receptors, pressure applied to a muscle's insertion inhibits that muscle.</item>
      <item>Stretching continuously for a few minutes to several weeks causes the muscle spindle to relapse into longer positions. Allowing lengthy positioning will upset the antagonistic and agonistic tonal equilibrium.</item>
      <item>Low thresholdGolgi Tendon Organbe employed to inhibit the agonists by unresisted contraction; this would facilitate the antagonists in return.[9]</item>
    </list>
    <paragraph>[11]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Basic concepts
    <paragraph>Rood's four basic concepts are;</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Its role with stroke patients
    <paragraph>Rood’s approach is significant in improving the ability of independent self-care. The two components of Rood’ treatment may be the cause of this significant improvement which are ;</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Rood's approach uses different types of exercises and activities to help people recover after aStroke. These exercises involve stimulating different parts of the body and repeating movements.Stimulating the senses and doing purposeful activities helps people get better at taking care of themselves on their own. Other research studies have also shown that these types of exercises can improve motor skills in stroke patients. For Example, for the arms, they might have to wipe a table or try to open a jar. And for the legs, they might have to stand up from a sitting position or kick a ball. so it can prevent various morbidities and mortality, includingDeep Vein Thrombosis, decubitus ulcers,Pneumonia, andContractures.[8]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.1Rood[https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/6023297/MS. The treatment of neuromuscular dysfunction: Rood approach. Notes taken by C.

Trombly at lecture delivered in Boston. 1976 Jul.]</item>
      <item>↑[1]Bordoloi K, Deka RS. Scientific reconciliation of the concepts and principles of rood approach. Int J Health Sci Res. 2018; 8(9):225-234.</item>
      <item>↑3.03.1RoodMS. Neurophysiological Reactions as a Basis for Physical Therapy*. Physical Therapy. 1954 Sep 1;34(9):444–9.</item>
      <item>↑offBJ. The application of recent advances in neurophysiology to Miss M. Rood’s concept of neuromuscular facilitation. PubMed. 1972 Dec 10;58(12):409–15.</item>
      <item>↑Ayres, A. J. Occupational therapy directed toward neuromuscular integration. Occupational therapy. 1963;3: 358-459.</item>
      <item>↑AyresAJ. The development of sensory integrative theory and practice: A collection of the works of A. Jean Ayres. Kendall/Hunt Publishing Company; 1974.</item>
      <item>↑Rood, M. S. Neurophysiological reactions as a basis for physical therapy. Physical Therapy Review. 1954;34:444-449.</item>
      <item>↑8.08.1BordoloiK, Deka RS. Effectiveness of home exercise program with modified rood's approach on muscle strength in post cerebral haemorrhagic individuals of assam:a randomized trial. Int J Physiother. 2019;6:231–239</item>
      <item>↑9.09.1Joan Elizabeth Cash (1986).Cash’s Textbook of Neurology for Physiotherapists. J.P. Lippincott.</item>
      <item>↑YouTube. (2020). YouTube. Retrieved November 27, 2023, from https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfcwW5Kl_0M&amp;amp;t=2s.</item>
      <item>↑YouTube. (2020a).YouTube. Retrieved November 27, 2023, from https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=js1VtsoI3ic.</item>
      <item>↑Bordoloi K, Deka RS. Modified Rood’s approach and ability of independent selfcare in haemorrhagic stroke patients of Assam, India. International Journal of Research in Medical Sciences. 2020 Feb 26;8(3):1070.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
