<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Acute Motor Axonal Neuropathy (AMAN), a Variant of Guillain-Barre Syndrome</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Acute_Motor_Axonal_Neuropathy_(AMAN),_a_Variant_of_Guillain-Barre_Syndrome:_A_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Acute Motor Axonal Neuropathy </parent_folder>
  <section>Acute Motor Axonal Neuropathy (AMAN), a Variant of Guillain-Barre Syndrome: A Case Study</section>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This case study documents a fictional description of a patient presenting with acute motor axonal neuropathy (AMAN), which is a subtype ofGuillain-Barre Syndrome. The patient’s experience in acute care is discussed briefly, while the patients’ sub-acute and long-term rehabilitation is covered in more detail. The purpose of this case study is to highlight approaches to assessment, outcome planning, and treatment interventions in the context of a community-based rehabilitation setting during the sub-acute phase of the disease. The case study is unique as it employs an interdisciplinary approach andinternational classification of function, disability, and health (ICF)framework to address the pathology of the disease in a patient-specific manner.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>Acute motor axonal neuropathy (AMAN) is a variant type ofGuillain-Barre Syndrome(GBS). AMAN is a non-inflammatory disease whereby axons of motor nerve cells are selectively targeted and destroyed by the body’s own immune system. The myelin sheath surrounding the axon is unaffected. Studies suggest that the body’s immune system specifically attacks the membrane surrounding the axon called the axolemma. AMAN is characterized byacute progressive motor weakness, areflexia,ataxia, oculomotor dysfunction and absence of sensory symptoms[1]. AMAN is typically preceded by an infection from bacteria called Campylobacter jejuni[2]or Haemophilus influenzae[3]. Prevalence of AMAN is estimated at 5% of cases in North America and Europe[1], while 30-65% of cases are located in Asia, Central and South America[4].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The prognosis involves two categories of patients undergoing rapid recovery or slower recovery after reaching the highest levels of unchanging symptoms and dysfunction, or plateau phase[5]. It is proposed that recovery is achieved through mechanisms such as terminal motor nerve axonal regeneration and collateral reinnervation processes[6]. Documented cases in literature that are relevant find absent or minor sensory deficits are present among patients with AMAN, and majority of patients have complete symptom resolution with 5-day intravenous immunoglobulin (IV Ig) treatment[7]. Patients with AMAN continue to see improvements in ambulation and functional ability up to four years post-diagnosis[3]. This brings us to the purpose of the following case study of a patient with AMAN.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Physiotherapy assessment and treatment can help prevent the decline of functional status and maintain functional independence, muscle strength, posture, balance, and cardio-respiratory fitness. Moreover, it enables an individual to continue performing self-care routines and activities of daily living (ADLs). In accordance to the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) framework[8], the primary objective of this case study is to elaborate on how physical therapy rehabilitation assessment and treatment interventions can aim to address body structure and function impairments, activity limitations, and participation restrictions in patients with AMAN. The case study further aims to focus on patient-centred care and an interdisciplinary approach to assessment and management of AMAN in a community-based rehabilitation setting.</paragraph>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/7vmZVNmAYf4?"/>
    <paragraph>[9]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Case Background
    <paragraph>Trish Jones, a 62 year old female, initially presented with nausea and diarrhea one week after returning home from vacation in Mexico. Due to COVID-19 travel restrictions, Trish refrained from visiting the hospital’s emergency department. Instead, Trish booked an appointment with her family doctor in two weeks’ time after her quarantine was finished. Over the next week, Trish complained of progressive muscle weakness in her hands and feet. She had difficulty grasping items with her hands and reported difficulty climbing stairs. During the subsequent week, Trish reported decreased coordination while ambulating and unusual shortness of breath and fatigue. Prior to the visit with her family doctor, Trish lost her balance and fell while walking upstairs, which led to admission to the hospital’s emergency department.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Although no injuries were sustained by the fall,  diagnostic investigation continued and  Trish was diagnosed with acute motor axon neuropathy caused by Campylobacter jejuni, and was treated immediately with a high dose of intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIg) therapy[10]. Trish spent the next two weeks in the intensive care unit (ICU), where she required mechanical ventilation due to respiratory muscle weakness. The acute health care team performed passive range of motion, splinting, airway clearance techniques, and frequent repositioning to prevent the development of contractures, deep vein thrombosis, pressure ulcers, and other complications. Prior to discharge, Trish was educated by an interdisciplinary team (including a physiotherapist, occupational therapist) about the rehabilitation plan, safety considerations, and was also fitted for a 4-wheel rollator to assist in her recovery. It has been 12 weeks since her discharge from the hospital. No other medical conditions or comorbidities have developed, and her medical status has remained stable.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The sub-acute phase of rehabilitation will be patient-specific, utilizing an ICF framework to address body function and structural impairments, activity limitations, and participation restrictions. In addition, health care providers will employ a safety-based approach to prevent patient exhaustion, and promote patient confidence in performing functional activities or tasks.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Patient Profile (PP): Trish Jones, 62 year old female</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medical Diagnosis:Acute motor axonal neuropathy</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Nature of the Condition:Sub-acute phase of the disease, in recovery</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Primary Complaint:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Past Medical History (PMHx)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medications (Meds):High dose ofintravenous immunoglobulin (IVIg)therapy as needed</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Primary Reason For Referral:Recovery from AMAN</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>
    Subjective
    <paragraph>Trish reported that she was feeling unstable and did not have confidence when walking around. She stated that both her distal upper (hands, wrist) and lower extremities (ankle, feet) were weak, and that she was having difficulties performing basic activities such as opening a can, climbing stairs, or walking around her home. She has reported a loss of mobility due to muscle weakness in her ankles, which she further contributes to her instability when performing everyday tasks. Trish notes that she has enough hand and wrist strength to carry light objects but fatigues quickly.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Objective
    <paragraph>Skin Inspection</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Normalsensationwas reported with the following tests</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Dermatomes:normal sensation bilaterally in C1 to T1 dermatomes and L1 to S2 dermatomes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Myotomes:weakness in the following myotome groups:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Reflexes</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Table 1:Vital SignsandVentilatory Muscle Strengthmeasured at the time of initial assessment.</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Vital Sign</th>
        <th>Measure</th>
        <th>Interpretation</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Heart Rate (HR)</td>
        <td>78 bpm</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Blood Pressure</td>
        <td>128/82 mmHg</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Respiratory Rate</td>
        <td>18 bpm</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Ventilatory Muscle Testing</th>
        <th>Measure</th>
        <th>Interpretation</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Maximum expiratory pressure (MEP)</td>
        <td>100 mmH2O</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Minimum inspiratory pressure (MIP)</td>
        <td>65  mmH2O</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Table 2:Outcome measure scores at the time of initial assessment.</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Outcome Measure</th>
        <th>Score</th>
        <th>Interpretation</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>GBS disability score</td>
        <td>3/6</td>
        <td>Able to walk 5 meters with an aid</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>TUG</td>
        <td>40 seconds</td>
        <td>High risk of falls</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>BBS</td>
        <td>31/56</td>
        <td>High risk of falls</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>6-MWT</td>
        <td>237 meters</td>
        <td>Low function and mobility</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Range of Motion and Manual Muscle Testing (MMT)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Table 3:Active range of motion (AROM), passive range of motion (PROM), andmanual muscle testing (MMT)scores per joint at time of initial assessment.</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Joint</th>
        <th>AROM (degrees)  L/R</th>
        <th>PROM (degrees) L/R</th>
        <th>BilateralMMT score(out of 5)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Metatarsophalangeal joint</th>
        <td>Unable to move (bilat)</td>
        <td>Flexion 30/30Extension 80/80</td>
        <td>1 flexion, 1 extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Subtalar</th>
        <td>Unable to move (bilat)</td>
        <td>Inversion 30/30Eversion 10/10</td>
        <td>1 inversion, 1 eversion</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Ankle</th>
        <td>Unable to move (bilat)</td>
        <td>Plantarflexion 45/49Dorsiflexion 18/20</td>
        <td>2- plantarflexion, 2- dorsiflexion</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Knee</th>
        <td>Flexion: 110/ 115extension: 10/ 8</td>
        <td>Within normal limits (WNL)</td>
        <td>4- flexion, 4- extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Hip</th>
        <td>Flexion: 100/ 105Extension: 10/ 10External rotation: 25/ 40Internal rotation: 20/ 38Abduction: 35/ 38Adduction: 20/ 20</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4- flexion, 4- abduction</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Shoulder</th>
        <td>Flexion: 90/ 115Abduction: 85/ 100External rotation: 50/ 70Internal rotation:  55/ 75</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4 abduction</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Elbow</th>
        <td>Flexion: 145/ 147Extension: 0/0</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+  flexion, 4+ extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Wrist</th>
        <td>Flexion: 60/ 62Extension: 50/ 54</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4- flexion, 4- extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Metacarpophalangeal joint</th>
        <td>Flexion: 60/ 62Extension: 10/ 10</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>3+ flexion, 3+ extension</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Extension 80/80</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Eversion 10/10</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Dorsiflexion 18/20</paragraph>
    <paragraph>extension: 10/ 8</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 10/ 10</paragraph>
    <paragraph>External rotation: 25/ 40</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Internal rotation: 20/ 38</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Abduction: 35/ 38</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Adduction: 20/ 20</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Abduction: 85/ 100</paragraph>
    <paragraph>External rotation: 50/ 70</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Internal rotation:  55/ 75</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 0/0</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 50/ 54</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 10/ 10</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Clinical Impression</section>
  <section>
    Physiotherapy Diagnosis
    <paragraph>Trish’s primary clinical presentation is bilateral peripheral motor weakness without sensory loss which was due to a medical diagnosis of Acute Motor Axonal Neuropathy (AMAN), a variant of Guillain-Barre Syndrome. Her symptoms are more severe in the lower extremities, where she presents with loss of ROM and weakness in the dorsiflexors and plantarflexors.  Consequently, she exhibits decreased ability to maintain balance, an increased fear of falls, and is also unable to ambulate without a mobility aid (4-wheeled rollator). Trish does does not require any ventilatory support, however she experiences extreme fatigue after 15 minutes of ambulation that subsides with rest. Although retaining full ROM in the upper extremity, she has decreased grip strength which limits her ability to perform certain ADLs independently such as turning door knobs and opening cans. Currently, Trish is unable to participate in activities she previously enjoyed including pilates, bowling nights with her friends, and attending her husband’s fitness classes.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Problem List (based on the ICF framework)
    <paragraph>Body Function and Body Structure Impairments</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Activity Limitations</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Participation Restrictions</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Intervention
    <paragraph>The purpose of the listed interventions are to:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Patient-Specific Goals</section>
  <section>
    Management Program during Recovery Phase
    <paragraph>General notes for exercises[11]:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Table 4:Detailed Explanation of Physiotherapy Interventions</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Intervention</th>
        <th>Rationale</th>
        <th>FITT (frequency, intensity, time, type) principles</th>
        <th>Additional Notes</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Education:Proper postural education (neutral spine, sitting up tall, shoulders back) and management (recommend postural adjustments that will help her maintain proper posture - lumbar roll)Safety consideration when using a gait aidUnderstand disease progression, prognosis, patient-specific goals, and treatment planRole of caregiver (supportive and motivating but should encourage patient self-managment)Indicators to decrease or increase the level of intervention, and safety associated with each exercise</td>
        <td>Having the patient understand the development and progress of their condition can increase patient buy-in, increases patient safety, and allows patients to take a larger role in their own rehabilitation.</td>
        <td>Education should begin during the first session of therapy. Use of pamphlets or videos may be helpful too.</td>
        <td>As therapists, it is important to encourage patients without making promises on patient’s recovery time and degree of recovery[12].</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Range-of-motion:Neuro-proprioception techniques to facilitate ankle dorsiflexion and plantarflexion</td>
        <td>AAROM and PROM techniques that facilitate ankle ROM, to keep existing neuro-muscular junctions active, to encourage motor control.</td>
        <td>10 reps x 3 times/day,performed dailyEven if muscles are weak and full ROM cannot be achieved independently, the patient is encouraged to visualize the action during the exercise</td>
        <td>Since sensation is not lost in these patients, can use external cues on on leg to promote muscle contractionPROM can be assisted by the therapistAAROM can be done as part of the home intervention plan using a belt to assist with ankle dorsiflexionPROM technique can be done in rehabilitation or by a caregiver in a home setting.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Muscle strengthening:Examples include:supine glute bridgesseated hip flexionmini-squats with hands supported on counter/ stable surfacetheraband-resisted shoulder flexion and abductionbicep curls</td>
        <td>Continue to strengthen and maintain larger lower (ie. quadriceps glutes, and hamstring) and upper extremities (ie. biceps and tricep) and trunk prime movers, as these are required to regain previous activity levels and function</td>
        <td>8 reps x 3 sets with adequate rest in between (patient dependent)3x/wkIntensity: low to moderate level of exertionType: isometric and isotonic resistance training</td>
        <td>Patient should be aware of fatigue levels using the Rate of Perceived Exertion on the Borg Scale (begin at low intensity and progress to moderate intensity)Multi-joint exercises can also be included as it encourages muscle synergies (coordinate prime mover and stabilizer action)[13]Should be taught  in rehabilitation and performed in home setting.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Grip Strengthening:Hand therapy:GRASP(graded repetitive arm supplementary program[14][15]</td>
        <td>This program focuses on upper extremity strengthening, fine motor tasks and repetitive functional tasks.Although this program is only validated in the acute stroke population, this can be beneficial if adapted to patients ability to improve grip strength and general upper functional outcomes.</td>
        <td>1 hour of exercises, daily8 weeksRemember to modify and adapt exercise to patient-specific fatigue levels, allow for rest as necessary</td>
        <td>GRASP is a “homework-based” program that can be performed at home.Should be done in home setting.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Cardiovascular aerobictraining:ExamplesWalking using gait aidArm Cycle ergometerStationary bike</td>
        <td>Safe, low-level, aerobic exercise that does not go past level of fatigue is indicated for positive clinical outcomes</td>
        <td>30 min total (can be broken up into 5-10 minute bouts) 3x/weekRecommended to do walking with 4-wheeled rollator as this is a most functional activity</td>
        <td>Patient should be aware of fatigue levels using the Rate of Perceived Exertion on the Borg Scale (begin at low intensity and progress to moderate intensity)[16]Can be done in rehabilitation or home setting.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>BalanceandGaitParallel bar gait training (walking, weight shift, challenge balance)Body-weight supported treadmill training[17]Educate proper and safe use of gait aid</td>
        <td>Training balance can help improve patient’s confidence in functional activities that require balance and help patients improve motor control patterns</td>
        <td>Always perform this in a safe setting and with a therapist spotting the patient. Can be performed in a home setting if caregiver is taught the proper way to support patient.Use ofankle-foot orthosisas indicatedUse gait belt for safety as indicated</td>
        <td>By using a body weight treadmill, the patient may feel safer and more comfortable to ambulate without holding on to a support as they are supported by a harness.External facilitation to encourage ankle dorsiflexion and plantarflexion as indicated.Parallel bar and body-weight treadmill can be done in rehabilitation setting.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Functional TrainingStep upSit to standReaching for objects while standingAdapted pilates (e.g seated pilates)</td>
        <td>Putting it all together: Functional training takes a multifaceted approach to help patients strengthen, improve ROM, coordination and balance in a patient relevant</td>
        <td>10 reps (or as many as tolerated), 2x/daypreformed dailyFor pilates perform 1-2x/wkWhen these exercises are performed at home, make sure that they are performed safely and within the patient’s limit to prevent excessive fatigue</td>
        <td>Patient should be aware of fatigue levels using the Rate of Perceived Exertion on the Borg Scale (begin at low intensity and progress to moderate intensity)[16]Can be done in rehabilitation or home setting.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>performed daily</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Even if muscles are weak and full ROM cannot be achieved independently, the patient is encouraged to visualize the action during the exercise</paragraph>
    <paragraph>PROM technique can be done in rehabilitation or by a caregiver in a home setting.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Examples include:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>3x/wk</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Intensity: low to moderate level of exertion</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Type: isometric and isotonic resistance training</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Multi-joint exercises can also be included as it encourages muscle synergies (coordinate prime mover and stabilizer action)[13]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Should be taught  in rehabilitation and performed in home setting.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Hand therapy:GRASP(graded repetitive arm supplementary program[14][15]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Although this program is only validated in the acute stroke population, this can be beneficial if adapted to patients ability to improve grip strength and general upper functional outcomes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>8 weeks</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Remember to modify and adapt exercise to patient-specific fatigue levels, allow for rest as necessary</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Should be done in home setting.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Examples</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Recommended to do walking with 4-wheeled rollator as this is a most functional activity</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Can be done in rehabilitation or home setting.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>External facilitation to encourage ankle dorsiflexion and plantarflexion as indicated.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parallel bar and body-weight treadmill can be done in rehabilitation setting.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>preformed daily</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For pilates perform 1-2x/wk</paragraph>
    <paragraph>When these exercises are performed at home, make sure that they are performed safely and within the patient’s limit to prevent excessive fatigue</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Can be done in rehabilitation or home setting.</paragraph>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/lnXKSNXpc8U?"/>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/eWoUwvxMi6Y?"/>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>After 12 weeks of physiotherapy sessions, Trish has improved significantly on multiple components of her diagnosis that have impacted her independence the most, such as her strength, range of motion, balance, and gait. She is also experiencing less fatigue in comparison to her initial assessment and can successfully ambulate over 25 minutes before feeling mild fatigue. Trish was assessed at various intervals throughout her treatment to ensure the interventions matched and challenged her function and activity levels. Trish’s progression at the 6-week interval is as follows:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Re-assessment 6-Weeks after Initial Assessment
    <paragraph>Table 5:Outcome Measures at 6-Weeks Re-assessment</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Outcome Measure</th>
        <th>Score</th>
        <th>Interpretation</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>GBS disability score</td>
        <td>2/6</td>
        <td>Able to walk for 5m or more without an aid</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>TUG</td>
        <td>33 seconds</td>
        <td>High risk of falls; requires gait aid</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>BBS</td>
        <td>40/56</td>
        <td>Increased functional balance</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>6-MWT</td>
        <td>307 meters</td>
        <td>Increased distance; improvement in patient’s mobility</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Table 6. Range of motion (ROM) and Manual Muscle Testing (MMT) at 6-Weeks</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th/>
        <th>End of Week 6 Update</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Joint</th>
        <th>AROM (degrees)L/R</th>
        <th>PROM (degrees)L/R</th>
        <th>BilateralMMT score(out of 5)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Metatarsophalangeal joint</th>
        <td>Flexion: 10/8Extension: 15/12</td>
        <td>Flexion: 33/32Extension:84/84</td>
        <td>2+ flexion, 2+ extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Subtalar</th>
        <td>Inversion:  7/10Eversion: 4/4</td>
        <td>Inversion: 34/34Eversion: 14/16</td>
        <td>3 inversion, 3 eversion</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Ankle</th>
        <td>Plantarflexion: 13/ 15Dorsiflexion: 8/7</td>
        <td>Plantarflexion: 47/51Dorsiflexion: 22/24</td>
        <td>3+ plantarflexion, 3+ dorsiflexion</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Knee</th>
        <td>Flexion: 117/ 120Extension: 6/6</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4 flexion, 4 extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Hip</th>
        <td>Flexion: 110/113Extension: 13/14External rotation: 30/42Internal rotation: 25/42Abduction: 39/41Adduction: 25/25</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4 flexion, 4 abduction</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Shoulder</th>
        <td>Flexion: 110/ 123Abduction: 100/ 104External rotation: 57/74Internal Rotation:  64/79</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4+ abduction</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Elbow</th>
        <td>Flexion: 153/153Extension: 0/0</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4+ extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Wrist</th>
        <td>Flexion: 66/69Extension: 57/62</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4 flexion, 4 extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Metacarpophalangeal joint</th>
        <td>Flexion: 65/68Extension: 15/16</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4 flexion, 4 extension</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>L/R</paragraph>
    <paragraph>L/R</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 15/12</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension:84/84</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Eversion: 4/4</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Eversion: 14/16</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Dorsiflexion: 8/7</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Dorsiflexion: 22/24</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 6/6</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 13/14</paragraph>
    <paragraph>External rotation: 30/42</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Internal rotation: 25/42</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Abduction: 39/41</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Adduction: 25/25</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Abduction: 100/ 104</paragraph>
    <paragraph>External rotation: 57/74</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Internal Rotation:  64/79</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 0/0</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 57/62</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 15/16</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Progression of her scores can be attributed to intervention education provided to Trish. She is eager to participate in her rehabilitation (strength, range of motion, and balance interventions) as she believes it will help her return to previous levels of independence and participate in her weekly hobbies. As Table 5. illustrates, Trish’s TUG score has improved significantly (from 40 seconds to 33 seconds, MCID is 3.4 seconds[18]). She also improved in her BBS score and has significantly increased in her 6-MWT (MCID estimated at 54-80 meters[19]). These improvements can be attributed to the parallel bar and body-weight treadmill gait training that was implemented. Trish reports that she sees increases in proficiency as she performs the prescribed muscle strengthening and functional exercises and believes she can return to her previous lifestyle. Trish also reported feeling decreased fatigue after physiotherapy each session. Trish is still advised to continue practicing neuro-proprioception techniques along with imagery to facilitate more ankle dorsiflexion and plantarflexion as part of the home intervention plan. Lastly, Trish reported feeling depressed at the very beginning of her treatment plan. We referred her to a psychologist at this stage to provide psychological support for her and her family and gain motivation to participate in her plan of care[20]. Since then, she reports improvement and is looking forward to advancing to the next stages of her treatment plan.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Re-assessment 12-Weeks after Initial Assessment
    <paragraph>At the end of week 12, a final assessment was taken again. Her results are as follows:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Table 7:Outcome Measures at 12-weeks Re-Assessment</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Outcome Measure</th>
        <th>Score</th>
        <th>Interpretation</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>GBS disability score</td>
        <td>2/6</td>
        <td>Able to walk for 5m or more without an aid</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>TUG</td>
        <td>27 seconds</td>
        <td>Patient still requires gait aid</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>BBS</td>
        <td>46/56</td>
        <td>Decreased risk of falling; functional balance improved</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>6-MWT</td>
        <td>382 meters</td>
        <td>Progression in distance; increase in patient’s mobility</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Table 8. Range of motion (ROM) and Manual Muscle Testing (MMT) at 12-Weeks</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th/>
        <th>End of Week 12</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Joint</th>
        <th>AROM (degrees)L/R</th>
        <th>PROM (degrees)L/R</th>
        <th>BilateralMMT score(out of 5)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Metatarsophalangeal joint</th>
        <td>Flexion: 13 /12Extension: 20/19</td>
        <td>Flexion: 35/35Extension: 86/88</td>
        <td>3 flexion, 3 extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Subtalar</th>
        <td>Inversion: 14 /14Eversion: 8/9</td>
        <td>Inversion: 35/35Eversion: 16/17</td>
        <td>4 inversion, 4 eversion</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Ankle</th>
        <td>Plantarflexion: 21/ 25Dorsiflexion: 11/14</td>
        <td>Plantarflexion: 49/52Dorsiflexion: 24/25</td>
        <td>4- plantarflexion, 4- dorsiflexion</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Knee</th>
        <td>Flexion: 126/132Extension: 3/3</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4+ extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Hip</th>
        <td>Flexion: 117/120Extension: 16/18External rotation: 35/45Internal rotation: 32/45Abduction: 44/46Adduction: 30/31</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4+ abduction</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Shoulder</th>
        <td>Flexion: 105/122Abduction 120/122External rotation: 65/80Internal Rotation:  70/82</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4+ abduction</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Elbow</th>
        <td>Flexion: 157/158Extension: 0/0</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4+ extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Wrist</th>
        <td>Flexion: 70/70Extension: 64/65</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4+ extension</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Metacarpophalangeal joint</th>
        <td>Flexion: 72/73Extension: 20/22</td>
        <td>WNL</td>
        <td>4+ flexion, 4 extension</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>L/R</paragraph>
    <paragraph>L/R</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 20/19</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 86/88</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Eversion: 8/9</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Eversion: 16/17</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Dorsiflexion: 11/14</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Dorsiflexion: 24/25</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 3/3</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 16/18</paragraph>
    <paragraph>External rotation: 35/45</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Internal rotation: 32/45</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Abduction: 44/46</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Adduction: 30/31</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Abduction 120/122</paragraph>
    <paragraph>External rotation: 65/80</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Internal Rotation:  70/82</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 0/0</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 64/65</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Extension: 20/22</paragraph>
    <paragraph>With the help of the body-weight treadmill, Trish is able to practice ambulation and train proper gait motor control in a supported environment. Along with this intervention, she reports increased ankle strength which has allowed her to ambulate more confidently. Trish also has a significantly higher TUG score (from 33 seconds to 27 seconds, MCID is 3.4 seconds[18]). She also gained significant improvements in her BBS overall and significantly improved her walking endurance as shown in the 6-MWT score (MCID 54-80 meters[19]). As illustrated above in Table 8, Trish has overall increased strength and has almost achieved full ROM in her ankle joint. She reports feeling reduced fatigue after physiotherapy sessions in her daily walks and can walk for up to 30 minutes before experiencing fatigue. Her grip strength also increased,  which is reflected in her ability to perform ADLs independently. Lastly, Trish reported feeling positive about her progression in therapy and mentioned feeling more independent when participating in her individual and social activities.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discharge
    <paragraph>Based on the current status of Trish’s progress, we recommend that Trish decrease the frequency of her appointments from weekly sessions to monthly check-ups. In these sessions we will reassess her progress and help her work towards her goal to progress from a 4-wheeled rollator to a quad-cane, if indicated.  Together with an occupational therapist, Trish will find ways to modify her home environment based on her needs[21]. We also recommended that Trish take part inaquatic therapy programs, as it is beneficial for patients with neurological conditions, such as AMAN[22]. Aquatic physical therapy can result in reduced pain, further reduce joint stiffness, promote greater physical function, and increase the quality of life for our patient[23]. We will have ongoing discussions with Trish as well as the interprofessional health team involved in her health.</paragraph>
    <video src="//www.youtube.com/embed/4Lux6l1Z0Rk?"/>
    <paragraph>[24]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Interdisciplinary Team
    <paragraph>Patients with a diagnosis of Acute Motor Axonal Neuropathy (AMAN) require holistic care from a variety of healthcare professionals in order to help optimize patient outcomes. Patients with AMAN can experience lasting motor weakness deficits, which require interdisciplinary rehabilitation approaches to support and facilitate patients in regaining their previous level of functioning and independence. It is important to involve patients and/or family caregivers in their unique care, the decision-making process, as it promotes autonomy and facilitates self-efficacy.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A multidisciplinary healthcare team is needed to effectively manage and treat patients with a diagnosis of AMAN. We have listed different healthcare professionals involved in the treatment and management of patients with AMAN along with their roles. Note, this list is not exhaustive.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Physiotherapist:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Occupational Therapists</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Psychologists</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Neurologist</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Acute Motor Axonal Neuropathy (AMAN) is a variant type of Guillain-Barre syndrome, characterized by acute progressive motor weakness, areflexia, ataxia, oculomotor dysfunction and absence of sensory symptoms[1]. Prognosis for this condition is typically positive, with severe cases continuing to recover movement and function up to four years after their initial diagnosis[3]. Deficits observed in motor function, range of motion, aerobic and muscular endurance, and muscle strength are key factors that continue to limit the quality of life of individuals suffering from AMAN[26].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>In her assessment, Trish presented with many of the listed signs and symptoms, which we measured via outcome measures in accordance with the ICF (such as the GBS disability score and TUG). The outcome measures were used to quantify her initial level of functioning, and as comparable signs to monitor her physiotherapy progress (at 6- and 12- weeks). Initially, Trish’s signs and symptoms led to a decrease in her level of independence and her ability to participate in enjoyable recreational activities such as pilates or bowling, leading in a reduction in her overall quality of life and mental health. Emphasis should be placed on the favourable prognosis of this condition when educating patients, along with highlighting the importance of physical therapy and a treatment approach revolving around functional activity.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Along with patient-stated goals, Trish’s 12-week treatment plan was structured with the ICF framework in mind. Her treatment focused on ROM, muscle strengthening, meaningful functional activities, aerobic exercise, and balance training to reduce her risk of falls. Throughout her engagement with the intervention program Trish demonstrated excellent progress and has become more functionally independent. An increase in her ankle strength (MMT testing) has allowed her to ambulate more confidently, and her ability to effectively counter light external perturbations has reduced her fear of falls. Trish still ambulates around her home and community with a rollator walker, although with notably improved endurance, and has not yet been able to get back to bowling with her friends. Her desire to progress to a cane and return to her husband's workout classes make her an excellent candidate to continue with rehabilitation. Physiotherapy continues to be beneficial as it can provide Trish with more education and functional-focused intervention that can help her achieve her goals. Trish’s previously high levels of physical activity, motivation to return to activity, and continued support from her family are strong indicators that she will continue progressing, ideally to a level where she does not feel limited by her AMAN diagnosis. AMAN patients and those with similar conditions continue to benefit from the expertise of a multidisciplinary team well beyond their diagnosis, to ensure a maximization of their quality of life.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Self Study Questions
    <paragraph>1. Which of the following symptoms is NOT typical of patients with AMAN</paragraph>
    <paragraph>2. The main characteristic differentiating acute motor axonal neuropathy (AMAN) from Guillain-Barre Syndrome (GBS) is</paragraph>
    <paragraph>3. The most effective treatment approach for AMAN focuses on (choose the best answer)</paragraph>
    <paragraph>4. Which of the following is NOT a proposed mechanism of recovery in AMAN?</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.11.2McGrogan A, Madle GC, Seaman HE, De Vries CS.The epidemiology of Guillain-Barré syndrome worldwide. Neuroepidemiology. 2009;32(2):150-63.</item>
      <item>↑Hafer‐Macko C, Hsieh ST, Ho TW, Sheikh K, Cornblath DR, Li CY, McKhann GM, Asbury AK, Griffin JW.Acute motor axonal neuropathy: an antibody‐mediated attack on axolemma. Annals of Neurology: Official Journal of the American Neurological Association and the Child Neurology Society. 1996 Oct;40(4):635-44.</item>
      <item>↑3.03.13.2Gabriel CM.Prognosis in the acute motor axonal form of Guillain–Barré syndrome. Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp; Psychiatry. 2005 May 1;76(5):622-.</item>
      <item>↑Ravikumar S, Poysophon P, Poblete R, Kim-Tenser M.A case of acute motor axonal neuropathy mimicking brain death and review of the literature. Frontiers in Neurology. 2016 Apr 26;7:63.</item>
      <item>↑Hughes RA, Rees JH.Clinical and epidemiologic features of Guillain-Barré syndrome. Journal of Infectious Diseases. 1997 Dec 1;176(Supplement_2):S92-8.</item>
      <item>↑Kuwabara S, Ogawara K, Mizobuchi K, Mori M, Hattori T.Mechanisms of early and late recovery in acute motor axonal neuropathy. Muscle &amp; Nerve: Official Journal of the American Association of Electrodiagnostic Medicine. 2001 Feb;24(2):288-91.</item>
      <item>↑Lefaucheur JP, Gregson NA, Gray I, Von Raison F, Bertocchi M, Creange A.A variant of multifocal motor neuropathy with acute, generalised presentation and persistent conduction blocks. Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp; Psychiatry. 2003 Nov 1;74(11):1555-61.</item>
      <item>↑International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) [Internet]. [cited 2021 May 12]. Available from:https://www.who.int/standards/classifications/international-classification-of-functioning-disability-and-health</item>
      <item>↑Guillain-Barre Syndrome (GBS) (Described Concisely) - YouTube [Internet]. [cited 2021 May 13]. Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7vmZVNmAYf4&amp;ab_channel=PhysioPathoPharmaco</item>
      <item>↑Sanap MN, Worthley LI.Neurologic complications of critical illness: part II. Polyneuropathies and myopathies. Critical Care and Resuscitation: Journal of the Australasian Academy of Critical Care Medicine. 2002 Jun 1;4(2):133-40.</item>
      <item>↑Bensman A. Strenuous exercise may impair muscle function in Guillain-Barré patients. JAMA. 1970;214(3):468–9. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1016/S0003-9993(97)90203-3</item>
      <item>↑GBS/CIDP Foundation International. Guidelines for Physical and Occupational Therapy: Guillain-Barre Syndrome, CIDP and Variants. [Internet]. [Cited May 13, 2021]. Retrieved from:https://www.gbs-cidp.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/Physical-and-Occupational-Therapy-Guidelines.pdf?fbclid=IwAR0YqGCkdr6CClDYaCJmvYoMEr-Iy5f0A-D3chnPQUqDYk5b38mbOH1GCQY</item>
      <item>↑Bassile, Clare C EdD, PT. Guillain-Barré Syndrome and Exercise Guidelines. Neurology Report: Volume 20 - Issue 2 - p 31-36.https://journals.lww.com/jnpt/Citation/1996/20020/Guillain_Barr__Syndrome_and_Exercise_Guidelines.17.aspx</item>
      <item>↑GRASP | Neurorehabilitation Research Program [Internet]. [cited 2021 May 12]. Available from:https://neurorehab.med.ubc.ca/grasp/</item>
      <item>↑15.015.1Virtual GRASP Intro - YouTube [Internet]. [Cited 2021 May 12]. Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lnXKSNXpc8U&amp;ab_channel=GRASPResources</item>
      <item>↑16.016.1Williams N. The Borg Rating of Perceived Exertion (RPE) scale. Occupational Medicine. 2017 Jul 1;67(5):404–5.DOI: 10.1093/occmed/kqx063</item>
      <item>↑17.017.1BWSTT – Biodex Gait TrainerTM 3 + NxStepTM Unweighing System - YouTube [Internet]. [cited 2021 May 13]. Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eWoUwvxMi6Y</item>
      <item>↑18.018.1Gautschi OP, Joswig H, Corniola MV, Smoll NR, Schaller K, Hildebrandt G, Stienen MN.Pre-and postoperative correlation of patient-reported outcome measures with standardized Timed Up and Go (TUG) test results in lumbar degenerative disc disease. Acta neurochirurgica. 2016 Oct;158:1875-81.</item>
      <item>↑19.019.1Wise RA, Brown CD.Minimal clinically important differences in the six-minute walk test and the incremental shuttle walking test. COPD: Journal of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease. 2005 Jan 1;2(1):125-9.</item>
      <item>↑20.020.1Leonhard SE, Mandarakas MR, Gondim FA, Bateman K, Ferreira ML, Cornblath DR, van Doorn PA, Dourado ME, Hughes RA, Islam B, Kusunoki S.Diagnosis and management of Guillain–Barré syndrome in ten steps. Nature Reviews Neurology. 2019 Nov;15(11):671-83.</item>
      <item>↑21.021.1Ko KJ, Ha GC, Kang SJ.Effects of daily living occupational therapy and resistance exercise on the activities of daily living and muscular fitness in Guillain-Barré syndrome: a case study. Journal of Physical Therapy Science. 2017;29(5):950-3.</item>
      <item>↑Kamioka H, Tsutani K, Okuizumi H, Mutoh Y, Ohta M, Handa S, Okada S, Kitayuguchi J, Kamada M, Shiozawa N, Honda T.Effectiveness of aquatic exercise and balneotherapy: a summary of systematic reviews based on randomized controlled trials of water immersion therapies. Journal of epidemiology. 2010 Jan 5;20(1):2-12.</item>
      <item>↑Hinman RS, Heywood SE, Day AR.Aquatic physical therapy for hip and knee osteoarthritis: results of a single-blind randomized controlled trial. Physical therapy. 2007 Jan 1;87(1):32-43.</item>
      <item>↑The Benefits of Hydrotherapy - YouTube [Internet]. [cited 2021 May 13]. Available from:https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Lux6l1Z0Rk</item>
      <item>↑Khan F. Rehabilitation in Guillian Barre syndrome. Australian family physician. 2005 Jan 1;33:1013–7. PMID:15630924</item>
      <item>↑26.026.1Guillain-Barré Syndrome [Internet]. NORD (National Organization for Rare Disorders). 2020 [cited 2021 May 11]. Available from:https://rarediseases.org/rare-diseases/guillain-barre-syndrome/</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
