<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Primary-Progressive Multiple Sclerosis (PPMS) - A Case Study</title>
  <source>nan extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Primary-Progressive_Multiple_Sclerosis_(PPMS)_-_A_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Multiple Sclerosis </parent_folder>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>Purpose:This is a fictional case study designed to understand and explore an individual diagnosed withPrimary Progressive Multiple Sclerosis (PPMS). Additionally, we investigated and applied a research-based treatment approach while integrating the role of technology in rehabilitation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Case Presentation:The case study focuses on Michelle White, a 47year old female who is a work-from-home accountant who recently progressed from active PPMS without progression to active PPMS with progression. Her primary complaints were fatigue, difficulty with a normal gait, impaired balance, weakness, and decreased attention and memory.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Intervention:Mrs. White was prescribed activities and exercises that will maintain and improve her function as her PPMS continues to progress. These interventions were designed to target the patient's short and long-term goals, allowing her to regain and maintain function that has been deemed meaningful to the patient. Treatments prescribed included aerobic exercise, resistance training, balance training, fatigue management, education as well as referrals to target problems that are outside the scope of physiotherapy. Technology was utilized during the patient's rehabilitation in a multitude of ways.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Outcomes:At the 4-month reassessment, the patient was reassessed using the following outcome measures;Multiple SclerosisWalking Scale, 6 Minute Walk, mini BESTest, Activities Balance Confidence Scale, 5 Times Sit to Stand Test, and the Modified Fatigue Impact Scale. After completing her physiotherapy sessions, her home exercise routine, and additional appointments with members of her inter-professional team, the patient was able to improve her abilities and confidence with ambulation, balance, and activities of daily living (ADLs).</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/a/a4/Types_all.gif"/>
    <paragraph>Multiple sclerosis (MS)is a neurological, autoimmune disease that affects the central nervous system.[2]Though the exact aetiology of MS is unknown, it occurs when the immune system attacks nerve fibers and the myelin sheath of neuronal axons, leading to inflammation and demyelination of the central nervous system.[3]As a result, it alters electrical signaling in the brain and leads to a variety of symptoms, such as difficulty with walking, blindness, paralysis, etc.[4]In Canada, over 90,000 people are living with MS, which equates to 1 in every 400 people.[5]Annually, 4,377 Canadians are diagnosed with MS, which equates to almost 12 people per day.[5]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>A thorough medical history in conjunction with a neurological examination and imaging are used to diagnose MS, and it is diagnosed once other potential reasons for symptoms are ruled out.[6]MS can be classified into four types of diagnoses: clinically isolated syndrome, relapsing remitting, secondary progressive and primary progressive.[7]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Primary progressive multiple sclerosis (PPMS) is characterised by a gradual deterioration in functional capacity due to neurological deficits, without the occurrence of early relapses (exacerbation or flare-ups). Furthermore, this type of MS can be categorized as active (confirmed via an occasional relapse and/or imaging) or inactive, as well as progressive (evident decrease in functional capacity) or non-progressive.[8]Globally, 10-15% of individuals diagnosed with MS present with PPMS[3].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This fictional case study will highlight the experience of Michelle White, a 47-year-old female who was diagnosed with PPMS. Michelle was referred to physiotherapy due to an acute exacerbation of PPMS, and her primary goals with rehabilitation are to improve her walking capacity and ability to perform ADLs. The purpose of this case study is to provide evidence-based information from the literature regarding symptoms, objective findings, and interventions for PPMS.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Michelle White is a 47-year-old female (DOB March 14th, 1975) who was diagnosed with PPMS 2 years ago. Since the onset of her symptoms, Mrs. White's status has changed from being in the active without progression PPMS stage (increasing accumulation of disability), to active (new MRI changes) with progression (increasing accumulation of disability). Mrs. White was diagnosed with clinical depression 1 year ago and has been managing hypertension for the last 5 years. Mrs. White is a work-from-home accountant and currently resides in a detached home in Mississauga, Ontario with her husband, 2 children, and a family dog. Mrs. White was referred to rehabilitation by her neurologist to reduce the risk of a relapse, as well as to help improve her mobility (walking with the use of a mobility aid and balance training) and function (activities of daily living).</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Examination Findings
    <paragraph>Initial Assessment:  May 3rd, 2022</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Subjective Assessment
    <paragraph>Chief Complaint:Mrs. White has concerns about taking her dog for daily walks in the summer. She is afraid of losing her balance and worried she won’t have enough energy to complete the walks. Mrs. White is also having trouble with the stairs in her house. She finds her legs weak and she is tired by the time she reaches the top of the stairs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>History of Present Illness:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Past Medical History:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Medications:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Social History:Mrs.White lives in Mississauga in a house with 2 steps to get into the house as well as 12 steps to get to the second floor. She lives there with her husband, 2 children, and a family dog. She has been a work-from-home accountant for the last 15 years. Mrs.White enjoys working from home but has noticed in the last few months that she has trouble concentrating on her work and thinks her memory has gotten worse. Her family recently moved to Mississauga from Ottawa last year, and friends and distant family are still located in Ottawa. Mrs.White enjoys walking her dog daily, reading, and watching movies. However, she finds when she sits in the same position for a long period her pain and discomfort increase.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Family History:History of hypertension on maternal side.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Functional History:Mrs.White was previously able to ambulate for 45 minutes with her dog without the use of a gait aid. She was also less fearful of community ambulation. She previously enjoyed gentle weight-bearing resistance training at her local gym, often going twice a week for about 30-45 minutes. Mrs.White was also able to walk up a flight of stairs without fatigue. She had no problems with her daily activities such as grooming, cleaning, and cooking. However, she found carrying laundry up the stairs quite difficult but often received help from her husband or children.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Current Functional Status:Mrs.White has been cutting back on the length of her workouts at the gym as she now finds resistance training more painful and difficult due to balance impairments. Mrs.White has also become more fearful of community ambulation due to fear of falling, and currently only walks around the block. She walks the dog only twice a week due to her balance and stability deficits and will only go if her husband or one of her children accompanies her. Mrs.White is often fatigued and feels weak after walking up a flight of stairs and is unable to carry her laundry up the stairs anymore. She still manages her daily activities well but finds herself tired if she does a large cleaning of the house.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Patient Goals:</paragraph>
    <list>
      <item>Mrs.White would like to get back to walking her dog 3-4 days a week, independently.</item>
      <item>Mrs.White would also like to limit the progression of her symptoms.</item>
      <item>Mrs.White would like to improve her strength to be able to walk upstairs better.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Objective Assessment
    <paragraph>Range of Motion</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Joint</td>
        <td>Movement</td>
        <td>Active ROM - LEFT</td>
        <td>Passive ROM - LEFT</td>
        <td>Active ROM - RIGHT</td>
        <td>Passive ROM -RIGHT</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip</td>
        <td>Flexion</td>
        <td>100</td>
        <td>105</td>
        <td>90</td>
        <td>100</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip</td>
        <td>Extension</td>
        <td>10</td>
        <td>15</td>
        <td>10</td>
        <td>15</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip</td>
        <td>Adduction</td>
        <td>20</td>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>20</td>
        <td>30</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip</td>
        <td>Abduction</td>
        <td>40</td>
        <td>45</td>
        <td>40</td>
        <td>45</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip</td>
        <td>External Rotation</td>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>40</td>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>40</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip</td>
        <td>Internal Rotation</td>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>40</td>
        <td>30</td>
        <td>40</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee</td>
        <td>Flexion</td>
        <td>125</td>
        <td>130</td>
        <td>115</td>
        <td>125</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee</td>
        <td>Extension</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>-5</td>
        <td>-5</td>
        <td>-5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle</td>
        <td>Plantar flexion</td>
        <td>40</td>
        <td>45</td>
        <td>35</td>
        <td>45</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle</td>
        <td>Dorsiflexion</td>
        <td>10</td>
        <td>15</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>10</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle</td>
        <td>Inversion</td>
        <td>15</td>
        <td>20</td>
        <td>10</td>
        <td>15</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle</td>
        <td>Eversion</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>10</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>10</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Spasticity</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Modified Ashworth Scale[13]</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Muscle Group</td>
        <td>Left Limb</td>
        <td>Right Limb</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Flexors</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Extensors</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Adductors</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Abductors</td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td>0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee Flexors</td>
        <td>1</td>
        <td>1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee Extensors</td>
        <td>1</td>
        <td>1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Plantar Flexors</td>
        <td>1+</td>
        <td>2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Dorsiflexors</td>
        <td>1</td>
        <td>1+</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Strength</paragraph>
    <paragraph>5 Times Sit to Stand Test: 7.3 seconds[14]</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Manual Muscle Testing(MMT)</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Muscle Group</td>
        <td>Left Limb</td>
        <td>Right Limb</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Flexors</td>
        <td>4+</td>
        <td>4+</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Extensors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Adductors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Abductors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>3+</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip External Rotators</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>3+</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Internal Rotators</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>3+</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee Flexors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4-</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee Extensors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4-</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Plantar Flexors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Dorsiflexors</td>
        <td>4-</td>
        <td>3+</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Inverters</td>
        <td>4-</td>
        <td>4-</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>Neurological</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/a/ac/Screen_Shot_2022-05-03_at_9.25.47_PM.png/300px-Screen_Shot_2022-05-03_at_9.25.47_PM.png"/>
    <paragraph>Gait</paragraph>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>Balance</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Assessments:</paragraph>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/f/f9/Screen_Shot_2022-05-03_at_9.39.33_PM.png/300px-Screen_Shot_2022-05-03_at_9.39.33_PM.png"/>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/e/e4/Screen_Shot_2022-05-06_at_9.58.02_AM.png/400px-Screen_Shot_2022-05-06_at_9.58.02_AM.png"/>
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/8/80/Screen_Shot_2022-05-06_at_9.52.01_AM.png/500px-Screen_Shot_2022-05-06_at_9.52.01_AM.png"/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph/>
    <paragraph>Fatigue</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Clinical Impression
    <paragraph>Patient Profile</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mrs. White is a 47-year-old female with PPMS that has been experiencing declining function since her disease progressed to active progression. Currently, Mrs. White is presenting to outpatient rehabilitation with significantly impaired mobility and balance due to lower extremity weakness and spasticity, reduced sensation of the feet, gait deviations, and fatigue. Additionally, Mrs. White is also experiencing urgency incontinence and cognitive deficits that are also impacting her quality of life.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Problems list</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Interventions
    <paragraph>Patient-Centered Treatment Goals</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Short Term Goals:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Long Term Goals:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Strength Training:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Gait Training:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Aerobic Training:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Flexibility Training</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Balance/Neuromotor Training:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Education:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Referrals:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>After Mrs.White's initial assessment on May 3, 2022 she was reassessed on September 4th, 2022,  about 4 months later. She was reassessed using the Multiple Sclerosis Walking Scale, 6 Minute Walk, mini BESTest, Activities Balance Confidence Scale, Modified Fatigue Impact Scale, and 5 times sit to stand. Table #4 below shows the change in each test. Mrs.White's improvement in the Multiple Sclerosis Walking and her 6-minute walk test demonstrates improved ability to walk indicated by increased pace, distance, and decreased effort needed to walk. Mrs.White's improved mini BESTest, Activities Balance Confidence scale, and 5 minutes Sit to Stand demonstrate the positive impact of the interventions on her dynamic balance, functional mobility, and confidence in balance. While completing these tests, Mrs. White experienced less overall fatigue. Mrs. White was able to improve her strength for the major LE muscles indicated by higher scores on MMT. Her ROM for LE did not change</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Outcome Measure</td>
        <td>Initial Assessment: May 3rd, 2022</td>
        <td>Reassessment: September 4th, 2022</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Multiple Sclerosis Walking Scale</td>
        <td>36/60 or 60%</td>
        <td>28/60 or 47%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>6 Minute Walk</td>
        <td>348m</td>
        <td>387m</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Mini BESTest</td>
        <td>11/28</td>
        <td>16/28</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Activities Balance Confidence Scale</td>
        <td>69%</td>
        <td>76%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>5 times sit-to-stand test</td>
        <td>7.3 seconds</td>
        <td>6.9 seconds</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Modified Fatigue Impact Scale</td>
        <td>50/84</td>
        <td>39/84</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>After the 16-week intervention, we are pleased with the progress Mrs.White has made and she will continue treatment as needed or every 6 months. Mrs.White will continue with her home exercise program and understands she is able to contact the clinic if she has any questions or concerns. No further referrals are needed at this time.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Mrs.White has completed her initial assessment with a pelvic floor physiotherapist and will be continued to seek treatment for her urgency incontinence. Mrs.White will continue to have follow-up appointments with other members of her inter-professional care team including her neurologist and general practitioner to follow the progression of her PPMS as well as her psychiatrist to help support her depression.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>Mrs.White is a 47year old female work-from-home accountant who was diagnosed with PPMS 2 years ago. Mrs.White was referred to physiotherapy because her status recently changed from active PPMS without progression to active PPMS with progression. As a result of the progressive demyelination and recently reduced activity level, Mrs.White had been experiencing challenges with normal gait, balance, fatigue, attention, and memory.  These symptoms have been affecting Mrs.White's ability to complete ADLs, work efficiently and participate in physical activity. Mrs.White's goals were to limit the progression of her symptoms, walk her dog 4 days a week and improve her strength to help with ambulation of stairs.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>In her physiotherapy assessment, Mrs.White demonstrated reduced strength and flexibility of her lower extremities, with her right being worse than her left. Her neurological testing was within normal limits with the exception of reduced sensation to her dorsal feet bilaterally and reduced proprioception of the ankle joint bilaterally. Furthermore, Mrs.White displayed moderate balance impairments, fatigue, and gait deviations.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>During her physiotherapy intervention, exercise was directed mostly at gait training, aerobic capacity and lower extremity exercise to target the patient's goals and limitations as best as possible. Functional and isolated resistance training exercises were performed to target both functional activities in order to improve ADL participation as well as improve the patient's widespread lower extremity weakness. Mrs.White was educated about monitoring and reducing the amount of fatigue that she experiences. Balance training was incorporated to improve the patient's stability as well as increase her confidence in her stability. Gait training was incorporated as well in order to improve the patient's function and participation.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>During the 4 month re-assessment, Mrs.White improved her ability to ambulate. She was able to walk further and longer while becoming less fatigued and having more confidence. Mrs.White's balance and strength also improved over the 16-week period. Her progress demonstrated improved scores on the following tests; Multiple Sclerosis Walking Scale, 6 Minute Walk, mini BESTest, Activities Balance Confidence Scale, 5 Times Sit to Stand Test, and the Modified Fatigue Impact Scale.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Individuals withMScan present with a variety of symptoms and impairments, despite this fact, there are many aspects of this current case study that can be applied to the MS population. Firstly, it is important to have a multi-disciplinary team unique to each patient based on the symptoms they are experiencing. In this case, we included a neurologist, a psychiatrist, a pelvic floor physiotherapist, and a pharmacist. Additionally, if available, technology can be used to enhance assessment and treatment. In this case, we used 3Dgaitanalysis to gather detailed information about gait deviations. In regards to treatment,functional electrical stimulationand robot gait training was used to help correct and strengthen the patient's gait pattern. Finally, the current case study demonstrates the importance of physical activity and exercise for patients with MS. Some of the benefits include reduced fatigue, improved mood, increased physical fitness, reduction of depressive symptoms, reduced pain, and improved balance.[31]</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑Types of Multiple Sclerosis.Multiple Sclerosis Association of America. Available from: https://mymsaa.org/ms-information/overview/types/ (accessed May10 2022)</item>
      <item>↑What is multiple sclerosis (MS)?: The Johns Hopkins Multiple Sclerosis Center. 2015. Available from: https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/neurology_neurosurgery/centers_clinics/multiple_sclerosis/conditions/ (accessed May10 2022)</item>
      <item>↑3.03.1Tafti D, Ehsan M, Xixis KL. Multiple Sclerosis. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2022  Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK499849/ ([accessed May10 2022)</item>
      <item>↑What is MS? National Multiple Sclerosis Society. Available from: https://www.nationalmssociety.org/What-is-MS (accessed May10 2022)</item>
      <item>↑5.05.1Latest MS Research News: Prevalence and incidence of MS in Canada and around the world - MS Society of Canada. MS Society. 2020. Available from: https://mssociety.ca/research-news/article/prevalence-and-incidence-of-ms-in-canada-and-around-the-world (accessed May10 2022).</item>
      <item>↑Diagnosis - MS Society of Canada. MS Society.  Available from: https://mssociety.ca/about-ms/diagnosing-ms (accessed May10 2022).</item>
      <item>↑Types of MS. National Multiple Sclerosis Society. Available from: https://www.nationalmssociety.org/What-is-MS/Types-of-MS (accessed May10 2022).</item>
      <item>↑Primary progressive MS (PPMS). National Multiple Sclerosis Society. Available from: https://www.nationalmssociety.org/What-is-MS/Types-of-MS/Primary-progressive-MS (accessed May10 2022).</item>
      <item>↑9.09.19.29.39.4Tsang BK, Macdonell R.Multiple sclerosis: diagnosis, management and prognosis. Australian family physician. 2011 Dec;40(12):948-55.</item>
      <item>↑10.010.110.210.310.410.510.610.7Miller DH, Leary SM.Primary-progressive multiple sclerosis. The Lancet Neurology. 2007 Oct 1;6(10):903-12.</item>
      <item>↑11.011.1Magyari M, Sorensen PS.Comorbidity in multiple sclerosis. Frontiers in Neurology. 2020 Aug 21;11:851.</item>
      <item>↑12.012.112.2Medications. MS Society of Canada. (n.d). Available from https://mssociety.ca/managing-ms/treatments/medications (accessed May10 2022).</item>
      <item>↑Harb A, Kishner S.Modified Ashworth scale. InStatPearls. 2021. StatPearls Publishing.</item>
      <item>↑Five times SIT to stand test. Shirley Ryan AbilityLab. (2013). Available from: https://www.sralab.org/rehabilitation-measures/five-times-sit-stand-test#non-specific-patient-population (accessed May10 2022).</item>
      <item>↑15.015.1Miehm JD, Buonaccorsi J, Lim J, Sato S, Rajala C, Averill J, et al.Sensorimotor function in progressive multiple sclerosis.Multiple Sclerosis Journal–Experimental, Translational and Clinical. 2020 Jul;6(3):2055217320934835.</item>
      <item>↑16.0016.0116.0216.0316.0416.0516.0616.0716.0816.0916.1016.1116.12A RESOURCE FOR HEALTHCARE PROFESSIONALS: Physical Therapy in Multiple Sclerosis. National Multiple Sclerosis Society. 2018. Available from:https://www.nationalmssociety.org/NationalMSSociety/media/MSNationalFiles/Brochures/Clinical_Bulletin_Physical-Therapy-in-MS-Rehabilitation.pdfb(accessed May10 2022).</item>
      <item>↑Wetzel JL, Fry DK, Pfalzer LA.Six-minute walk test for persons with mild or moderate disability from multiple sclerosis: performance and explanatory factors.Physiotherapy Canada. 2011 Apr;63(2):166-80.</item>
      <item>↑Twelve item ms walking scale (MSWS-12). Shirley Ryan AbilityLab. (n.d). Available from: https://www.sralab.org/sites/default/files/2017-07/msws-eng.pdf (accessed May5 2022).</item>
      <item>↑Mini-bestest: Balance Evaluation Systems Test. Oregon health. (n.d). Available from: https://www.sralab.org/sites/default/files/2017-06/MiniBEST_revised_final_3_8_13.pdf (accessed May 9 2022).</item>
      <item>↑Nilsagård Y, Carling A, Forsberg A.Activities-specific balance confidence in people with multiple sclerosis.Multiple sclerosis international. 2012 Aug 7;2012: 613925.</item>
      <item>↑Modified fatigue impact scale (MFIS). Shirley Ryan Abilitylab. (n.d). Available from: https://www.sralab.org/sites/default/files/2017-06/mfis.pdf (accessed May 9 2022)</item>
      <item>↑Multiple sclerosis. NORD (National Organization for Rare Disorders). 2020. Available from: https://rarediseases.org/rare-diseases/multiple-sclerosis/ (accessed May 9 2022)</item>
      <item>↑Spasticity (stiffness). MSAA. 2022. Available from: https://mymsaa.org/ms-information/symptoms/spasticity/ (accessed May 9 2022)</item>
      <item>↑Raad J, Moore J, Hamby J, Rivadelo RL, Straube D.A brief review of the Activities-Specific Balance Confidence Scale in older adults. Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation. 2013 Jul 1;94(7):1426-7.</item>
      <item>↑25.025.125.2Feinstein A, Freeman J, Lo AC.Treatment of progressive multiple sclerosis: what works, what does not, and what is needed. The Lancet Neurology. 2015 Feb 1;14(2):194-207.</item>
      <item>↑26.0026.0126.0226.0326.0426.0526.0626.0726.0826.0926.1026.1126.1226.1326.14Kalb R, Brown TR, Coote S, Costello K, Dalgas U, Garmon E, et al.Exercise and lifestyle physical activity recommendations for people with multiple sclerosis throughout the disease course.Multiple Sclerosis Journal. 2020 Oct;26(12):1459-69.</item>
      <item>↑27.027.1Lo AC, Triche EW.Improving gait in multiple sclerosis using robot-assisted, body weight supported treadmill training. Neurorehabilitation and neural repair. 2008 Nov;22(6):661-71.</item>
      <item>↑Campbell E, Coulter EH, Mattison PG, Miller L, McFadyen A, Paul L.Physiotherapy rehabilitation for people with progressive multiple sclerosis: a systematic review.Archives of physical medicine and rehabilitation. 2016 Jan 1;97(1):141-51.</item>
      <item>↑Beer S, Khan F, Kesselring J.Rehabilitation interventions in multiple sclerosis: an overview. Journal of neurology. 2012 Sep;259(9):1994-2008.</item>
      <item>↑30.030.130.230.3Jackson K, Mulcare JA, Donahoe-Fillmore B, Fritz HI, Rodgers MM.Home balance training intervention for people with multiple sclerosis. International Journal of MS Care. 2007;9(3):111-7.</item>
      <item>↑Motl RW, Sandroff BM.Benefits of exercise training in multiple sclerosis.Current neurology and neuroscience reports. 2015 Sep;15(9):1-9.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
