<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
  <title>Young Adult Cerebral Palsy Fictional Case Study</title>
  <source>Case Study extracted from Physiopedia</source>
  <url>https://www.physio-pedia.com/Young_Adult_Cerebral_Palsy_Fictional_Case_Study</url>
  <parent_folder>Cerebral palsy</parent_folder>
  <section>
    Abstract
    <paragraph>This is a fictional case study of a 21 year old female living withCerebral Palsy(CP). The purpose is to identify out-patient musculoskeletal and neurological rehabilitation in adults living with CP.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Blake was born premature and diagnosed with diplegic spastic CP at the age of 4 which affects her bilateral lower extremities and was classified as a level II on the Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS). She has a medical history ofdepressionandosteoarthritis(OA) and is currently experiencing increased bilateral knee pain, increased difficulty walking, causing her to skip her usual classes at university. She has increasedspasticitywithin her calf and hip flexor muscles as well as diffuse weakness within her lower extremities.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>This case study documents the process from the initial assessment to discharge outlining the patient's goals and treatment plan. This case aims to discuss the limitations and provide evidence for rehabilitation and outcomes for adults living with CP.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Introduction
    <paragraph>Cerebral palsy (CP)arises from damage or malformations to the brain during development and is one of the most common paediatric onset physical disabilities[1][2]. CP can lead to a variety of neurological and neuromuscular alterations which prevent optimal motor function capacity and mechanical loading[1]. It is a non-progressive disorder of posture and movement pathology. It is typically associated with an impairment of the developing fetal brain or infant brain, typically up until 2 years of age. This is typically the age where these malformations occur as the brain is rapidly growing during this time which increases the risk for damage[2]. The prevalence of CP is approximately 2-3 individuals per every 1000, most affecting children but continues into adulthood[2].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>There are many different types of CP, which are often classified in terms of whether it is a unilateral or bilateral disorder, the motor subtype (spastic, dystonia, dyskinesia, etc.), and the severity[2]. Spastic diplegia affects 35% of children diagnosed with CP, making it one of the most common types of CP[3]. This form of CP typically involves muscle stiffness bilaterally in the lower limbs, however, individuals will have normal cognitive function and a good prognosis for independent ambulation[3].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The severity can be categorized by theGross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS), which has been approved and validated for individuals with CP ages 0-18 years at the time of diagnosis[2]. Although it is not validated in adults, it can provide a good indication of what an individual's functional mobility will be like into adulthood. This classification system describes the gross motor function based on self-initiated movement abilities, with level I representing individuals who are most able and level V representing individuals who are most dependent on others for all mobility needs[2].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>There is a lack of research and evidence on CP once individuals reach adulthood. Adults with CP may experience decreased mobility because of a number of factors, including muscle tone, weakness, and pain. Adults with CP have a wide range of abilities from full independence to 24-hour care needed. Although CP is a non-progressive disorder, adults may experience new symptoms and difficulties due to progression of musculoskeletal disorders and comorbidities that are associated with their CP diagnosis. Additionally, young adults with CP, ages 18-30 years old, have been shown to have approximately ten times more of a risk for musculoskeletal conditions than young adults without CP[4]. Some common comorbidities that have been identified in adults with CP are hypertension, depression, epilepsy, osteoarthritis, and many more. There is also a variability in the services for adults with CP and how they are provided, and there is a reduced focus in the healthcare system on the long-term needs of adults with CP[2].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The purpose of this case presentation is to explore the effects of CP on a young adult who is independent, but is experiencing new musculoskeletal symptoms with her CP in adulthood. The case presentation will take place in an outpatient setting and will discuss all necessary components of a comprehensive physiotherapy exam. This case presentation will then discuss the analysis and plan for this individual and will also cover some newer technologies available for CP treatment, and how an interdisciplinary team can be beneficial to treating adults with CP. The overall goal of this case presentation is to bring awareness to CP in adulthood. It will focus on maintaining function while creating new management and treatment strategies for new symptoms that may arise in adulthood.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Client Characteristics
    <paragraph>Blake Parker (she/her) is a 21 year old female who has been diagnosed with CP. She was diagnosed at the age of 4 with diplegic spastic CP affecting her bilateral lower extremities. At the time of her diagnosis, she was classified as a level II on the GMFCS Score. She was born premature and has a past medical history of depression and OA. She was previously able to ambulate without agaitaid and complete all activities of daily living (ADLs) independently. The patient is seeking outpatient physiotherapy as she has been experiencing increased bilateral diffuse knee pain, increased difficulty walking, and has not been attending her university classes due to the pain for the past four weeks.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The pain has progressively gotten worse over the last 4 weeks reaching an 8/10 on theVisual Analogue Scale(VAS) when walking for more than 10 minutes and takes about 20 minutes to come back down to a 2/10 at rest. The patient lives in her two-storey family home with her parents and three sisters in Kingston, Ontario. She is a general arts student at Queen's University and enjoys volunteering at a horse range, exercising with friends, and reading in her free time.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Examination Findings</section>
  <section>Subjective</section>
  <section>
    Objective
    <paragraph>All UE and LE ROM are Within Normal Limits (WNL), except:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>All UE and LE ROM are Within Normal Limits (WNL), except:</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Muscle Group</th>
        <th>Right</th>
        <th>Left</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Abductors</td>
        <td>3+</td>
        <td>3+</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Flexors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Extensors</td>
        <td>3+</td>
        <td>3+</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Hip Adductors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee Flexors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Knee Extensors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Plantar Flexors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Dorsiflexors</td>
        <td>3</td>
        <td>3+</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Invertors</td>
        <td>4</td>
        <td>4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Ankle Evertors</td>
        <td>3</td>
        <td>3+</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome Measures at Baseline
    <paragraph>The VAS as an outcome measure has the strongest reliability and validity for measurement of knee pain caused by OA[5]. Since pain has been shown to be linked to spasticity caused by CP, it is also beneficial to determine the degree of spasticity. It has been shown that thePenn Spasm Frequency Scale(PSFS) has the best association with spasticity-induced pain[6]. It is a self-reported measure that indicates the perception of spasticity for a number of different neurological disorders including CP in adults[6]. The measure looks at the severity and frequency of spasticity[6].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Case Study:</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th/>
        <th>VAS</th>
        <th>PSFS: Spasm Frequency</th>
        <th>PSFS: Spasm Severity</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>At Rest</td>
        <td>2/10</td>
        <td>1/4</td>
        <td>1/3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>After 10 minutes of Walking</td>
        <td>8/10</td>
        <td>3/4</td>
        <td>2/3</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>This outcome measure is commonly used to assess an individual’s walking ability in several cardiovascular and neurological disorders. It is shown to have good reliability[7]and concurrent validity[8]of functional mobility and endurance in adults with CP.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Case Study: 410m</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Pediatric Evaluation of Disability Inventory Computer Adaptive Test (PEDI-CAT):</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The PEDI was revised to a computer adaptive test (CAT) that is intended to be used for adolescents and young adults (up to 21 years old) to assess function and quality of life in a variety of different populations including individuals with CP[9]. The outcome measure looks at daily activities, mobility, social/cognitive abilities, and responsibility and it has a high validity for the daily activity and mobility categories for young adults[9].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Case Study: Daily Activities = 83, Mobility = 81, Social/Cognition = 89</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Analysis Statement/Clinical Impression
    <paragraph>Patient is a 21 y/o female diagnosed with CP presenting with right knee pain that began 4 weeks ago due to OA. Patient has increased tone in bilateral hip flexors and calves that results in decreased dorsiflexion during gait and internal rotation of the ankles. The patient was previously active participating in horseback riding and going to the gym 2-3 times a week. Previously was fully independent in ADLs and ambulated well without a gait aid. Patient is currently able to perform ADLs independently, however, needs to take a break when walking more than 10 minutes due to pain increasing to an 8/10 with activity which takes 20 minutes to come back down to a resting 2/10. The patient is an excellent candidate for physiotherapy treatment aimed at gait training, strengthening, stretching, tone reduction, and education to help decrease pain and increase functional mobility. The patient shows signs for a good prognosis as she was was previously active and independent, is in the acute/sub-acute phase of this exacerbation of her CP symptoms, and has a good support system from friends and family. The patient may also benefit from gait aid use and from referrals for a multidisciplinary team to tackle all of her needs, including returning to school. The patient is at risk of the knee OA continuing to progress, but will benefit from exercises and self management strategies.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Problem List</section>
  <section>Short-Term Goals</section>
  <section>Long-Term Goals</section>
  <section>
    Treatment
    <paragraph>This treatment plan uses theInternational Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF)model by targeting different aspects of her condition that will allow the patient to reach their functional and meaningful goals. It is important to note that there is no single template for CP physiotherapy intervention, as every individual with CP may present differently and needs a personalized approach.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Education
    <paragraph>Educate patient on techniques for using forearm crutches and the importance of using them when needed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Education on performing additional hip flexor stretches after sitting for long periods of time such as after a day of classes or after increased physical activity in addition to the home exercise program (HEP).</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Education on the importance of monitoring fatigue and regressing the HEP if needed.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Referral to occupational therapy will assist in determining modifications that can be made to her environment to decrease barriers in participation and activity.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Stretching
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/2/2c/HEP_CP_Stretches_2023-05-07_at_12.48.56_PM.png/250px-HEP_CP_Stretches_2023-05-07_at_12.48.56_PM.png"/>
    <paragraph>Spasticity of hip flexors and plantar flexors to be targeted with gentle stretching of these muscle groups.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Strengthening
    <image src="https://www.physio-pedia.com/images/thumb/a/af/HEP_CP_Strengthening_2023-05-07_at_1.59.24_PM.png/250px-HEP_CP_Strengthening_2023-05-07_at_1.59.24_PM.png"/>
    <paragraph>Exercises to strengthen hip extensors, hip abductors, and ankle dorsiflexors to counteract spasticity in opposing muscle groups.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Each exercise to be completed for10 repetitions, 3 sets, with a 5 second hold. Exercises to be completed daily, or as tolerated.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Functional Electrical Stimulation (FES)
    <paragraph>Recent research demonstrates that FES can facilitate safe walking and exercise of ‘normal’ movement patterns, increase joint ROM, stimulate muscle strengthening, improve proprioception, and reduce the effects of spasticity in children and young adults with CP[11]. Additionally, research suggests that FES is a more functional way to improve dorsiflexion than using ankle foot orthoses (AFO), because it addresses issues with foot clearance during the swing phase[12]. This is due to the restrictive nature of AFOs, which hold the joint in place rather than working on the strength and movement patterns at the ankle.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Parameters:</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>Gait Training</section>
  <section>Home Exercise Program</section>
  <section>
    Referrals
    <list>
      <item>Occupational Therapists: Individual could benefit from a new gait aid, as well as any additional mobility devices and school adaptations that may be recommended.</item>
      <item>Psychologist: Individual has been diagnosed with depression and could benefit from a therapy intervention to help with mental health challenges.</item>
      <item>Massage Therapist: Patient displays muscle spasticity and could benefit from massage therapy to assist with pain and tone.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    Technology-Based Treatment
    <paragraph>Robotics Assisted Gait Training (RAGT) uses a robotic exoskeleton to help individuals normalize their gait pattern. It is a safe and effective option for improving motor performance when used with conventional therapies in a rehabilitation setting[13]. RAGT benefits the CP population because it allows them to be physically active and maintain their physical performance to help prevent the development of comorbidities[13]. However, the exoskeleton is a new technology and requires further investigations before conclusions can be drawn on its efficacy for gait training[14].</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For additional information on robotic rehabilitation, head over to:Robotic Rehabilitation for the Lower Extremity</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Outcome
    <paragraph>Following the initial consult, the physiotherapy team continued to see Blake 2 times per week for 6 weeks to continue to help improve her symptoms and increase her functional status.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Blake has met all short and long-term goals. After the 6 weeks, Blake has increased strength in hip extensors, hip abductors, and ankle dorsiflexors. She has been able to consistently walk 20 minutes with decreased pain and is now attending her University classes 3 days a week.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>In addition to meeting her goals, we saw a decrease in overall pain, reduced muscle tone, and increased ROM into dorsiflexion bilaterally. We have observed Blake using her forearm crutches efficiently, which has created a longer stride length and allowed her to offload her knee during long periods of walking. She has demonstrated a proper understanding of when to use her forearm crutches and the importance of using them when needed. Blake has also been following our recommendations to perform additional hip flexor stretches after an extended period of time sitting in class or after a day of increased physical activity.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>AROM:Ankle dorsiflexion: neutral (0 degrees), Knee flexion: 110 degrees. All other ROM remained unchanged from her initial assessment.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>MMT:Hip extensors, hip abductors, and ankle dorsiflexors all increased to a 4/5</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Tone:</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Pain:</paragraph>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th/>
        <th>VAS</th>
        <th>PSFS: Spasm Frequency</th>
        <th>PSFS: Spasm Severity</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>At Rest</td>
        <td>1/10</td>
        <td>1/4</td>
        <td>1/3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>After 10 minutes of Walking</td>
        <td>3/10</td>
        <td>1/4</td>
        <td>1/3</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <paragraph>6-Minute Walk Test:550 m</paragraph>
    <paragraph>PEDI-CAT:Daily Activities = 90, Mobility = 88, Social/Cognition = 89</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Her discharge plan includes keeping up with her HEP for 2-3 additional months, as well as providing education and information for additional referrals. She has been referred to OT, massage therapy, and a psychologist. She has received accommodations for school that allow her to attend 3 days a week while doing the other 2 days online. Additionally, she has been granted additional time between classes so she does not have to rush when walking across campus. She has been advised to reach out to the physiotherapy team if she requires any additional questions or concerns. Patient has been discharged at this time.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    Discussion
    <paragraph>The treatment approach for this patient was focused on treating and managing the acute knee pain and OA, while taking a holistic approach that considered how the CP diagnosis affected the function of her lower extremities and entire body. Studies show that adults with CP have an increased risk of developing osteoporosis and OA, so it is likely that young adults with CP may present with similar symptoms to Blake’s case[15].OAis a degenerative joint disease that has an increased prevalence in the adult CP population compared to adults without CP[15]. OA can cause functional limitations because of joint pain, which can decrease an individual's ability to perform physical activity. A common treatment for OA is surgery. Individuals with CP who have had surgery to treat their OA were found to have a significant reduction in pain[16]. Despite the effectiveness of surgery for OA in the CP population, surgeons are reluctant to operate due to the increased risk of dislocation and prosthetic failure[16]. This and Blake's young age was the rationale for treating Blake's OA conservatively with physiotherapy that included gait and gait aid training, FES, and stretching and strengthening exercises. Although the prevalence of OA in the CP population is high, there remains a lack of evidence on the most effective forms of rehabilitative treatment[15]. It is important that further research is conducted in individuals with CP and OA due to the high prevalence, and so healthcare professionals know how to modify treatments and assessments when considering coexisting conditions.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The physiotherapy treatment plan was based on Blake’s short-term and long-term goals of increasing strength, reducing pain when walking, and returning to in-person classes. One focus of the physiotherapy plan was teaching Blake how to ambulate with her forearm crutches, which have been shown to reduce the body load on the legs for individuals with CP[10]. The crutches were introduced as a compensatory management strategy to reduce load on Blake’s knee joints and to help her achieve independence when walking on campus. Studies have also shown that functional gait training and FES can be effective to improve walking speed and gross motor function for young adults with CP[17]. Incorporating FES during gait training in the exercise plan would likely help Blake to achieve her goals.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The life expectancy of individuals who are diagnosed with CP depends on the severity of the condition[18]. In this case, Blake was diagnosed with level II on theCMFCSindicating mild impairments. Blake’s diagnosis should therefore not decrease her life expectancy. There are many resources and programs that can be found throughCan ChildandCerebral Palsy Canada, but they are more focused towards children with CP, rather than adults. Individuals diagnosed with CP will require treatments and accommodations throughout their life. It is important to continue conducting research with adult CP populations, so that healthcare professionals can provide the best evidence-based treatment for concerns occurring later in these patients' lives. This fictional case highlighted the early onset of OA that individuals with CP often experience due to the abnormal joint movements, greater stress concentration at the joints, and the increased tone of muscles surrounding the joints[19]. Each person with CP will require an individualized treatment plan, with physiotherapists, occupational therapists, and massage therapists being vital to help individuals with CP manage their condition and be as independent as possible for as long as possible.</paragraph>
  </section>
  <section>
    References
    <list>
      <item>↑1.01.1Whitney DG, Alford AI, Devlin MJ, Caird MS, Hurvitz EA, Peterson MD. Adults with cerebral palsy have higher prevalence of fracture compared with adults without cerebral palsy independent of osteoporosis and cardiometabolic diseases. Journal of Bone and Mineral Research. 2019;34(7):1240–7.doi: 10.1002/jbmr.3694</item>
      <item>↑2.02.12.22.32.42.52.6Bromham N, Dworzynski K, Eunson P, Fairhurst C. Cerebral palsy in adults: Summary of NICE guidance. BMJ (Online). 2019;364:l806-06.doi: https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.l806</item>
      <item>↑3.03.1Patel DR, Neelakantan M, Pandher K, Merrick J. Cerebral palsy in children: A clinical overview. Translational pediatrics. 2020;9(Suppl 1):S125–S135.doi: 10.21037/tp.2020.01.01</item>
      <item>↑Whitney DG, Kamdar NS. Development of a new comorbidity index for adults with cerebral palsy and comparative assessment with common comorbidity indices. Developmental Medicine and Child Neurology. 2021;63(3):313–9.doi: 10.1111/dmcn.14759</item>
      <item>↑Alghadir AH, Anwer S, Iqbal A, Iqbal ZA. Test-retest reliability, validity, and minimum detectable change of visual analog, numerical rating, and verbal rating scales for measurement of osteoarthritic knee pain. J Pain Res. 2018 Apr 26;11:851-856. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S15884.doi: 10.2147/JPR.S158847</item>
      <item>↑6.06.16.2Flanigan M, Gaebler-Spira D, Kocherginsky M, Garrett A, Marciniak C. Spasticity and pain in adults with cerebral palsy. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2020 Mar;62(3):379-385.doi: 10.1111/dmcn.14368.</item>
      <item>↑Andersson C, Asztalos L, Mattsson E. Six-minute walk test in adults with cerebral palsy. A study of reliability. Clin Rehabil. 2006 Jun;20(6):488-95.doi: 10.1191/0269215506cr964oa.</item>
      <item>↑Maltais DB, Robitaille NM, Dumas F, Boucher N, Richards CL. Measuring steady-state oxygen uptake during the 6-min walk test in adults with cerebral palsy: feasibility and construct validity. Int J Rehabil Res. 2012 Jun;35(2):181-3.doi: 10.1097/MRR.0b013e3283527792.</item>
      <item>↑9.09.1Amaral MF, Sampaio RF, Coster WJ, Souza MP, Mancini MC. Functioning of young patients with cerebral palsy: Rasch analysis of the pediatric evaluation of disability inventory computer adaptive test daily activity and mobility. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2020 Nov 18;18(1):369.doi: 10.1186/s12955-020-01624-5.</item>
      <item>↑10.010.1Krautwurst B, Dreher T, Wolf S. The impact of walking devices on kinematics in patients with spastic bilateral cerebral palsy. Gait &amp; Posture. 2016 May;46, 184–187.doi:10.1016/j.gaitpost.2016.03.014</item>
      <item>↑Singleton C, Jones H, Maycock L. Functional electrical stimulation (FES) for children and young people with cerebral palsy. Pediatrics and Child Health. 2019 Nov;29(11):498-502.doi:10.1016/j.paed.2019.07.015</item>
      <item>↑Prosser L, Curatalo L, Alter K, Damiano D. Acceptability and potential effectiveness of a foot drop stimulator in children and adolescents with cerebral palsy. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2012 Nov;54(11):1044-9.doi:10.1111/j.1469-8749.2012.04401.x</item>
      <item>↑13.013.1Digiacomo F, Tamburin S, Tebaldi S, Pezzani M, Tagliafierro M, Casale R, et al. Improvement of motor performance in children with cerebral palsy treated with exoskeleton robotic training: A retrospective explorative analysis. Restorative neurology and neuroscience. 2019;37(3):239–44.doi: 10.3233/RNN-180897</item>
      <item>↑Cumplido C, Delgado E, Ramos J, Puyuelo G, Garcés E, Destarac MA, et al. Gait-assisted exoskeletons for children with cerebral palsy or spinal muscular atrophy: A systematic review. NeuroRehabilitation (Reading, Mass). 2021;49(3):333–48.doi: 10.3233/NRE-210135</item>
      <item>↑15.015.115.2O’Connell NE, Smith KJ, Peterson MD, Ryan N, Liverani S, Anokye N, et al. Incidence of osteoarthritis, osteoporosis and inflammatory musculoskeletal diseases in adults with cerebral palsy: A population-based cohort study. Bone (New York, NY). 2019;125:30–5.</item>
      <item>↑16.016.1Houdek MT, Watts CD, Wyles CC, Trousdale RT, Milbrandt TA, Taunton MJ. Total Hip Arthroplasty in Patients with Cerebral Palsy: A Cohort Study Matched to Patients with Osteoarthritis. Journal of bone and joint surgery American volume. 2017;99(6):488–93.</item>
      <item>↑Booth ATC., Buizer AI, Meyns P, Oude Lansink ILB, Steenbrink F, van der Krogt MM. The efficacy of functional gait training in children and young adults with cerebral palsy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Developmental Medicine &amp; Child Neurology. 2018 Sep;60(9):866-83.https://doi-org.proxy.queensu.ca/10.1111/dmcn.13708</item>
      <item>↑Blair E, Langdon K, McIntyre S, Lawrence D, Watson L. Survival and mortality in cerebral palsy: observations to the sixth decade from a data linkage study of a total population register and National Death Index. BMC Neurol. 2019 Jun 4;19(1):111.doi: 10.1186/s12883-019-1343-1.</item>
      <item>↑Carter DR, Tse B. The pathogenesis of osteoarthritis in cerebral palsy. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2009 Oct;51 Suppl 4:79-83.doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8749.2009.03435</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</document>
